<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Account of Proceedings in Parliament</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="VA">
                    <name>Victoria Anker</name>
                    <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="HBy">
               <name>Helen Busby</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BS">
               <name>Beth Southard</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/NorfRO_HMN_7307_772X8.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="NorfRO_HMN_7307_772x8">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>Norwich</settlement>
               <repository>Norfolk Record Office</repository>
               <collection/>
               <idno>HMN 7/307, 772X8</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">Norfolk Record Office,  HMN 7/307, 772X8</p>
            </msDesc>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1628">1628</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term>parliament</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-09-24" who="#RB" status="drafted"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#HBy" status="transcribed"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#BS" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="176r" facs="/nro/hmn_7-308/hmn_7-308-002/hmn_7-308-002.jpg"/>
         <head>
            At <ex>th</ex>e Parl<ex>iament</ex> begun Jan<ex>uary</ex> <ex>th</ex>e <hi rend="underline">1628</hi>
         </head>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               J<supplied>a</supplied>n 21
            </add>
            <del rend="strikethrough">The first thing insisted vpon was what Innovations</del> <lb/>
            Their first walk into publiq<ex>e</ex> affairs was <del rend="strikethrough">to be</del> like good husbands to see if ther <lb/>
            fences were firme for the Last P<ex>arliament</ex> having made a gallant hedge between <lb/>
            Royal Prerog<ex>ative</ex> &amp; Pop<ex>ular</ex> Liberty their first care was to see <del rend="strikethrough">wheth</del> what incroach <lb/>
            ments had been made vpon it &amp; appointed  a Com<ex>m</ex>ittee to to view the scathes <lb/>
            who gave account that not onely several irruptions and gapps had been <lb/>
            made therein but also that it had been new printed with such an additio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            as <del rend="strikethrough">was dis</del> would gangrene the hole masse if not prevented.  This inquisi=<lb break="no"/>
            tion taking notice of the vndue <del rend="strikethrough">enfer</del> extorting Ton<ex>n</ex>age &amp; Poundage vrged his <lb/>
            M<ex>ajesty</ex> to declare himself to the house Jun<ex>e</ex> 24 that those levyes were not <lb/>
            made as filing them vp vpon the score of his just Rights but onely as the <lb/>
            products of his instant exigents disavowing vtterly any legal capa-<lb break="no"/>
            city in him to impose them without Parl<ex>iament</ex> concessio<ex>n</ex> &amp; withal desiring <lb/>
            they would <unclear>hush</unclear> all <unclear>dolates</unclear> relating <add place="above">to</add> them by a <unclear>present condescension</unclear> <lb/>
            and that since he had disclaimed the right it might be a motive to obs <lb/>
            teme the favour. Their next walke was into Religion which was p<ex>re</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            sented <del rend="strikethrough">obst</del> in a very lapsing &amp; tottering condition that Popery <lb/>
            while the lawes were layd to sleep began to repullulate &amp; grow a <lb/>
            fresh That Papists were not onely tolerated but countenanced <lb/>
            &amp; graced That Armmianisme which is but parboyld Popery <lb/>
            began to domineere notwithstanding it was declared against by <lb/>
            the Lambeth Articles which were sent by K<ex>ing</ex> James to the Synod of <lb/>
            Dort and to Ireland as the doctrine of <ex>th</ex>e Church of England <lb/>
            that the faitors of that ipinion rode safe vnder the lee of Royal <lb/>
            favour, wheras <ex>th</ex>e sound and <unclear>oathedon</unclear> were vnder inglorious disdein <lb/>
            the Constat of this was that Mr Montague a man complained against in <lb/>
            open P<ex>arliament</ex> was not withstanding <add place="above">by the sollicitasio<ex>n</ex> of <unclear>nol</unclear>
                </add> both pardoned his preceding errour, but <lb/>
            advanced fines to the see of Chichester. And that Dr Mannering who <lb/>
            was sensured also for high misdomeanours had reingratiated himself <lb/>
            and obteined his Pardon &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">that there</del>
         </p>
         <p>
            For Constat of Recusants p<ex>re</ex>vailing it was proved <del rend="strikethrough">that</del> <lb/>
            That in D<del rend="strikethrough">ublin</del> <ex>th</ex>e City of Dublin there were lately erected 13 houses <lb/>
            (peculiar to Jesuites &amp; Friers) more in number then there are Protestant <lb/>
            Churches.
         </p>
         <p>
            That in Scotland they have lately been very insolent &amp; turbulent
         </p>
         <p>
            That in <add place="above">some countyes of</add> England they are multiplyd to the product some thousands of <lb/>
            families now then in Q<ex>ueen</ex> El<ex>izabeth</ex> her time
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               Putet by their m<ex>ar</ex>k <lb/>
               &amp; c.
            </add>
            That in Clarkenwel there was a discovery of a Colledge of <del rend="strikethrough">iu</del> Jesui <lb/>
            tes &amp; Preists whereof 10 were apprehended &amp; 3 were endited for Preists <lb/>
            <add place="above">(<unclear>and the rest of Preminm<ex>en</ex>t</unclear>)</add> whereof one was condemned and though direct treason was proved <lb/>
            against them &amp; one condemned yet the night before Excecution he <lb/>
            was repreived by <add place="above">warrant</add> <del rend="strikethrough">th Order</del> from the (<del rend="strikethrough">R<unclear>???</unclear> who <unclear>???</unclear> an order for</del> <add place="above">Lord Ch<ex>ief</ex> Iustice hide who said he</add> <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">the Council table</del> did it by order fro<ex>m</ex> his Maj<ex>es</ex>ty
         </p>
         <p>
            The maine breach into <ex>th</ex>e Subjects Liberty was by divers Customers <lb/>
            who seased several M<ex>e</ex>rchants goods for Ton<ex>n</ex>age &amp; p<ex>oun</ex>dage vpon which the <lb/>
            Custom<ex>e</ex>rs were questioned and the K<ex>ing</ex> resigned vp the interest in them <lb/>
            other ways then of free gift (though his warrant for the <unclear>???</unclear> of the <lb/>
            sayes <unclear/> expressly they are a Principal Revenue of o<ex>u</ex>r crown) but to <lb/>
            indemnify the Customers who he avowed acted onely by his com<ex>m</ex>and <lb/>
            he requested the Parl<ex>iament</ex> woud compare the difference by some expedi-<lb break="no"/>
            ent of honour to him and saftey to them. But the house stood so <lb/>
            stiff to the maintenance of their own rights as K<ex>ing</ex> much <unclear>incensed</unclear> <lb/>
            wished to <del rend="strikethrough">aj</del> adjorn.
         </p>
         <pb n="176v" facs="/nro/hmn_7-308/hmn_7-308-003/hmn_7-308-003.jpg"/>
         <p>
            In religion they complained of several abuses <del rend="strikethrough">Great complaints being exhibeted</del> <add place="above">some relating to</add> <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">against the spreading</del> 1. <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> Arminianisme then <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> Popery. For Arminianisme <lb/>
            it was complained that not withstanding the Resolution of the ArchBis<ex>hop</ex> of <lb/>
            C<ex>anterbury</ex> &amp; other Reverend &amp; learned <del rend="strikethrough">princes</del> Byshops &amp; divines assembled at Lambeth <lb/>
            1595 on purpose to declare their opinions concerning the some of the 39 <lb/>
            Articles in those Particulars vnto which <del rend="strikethrough">Articles</del> the ArchB<ex>ishop</ex> of York &amp; all <lb/>
            his Prov<ex>ince</ex> did agree. , <del rend="strikethrough">That notwithstanding</del> the suffrage of our Brition <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">Divines sent by K<ex>ing</ex> J<ex>ames</ex> to the Synod at Dort. And published by com<ex>m</ex>and <lb/>
            That notwithstandin</del> the / That notwithstanding those Articles of Lambeth <lb/>
            were sent <add place="above">by K<ex>ing</ex> James first</add> to the Synod at Dort <del rend="strikethrough">by King James</del> as the Doctrine of our <lb/>
            ch<ex>urch</ex> and <del rend="strikethrough">there</del> asserted by <add place="above">the suffrage of</add> our British divines, And again to the Convoca-<lb break="no"/>
            tion in Ireland there to be inserted amongst the Articles of the Religion <lb/>
            establist there. That notwithstanding several <del rend="strikethrough">de</del> Recantations <lb/>
            Censures formaly enjoyned and inflicted vpon the spreaders of that <lb/>
            doctrine yet the maintainers of these points did dare to publish both <lb/>
            by the presse &amp; pulpit their <unclear>tenets</unclear>  <del rend="strikethrough">P</del> <add place="above">2</add>/ they were not onely sheltered <lb/>
            under the Lee of Royal favour but by the power &amp; prevalence of the <lb/>
            Byshops of Winchester &amp; London advanced /1/ <add place="above">some</add> <del rend="strikethrough">they were pardoned</del> formerly <lb/>
            censured in open Parliament as Mountague Cozen, Manwaring, &amp; Sibthorpe <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">were</del> <add place="above">had</add> by the procuremeant <add place="above">&amp; <unclear>collinitative</unclear>
                </add> of Note Bysh<ex>op</ex> of Winch<ex>ester</ex> &amp; the Earle of Dorcest <lb/>
            obtenied their pardons under the great Seal <del rend="strikethrough">and others were</del> <add place="above">and those very men with others</add> not only &amp;c. <lb/>
            to the great disanimation of the tru p<ex>ro</ex>fesors. The Complaints referring to <lb/>
            <add place="above">Oblique</add> Popery were <add place="above">
                    <del rend="strikethrough">judacises</del>
                </add> <del rend="strikethrough">the obtruting of</del> the uncontrouled preaching of several points <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">thereof</del> <add place="above">warninge; that was</add> by Mountague, Cozens &amp; <ex>th</ex>e B<ex>ishop</ex> of Gloucester, the <unclear>endeviour</unclear> obtru=<lb break="no"/>
            ding of divers superstitious ceremonies by the Prelates as warring of <lb/>
            Altars and placing the holy table Altarwise the <unclear>
                    <del rend="strikethrough">L___ing</del> <add place="above">dopping</add> &amp; cringing</unclear> towards <lb/>
            it the standing up at Gloria Patri things not enjoyned <add place="above">by</add> any authoritqe <lb/>
            act of State
         </p>
         <p>
            Relating to Popery direct. The extraordinary fructification <add place="above">both in Ireland and Engl<ex>and</ex>
                </add> thereof, that in <lb/>
            Dublin the <del rend="strikethrough">chri</del> Metroperlis of Ireland where lately all resorted to Church <lb/>
            now there were erected more houses for Masse preists &amp; Friers to officiat <lb/>
            in than there were Parochial churches, that in some Counties of Engl<ex>and</ex> <lb/>
            where there were few or none during Q<ex>ueen</ex> Eliz<ex>abeth</ex> her time there were now <lb/>
            above 2000. That <del rend="strikethrough">they</del> there was a Colledge of Jesuits erected at Clerk-<lb break="no"/>
            enwell who had there a Chappell and Library and other Roomes of necessaary <lb/>
            accomodation with <add place="above">houshold</add> vtensills <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> marked with <unclear>+ S</unclear>. and <add place="above">as</add> by their bookes of <lb/>
            accoumpt appeared had in revenue 300l <unclear>&amp;</unclear> an allowed them by <add place="above">the subscription if</add> diverse <lb/>
            Recusants <del rend="strikethrough">subscribers</del> That 10 of these were apprehended and indited <lb/>
            3 of Treason the rest of <unclear>Pre???</unclear> And that although plain treason was <lb/>
            Proved against them at the Sessions yet by the artiface of the <add place="above">2</add> L<ex>ord</ex> chief <lb/>
            Justices Hide &amp; Richard <add place="above">suppassing our Kings evedence</add> nothing was done against <add place="above">them</add>, onely one was con-<lb break="no"/>
            demned and the day before Execution was repreived by a warrant <lb/>
            from th<ex>e</ex> Ch<ex>ief</ex> Justice Hide: That the <del rend="strikethrough">great</del> resort to <unclear>M???</unclear> at Som<ex>erset</ex> house <lb/>
            was so great so frequent so openly connived at and the penal<add place="above">ity if</add> <unclear>state???</unclear> <lb/>
            through his M<ex>ajesty</ex> if over great indulgence so dispenced with as amounted in <lb/>
            <add place="above">the</add> <del rend="strikethrough">able</del> totel to litle lesse then in toleratio<ex>n</ex>.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               virtue onely <del rend="strikethrough">quan</del> quantifyes nobility and gives it its dimensions <lb/>
               A lea<ex>r</ex>nd man but no good scholler <lb/>
               <unclear>???</unclear>
            </add>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/nro/hmn_7-308/hmn_7-308-002/hmn_7-308-002.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/nro/hmn_7-308/hmn_7-308-003/hmn_7-308-003.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>