<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advices and Motives for Soliciting Catholics</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="VA">
                    <name>Victoria Anker</name>
                    <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="HB">
               <name>Howard Barlow</name>
               <resp>BRIHC Research Assistant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TW">
               <name>Tim Wales</name>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLHarleyMS4931.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Harley_MS_4931">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Harley</collection>
                <idno>MS 4931</idno>
                <msName/>
             </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Harley MS 4931</p>
            </msDesc>
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_11045">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <repository>British Library</repository>
               <collection>Additional</collection>
               <idno>MS 11045</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="All_Souls_College_MS_181">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
               <repository>All Souls College</repository>
               <collection/>
               <idno>MS 181</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Harley_MS_5108">
                    <country>United Kingdom</country>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Harley</collection>
                    <idno>MS 5108</idno>
                    <msName/>
                </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="John_Rylands_Eng_MS_737">
                    <country>United Kingdom</country>
                    <settlement>Manchester</settlement>
                    <repository>John Rylands Library</repository>
                    <collection>Eng</collection>
                    <idno>MS 737</idno>
                    <msName/>
                </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated">
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/All_Souls_College_MS_181.xml">All Souls College,  MS 181, ff. 201r–209v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHarleyMS5108.xml">British Library, Harley MS 5108, ff. 131r–136v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Carte_77.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Carte 77, ff. 478r–482r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            
            <listBibl xml:id="modern_print_witness">
               <bibl>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Rushworth</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <title>Historical Collections</title>
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1721">1721</date>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="820" to="822">820-822</biblScope>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Nalson</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <title>Impartiall Collection of the Great Affairs of State</title>
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1682" from="1682" to="1683">1682-1683</date>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="741" to="744">741-744</biblScope>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1639-04-04">4 April 1639</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term>advice</term>
               <term>instructions</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term>Catholics</term>
               <term>state finance</term>
               <term>revenue</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-09-28" who="#TW" status="proofread"/>
            <change when="2018-01-23" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2018-01" who="#HB" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         
         <pb n="31r" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f031r/harley_ms_4931_f031r.jpg"/>
         <head rend="indent">
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="underline">
                  Anno <add place="above">1638 et</add> 1639
               </hi>
            </add>
            Advices, and Motiues for the Noblemen, Knights, <lb/>
            and Gentlemen, that shall imploy <ex>the</ex>mselues in <ex>th</ex>e Country <lb/>
            in sollicitting Catholiques for a Contribution to his <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty, upon occasion of his pr<ex>ese</ex>nt Northern Iorney.
         </head>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">1</add>It is fitt yo<ex>u</ex> repr<ex>e</ex>sent to <ex>th</ex>os we treate w<ex>i</ex>th, the extraordinary graces, &amp; <lb/>
            protections wee owe to the Queenes Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty, And <ex>tha</ex>t to her favourable inter-<lb break="no"/>
            cessions meeting w<ex>i</ex>th the Kings Clemency, we must ascribe the happy modera-<lb break="no"/>
            tion we liue in under him. Thereby to make <ex>the</ex>m apprehend How fitt, or rather <lb/>
            How iust, and necessary a duty it is in us to lay hold on the first occasion, <lb/>
            thereby to express o<ex>u</ex>r bounden gratitude to both their Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">2</add>Then yo<ex>u</ex> may bring into y<ex>ou</ex>r considerac<ex>i</ex>on how much is importeth <ex>th</ex>e Kings ser-<lb break="no"/>
            vice to be assisted w<ex>i</ex>th extraordinary contribuc<ex>i</ex>ons of Moneyes upon this extraor-<lb break="no"/>
            dinary, &amp; chargable occasion of going into <ex>th</ex>e Northerne parts w<ex>i</ex>th an Army. <lb/>
            And <ex>tha</ex>t accordingly all well-affected Persons doe so, as is euident by <ex>th</ex>e contributions <lb/>
            of many particular Persons. Besides <ex>th</ex>os of <ex>th</ex>e body of <ex>th</ex>e Lawyers, of <ex>th</ex>e Iudges, of <lb/>
            the City, and severall other parts.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">3</add>You may tell <ex>tha</ex>t besides the g<ex>e</ex>n<ex>e</ex>rall Motiues <ex>tha</ex>t p<ex>er</ex>swade every well-affected p<ex>er</ex>son to <lb/>
            giue liberally upon this occasion, Catholiques haue other p<ex>ar</ex>ticular pressing ones, as <lb/>
            Their owne private Interest, And likewise the Queenes earnest reco<ex>m</ex>mendac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of this action in general to all Catholiques throughout England; w<ex>hi</ex>ch to make <lb/>
            <ex>the</ex>m rightly to conceiue, it will be necessary <ex>tha</ex>t yo<ex>u</ex> informe <ex>the</ex>m Of <ex>th</ex>e p<ex>ar</ex>ticulars of her <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes reco<ex>m</ex>mendac<ex>i</ex>ons, w<ex>hi</ex>ch are,
         </p>
         <p>
            That her Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty hath so much taken to heart to haue a considerable Sum<ex>m</ex>e <lb/>
            raised by this contribution, as shee hath beene graciously pleased to reco<ex>m</ex>mend <lb/>
            it efficaciously to all <ex>th</ex>e Catholick L<ex>or</ex>ds about London, &amp; to <ex>th</ex>e chiefe p<ex>er</ex>sons <lb/>
            of eminency <ex>tha</ex>t her express Co<ex>m</ex>mands could find out both to be Contributers, &amp; <lb/>
            Sollicitors in it, And to the several Superiors of the Cleargy, &amp; Religious Or-<lb break="no"/>
            ders to promote it all they can, both by their owne negociac<ex>i</ex>ons, &amp; p<ex>er</ex>swasions, &amp; <lb/>
            by the like Offices of all <ex>th</ex>os who do depend on <ex>the</ex>m. And lastly <ex>tha</ex>t her Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty hath <lb/>
            co<ex>m</ex>manded all <ex>th</ex>os, <ex>tha</ex>t by their aboads about this Towne haue had the honor to <lb/>
            receive her gracious directions im<ex>m</ex>ediatly from herselfe, to signify w<ex>i</ex>th all speede <lb/>
            to the eminentest p<ex>er</ex>sons in every Country, <ex>tha</ex>t they may <ex>the</ex>n doe <ex>th</ex>e like to all <lb/>
            the p<ex>ar</ex>ticular Catholiques w<ex>i</ex>thin their Neighbourhood, &amp; knowledge.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">4</add>That in the pursuance of this co<ex>m</ex>mand from her Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty, all the p<ex>er</ex>sons mett to-<lb break="no"/>
            gether here in London, sc<ex>ilicet</ex> <ex>th</ex>e L<ex>or</ex>ds, Superiors of <ex>th</ex>e Cleargy, &amp; Religious Orders, <lb/>
            &amp; <ex>th</ex>e Knights, &amp; Gent<ex>lemen</ex> have all of <ex>the</ex>m agreed upon those Motiues, &amp; Advices, <lb/>
            &amp; upon the p<ex>er</ex>sons to w<ex>ho</ex>m they shalbe sent, And <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e Superiors of <ex>th</ex>e Cleargy, <lb/>
            &amp; Religious Orders haue charged <ex>the</ex>mselues w<ex>i</ex>th <ex>th</ex>e conveying <ex>the</ex>m to <ex>th</ex>os p<ex>ar</ex>ticular <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>sons, &amp; accompanying <ex>the</ex>m w<ex>i</ex>th effectual letters from <ex>the</ex>mselues, to assure That these <lb/>
            are the Act of all <ex>th</ex>e p<ex>er</ex>sons so mett together, And haue p<ex>ro</ex>mised every one of <ex>the</ex>m by <lb/>
            <ex>the</ex>mselues, &amp; by the Priests <ex>tha</ex>t depend on <ex>the</ex>m, to negociate sincerely, to p<ex>ro</ex>mote, &amp; aduance <lb/>
            this business effectually as a thing mainly importing <ex>th</ex>e Kings service, &amp; o<ex>u</ex>r duty, &amp; good.
         </p>
         <pb n="31v" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f031v/harley_ms_4931_f031v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">5</add> You are to lett <ex>th</ex>os know, <del rend="strikethrough">
                    <gap reason="illegible" quantity="4" unit="chars"/>
                </del> w<ex>ho</ex>m yo<ex>u</ex> imploy to assist yo<ex>u</ex> in this work, <lb/>
            (&amp; we conceiue it wilbe noe small encouragement to yo<ex>u</ex>rselues to labor effectu-<lb break="no"/>
            ally in the business) that her Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty undertakes to secure all those that shall im-<lb break="no"/>
            ploy <ex>the</ex>mselues in these affaires from any inconvenience <ex>tha</ex>t may be appr<ex>e</ex>hended by <lb/>
            them, by reason of their forwardness, &amp; declarac<ex>i</ex>on in this service.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">6</add>To make <ex>the</ex>m appr<ex>e</ex>hend of one Instance,how much it importeth <ex>the</ex>m upon this <lb/>
            occasion to meritt at <ex>th</ex>e Kings, and Queenes hands, yo<ex>u</ex> may let <ex>the</ex>m know, There <lb/>
            hath beene lately granted to one Pulford, a Co<ex>m</ex>mission to indite, &amp; Convict <lb/>
            such Catholiques as yet are not, &amp; to question Composic<ex>i</ex>ons allready made upon <lb/>
            pretence Of their having passed at too low a rate, And to prosecute the rest <lb/>
            of the Lawes ag<ex>ains</ex>t them, And <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>the</ex>rupon he hath sett on <del rend="strikethrough">in</del> work many A-<lb break="no"/>
            gents in severall parts, And hath erected an Office for <ex>tha</ex>t Service; But by <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Queenes mediac<ex>i</ex>on to the King, his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty hath beene graciously pleased To <lb/>
            direct the Suspending of the execuc<ex>i</ex>on of this Co<ex>m</ex>mission, &amp; to stay all pro-<lb break="no"/>
            ceedings upon it; so as o<ex>u</ex>r behaviour in this contribuc<ex>i</ex>on will assuredly much altere <lb/>
            o<ex>u</ex>r Condic<ex>i</ex>on generally, either to the Better, or to <ex>th</ex>e Worse, according as we <lb/>
            shall expresse o<ex>u</ex>rselvus affectionate, or cold to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes Service, &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">upon this</del> pre-<lb break="no"/>
            sent occasions.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">7</add>To <ex>th</ex>e end <ex>tha</ex>t all p<ex>er</ex>sons of w<ex>ha</ex>t degree soeuer be spoken to, &amp; Solicited for <lb/>
            this contribuc<ex>i</ex>on, It wilbe fitt <ex>tha</ex>t yo<ex>u</ex> speake to all subordinate Superiors of the <lb/>
            Country where yo<ex>u</ex> liue, That they reco<ex>m</ex>mend effectually to all the Priests w<ex>i</ex>thin <lb/>
            their Provinces to give yo<ex>u</ex> all the Assistance in their power for the advance-<lb break="no"/>
            ment of this business.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">8</add>Though we will not pr<ex>e</ex>sume to pr<ex>e</ex>scribe limits to the/ Devoc<ex>i</ex>on, &amp; liberality of <lb/>
            any others, yet we think it not amiss to lett yo<ex>u</ex> know, <ex>tha</ex>t upon this occasion we <lb/>
            find here about London so g<ex>rea</ex>t a cheerfullness in Catholiques to advance <lb/>
            this business, &amp; to bring <ex>th</ex>e contribuc<ex>i</ex>on to a considerable summe, as <ex>tha</ex>t we confi-<lb break="no"/>
            dently hope noe man will giue lesse <ex>tha</ex>n 8, 9 or 10 parts of his Annuall <lb/>
            revenue (as <ex>th</ex>e iust, &amp; true values) And hither to we haue mett w<ex>i</ex>th none <lb/>
            <ex>tha</ex>t haue gone under, but w<ex>i</ex>th many <ex>tha</ex>t doe farre exceed <ex>tha</ex>t p<ex>ro</ex>porc<ex>i</ex>on, w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            we conceiue the most will imitate, Considering <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e Action is such, as <ex>tha</ex>t no duti<lb break="no"/>
            full subject ought to be backward in these times, wherein the safety of the king<lb break="no"/>
            dome is so nearly concerned, &amp; for <ex>tha</ex>t it hath beene so effectually reco<ex>m</ex>mended <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">by us</del> unto us by <ex>th</ex>e Queenes Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty, who hath beene so tender in matters of <lb/>
            this nature, as never to haue reco<ex>m</ex>mended the like before, &amp; unto w<ex>ho</ex>m we <lb/>
            haue so g<ex>rea</ex>t obligac<ex>i</ex>ons (as <ex>tha</ex>t <hi rend="bold">w<ex>ha</ex>t is</hi> but for her sake) <ex>the</ex>r is noe man (we p<ex>er</ex>-<lb break="no"/>
            swade o<ex>u</ex>rselues) but wold be content to sufferr some Inconvenience in his own <lb/>
            estate to comply w<ex>i</ex>th such a desire from so gracious, &amp; deseruing a Princesse <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">Into</del> <add place="above">unto</add> w<ex>hi</ex>ch severall consid<ex>e</ex>rac<ex>i</ex>ons all hereabout haue had so zealous a regard : <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            Even such who are much en<ex>cu</ex>mbred w<ex>i</ex>th debts, &amp; distracted in their estates <lb/>
            (w<ex>hi</ex>ch may also happen to many others in the country) haue beene so farre <lb/>
            from offerring the same as an excuse, as that they haue borrowed monyes to giue <lb/>
            upon this occasion, in so large a p<ex>ro</ex>porc<ex>i</ex>on, as if <ex>thei</ex>r estates w<ex>e</ex>r free, &amp; they be-<lb break="no"/>
            fore hand in the world. And no man need to appr<ex>e</ex>hend That this gift upon this <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">occasion</fw>
            <pb n="32r" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f032r/harley_ms_4931_f032r.jpg"/>
            occasion may discover the value of his estate (w<ex>hi</ex>ch for sundry reasons he may <lb/>
            desire to keepe private) for w<ex>ha</ex>t he giues, being voluntary, &amp; w<ex>ha</ex>t we haue s<ex>ai</ex>d, <lb/>
            being only to informe <ex>the</ex>m how others comport <ex>the</ex>mselues about London, w<ex>ha</ex>tsoever he <lb/>
            contributeth, will not discover any certeine value of his estate, but <ex>th</ex>e p<ex>ro</ex>porc<ex>i</ex>on of <lb/>
            his zeale, &amp; good will, And this is the unanimous <del rend="strikethrough">con</del> sense of <del rend="strikethrough">almost all the </del>
                <add place="above">as well of the</add> <lb/>
            Eccl<ex>esiast</ex>icall p<ex>er</ex>sons, as well as the noblemen, &amp; Gent<ex>lemen</ex> mett here together.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">9</add>Although we are well assured <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e chiefe motiues w<ex>hi</ex>ch will induce men to straine <lb/>
            <ex>the</ex>mselues to giue as largely as their estates will p<ex>er</ex>mitt, are the Honor, &amp; glory of <lb/>
            g<ex>o</ex>d, &amp; his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes Service. Yet to <ex>th</ex>e end <ex>tha</ex>t ev<ex>e</ex>ry one may likewise receiue such <lb/>
            advantage as may be iustly expected from his forwardnes, &amp; piety, Vpon this oc-<lb break="no"/>
            casion we desire <ex>tha</ex>t the Collectors wold giue Receipts under their Hands for such <lb/>
            monyes as shalbe paid in to <ex>the</ex>m, to the end <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e p<ex>er</ex>sons may upon occasions shew <lb/>
            the same, &amp; make use <ex>the</ex>rof as a faire Motiue to p<ex>ro</ex>cure <ex>the</ex>m reasonable favors, &amp; <lb/>
            graces, as hereafter they may stand in need of.
         </p>
         <p>
            The Forme of the Receipt <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e Collectors doe giue, is this. <lb/>
            I A. B. doe acknowledge to haue received of N. N. the day <lb/>
            &amp; yeare abouewritten, the Summe of ----- as his free, &amp; volun-<lb break="no"/>
            tary gift, &amp; for his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes Service reco<ex>m</ex>mended to us by o<ex>u</ex>r gra-<lb break="no"/>
            cious Queene, upon occasion of his pr<ex>ese</ex>nt iorny w<ex>i</ex>th an Army <lb/>
            into the Northerne parts.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">10</add>
            Bec<ex>ause</ex> no circumstance is so important in this service as EXPEDITION, wee <lb/>
            desire <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>os p<ex>er</ex>sons in London, &amp; neare about it, and in the Southerne Countreyes <lb/>
            who wilbe Contributers, will pay in their monies betweene this, &amp; <ex>th</ex>e end of <lb/>
            Easter Terme, And <ex>tha</ex>t they who are in Countries more remote, will pay in theirs <lb/>
            by the end of Mid-summer Terme.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">11</add>If any <ex>tha</ex>t are allready convicted, &amp; do pay Composic<ex>i</ex>ons for their Recusancy, doe <lb/>
            p<ex>re</ex>tend to be <ex>the</ex>rfore eased in this contribuc<ex>i</ex>on, yo<ex>u</ex> may tell <ex>the</ex>m, <ex>tha</ex>t w<ex>ha</ex>t they pay upon <lb/>
            these <del rend="strikethrough">
                    <gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="chars"/>
                </del> termes, Is an Annuall certainty, &amp; so settled into the substance of their <lb/>
               estates, as ought not at all to divert this extraordinary Acc<ex>i</ex>on, w<ex>hi</ex>ch is to receive <lb/>
               its alottment, &amp; p<ex>ro</ex>porc<ex>i</ex>on out of w<ex>ha</ex>t remaineth <ex>the</ex>rafter <ex>th</ex>e co<ex>m</ex>posic<ex>i</ex>on is deducted.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">12</add>If any pr<ex>e</ex>tend any other charges, as Noblemen <ex>tha</ex>t they haue allready contributed to <lb/>
            this expedic<ex>i</ex>on upon <ex>th</ex>e Kings Letters to <ex>the</ex>m, or if others pr<ex>e</ex>tend any other g<ex>rea</ex>t paiments, <lb/>
            or extraordinary charges, yo<ex>u</ex> may also tell <ex>the</ex>m, <ex>that</ex>t <ex>th</ex>os consid<ex>e</ex>rac<ex>i</ex>ons ought not at all <lb/>
            to lessen their contribuc<ex>i</ex>on upon this occasion, for this concerneth <ex>the</ex>m only as Catho-<lb break="no"/>
            liques, abstracting from all other regards w<ex>ha</ex>tsoever; but these other are <del rend="strikethrough">as</del> co<ex>m</ex>mon <lb/>
            as well to protestants, &amp; all sorts of people as to <ex>the</ex>m.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">13</add>If yo<ex>u</ex> perceiue any shalbe cold in this worke by not being so sensible as they <lb/>
            ought to be of <ex>th</ex>e publick good, &amp; pr<ex>e</ex>suming they are secured in their p<ex>ar</ex>ticular by <lb/>
            some priviledges w<ex>hi</ex>ch they may happily haue obtained by pow<ex>e</ex>rfull mediac<ex>i</ex>on, or <lb/>
            hope otherwise <hi rend="bold">to</hi> excuse, or exempt <ex>the</ex>mselues, yo<ex>u</ex> may assure <ex>the</ex>m <ex>tha</ex>t as <ex>th</ex>e good success <lb/>
            of this Contribuc<ex>i</ex>on is likely to better all o<ex>u</ex>r condic<ex>i</ex>ons in g<ex>e</ex>n<ex>e</ex>rall, so their priviledges <lb/>
            may proue lesse availeable to <ex>the</ex>m if <ex>the</ex>mselues be defective upon this occasion. And <lb/>
            accordingly yo<ex>u</ex> are desired to returne the Names of all <ex>th</ex>os who shall forbeare <lb/>
            to giue (the w<ex>hi</ex>ch we conceiue none will doe) or shall give inconsiderably.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">14</add>
            You may do well likewise to solicit those <ex>tha</ex>t though they be no Catholiques,
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">yet</fw>
            <pb n="32v" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f032v/harley_ms_4931_f032v.jpg"/>
            yet are well affected, &amp; haue their Wiues &amp; Children Catholiques; for besides <lb/>
            the generall, every one in his owne particular is like to fare the better, or <lb/>
            worse, according as he demeaneth hims<ex>elf</ex> in this contribuc<ex>i</ex>on. And where <ex>the</ex>r are <lb/>
            no p<ex>ar</ex>ticular meritts to exempt, it may be feared the rigour of <ex>th</ex>e lawes may be <lb/>
            putt into execuc<ex>i</ex>on ag<ex>ains</ex>t <ex>th</ex>os (upon p<ex>ar</ex>ticular notice taken of <ex>the</ex>m) w<ex>hi</ex>ch will fall upon <lb/>
            <ex>the</ex>m, if throughly looked into, as well as for their wiues being Catholiques, &amp; such <lb/>
            other lapses, <hi rend="bold">as</hi> by their being declared Catholiques <ex>the</ex>mselues.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">15</add>You may repr<ex>e</ex>sent to such p<ex>er</ex>sons to consider w<ex>ha</ex>t a g<ex>rea</ex>t Charity their contribuc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            wilbe to the poorer sort of Catholiques, who will also be utterly ruined, if <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            course of informers goe on, as it is to be feared it will do, if the contribuc<ex>i</ex>on a-<lb break="no"/>
            mount not to a consid<ex>e</ex>rable matter, w<ex>hi</ex>ch it cannot be unles all hands putt it forward.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">16</add>You are desired to receiue all such monies as shall come in by this contri-<lb break="no"/>
            buc<ex>i</ex>on giving the Receipts for it, &amp; <ex>the</ex>n to pay it to such p<ex>er</ex>son, or p<ex>er</ex>sons, as the <lb/>
            Queene shalbe pleased to direct for <ex>th</ex>e Service afores<ex>ai</ex>d.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">17</add>And Lastly. Yo<ex>u</ex> are desired to returne unto the Superiors of <ex>th</ex>e Cleargy, &amp; Re-<lb break="no"/>
            ligious Orders (<ex>tha</ex>t shall send yo<ex>u</ex> these from us) assoone as yo<ex>u</ex> can, an Informac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of w<ex>ha</ex>t p<ex>ro</ex>gresse yo<ex>u</ex> make in this business, And how yo<ex>u</ex> find Catholicks affected <lb/>
            in it, <ex>tha</ex>t we may accordingly ioyne w<ex>i</ex>th <ex>the</ex>m, &amp; yo<ex>u</ex>, in giving her Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty <ex>tha</ex>t account <lb/>
            of all o<ex>u</ex>r labors <ex>the</ex>rin, as is expected at o<ex>u</ex>r hands. W<ex>hi</ex>ch we doubt not, but will <lb/>
            in effect proue answearable to the faire hopes given severally by <ex>th</ex>e s<ex>ai</ex>d Supe-<lb break="no"/>
            riors, upon the returne they r<ex>eceived</ex>d of their 1st letters into <ex>th</ex>e Country as pr<ex>e</ex>pare <lb/>
            Catholiques for this contribuc<ex>i</ex>on, And to gods honor, &amp; glory, &amp; a good service <lb/>
            to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty, and a complying duty to <ex>th</ex>e Queene, &amp; benefitt to Catholiques, <lb/>
            For w<ex>hi</ex>ch ends we shall imploy both o<ex>u</ex>r prayers, &amp; all o<ex>u</ex>r best endeavors.
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            Finis./.
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            The Queenes Letter. <lb/>
            To o<ex>u</ex>r Trusty, &amp; well-beloved Councellor S<ex>i</ex>r John Winton <lb/>
            Knight, o<ex>u</ex>r Principall Secretary, &amp; M<ex>aste</ex>r of Requests
         </p>
         <p rend="outdent">
            Henriette Marie Regina,
         </p>
         <p>
            Wee haue so good a beliefe of the loyaltie, &amp; affection of his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes Subi<ex>ec</ex>ts, <lb/>
            as we doubt not but <ex>tha</ex>t upon this occasion, <ex>tha</ex>t hath called his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty into <ex>th</ex>e Northerne <lb/>
            p<ex>ar</ex>ts, for <ex>th</ex>e defense of his honor, &amp; dominions, they will expresse <ex>the</ex>mselues so affected, <lb/>
            as we haue allwaies repr<ex>e</ex>sented <ex>the</ex>m to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty, so in this co<ex>m</ex>mon consent w<ex>hi</ex>ch hath <lb/>
            appeared in the Nobility, Iudges, Gentry &amp; others to forward his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes Service <lb/>
            by <ex>thei</ex>r p<ex>er</ex>sons &amp; estates, we haue made no difficulty to answeare for <ex>th</ex>e same <lb/>
            correspondency in <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> his Catholique Subi<ex>ec</ex>ts as Catholiques, not w<ex>i</ex>thstanding <ex>tha</ex>t they haue <lb/>
            concurred to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes Service, according to the qualityes wherof they are, w<ex>he</ex>n o-<lb break="no"/>
            thers of <ex>th</ex>e same quality w<ex>e</ex>r called upon; For we believed, <ex>tha</ex>t it became us, who <lb/>
            haue beene so <del rend="strikethrough">en</del> often interessed in the solicitac<ex>i</ex>on of their benefitts, to <lb/>
            shew o<ex>u</ex>rselues now the p<ex>er</ex>swasers of their gratitude. Therefore having allready <lb/>
            by other meanes reco<ex>m</ex>mended to <ex>the</ex>m this earnest desire of o<ex>u</ex>rs to assist, &amp; secure his <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty by</fw>
         </p>
         <pb n="33r" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f033r/harley_ms_4931_f033r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty by some considerable summe of mony freely, &amp; cheerfully pr<ex>e</ex>sented, we haue <lb/>
            haue thought fitt to <ex>th</ex>e end <ex>tha</ex>t this o<ex>u</ex>r desire may be the more publick, &amp; the more au-<lb break="no"/>
            theorised hereby to giue yo<ex>u</ex> a Com<ex>m</ex>ission, &amp; direction to distribute Copies und<ex>e</ex>r yo<ex>u</ex>r hand <lb/>
            of o<ex>u</ex>r certificac<ex>i</ex>on thereof, unto <ex>the</ex>m who haue mett at London by o<ex>u</ex>r directions about <lb/>
            this business; And unto the severall Collecters of every county. And as we pr<ex>e</ex>sume <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            summe they will raise, will not be unworthy of o<ex>u</ex>r p<ex>re</ex>senting to that K<ex>ing</ex>. So shall we be <lb/>
            very sensible of it as p<ex>ar</ex>ticular respects to o<ex>u</ex>rselues, &amp; will endeavor in the most efficaci-<lb break="no"/>
            ous manner we can, to improue the merit of it, &amp; remoue any appr<ex>e</ex>hension of pr<ex>e</ex>iudice <lb/>
            <ex>tha</ex>t any who imploy <ex>the</ex>mselues towards the successe of this business, by this they may be <lb/>
            assured <ex>tha</ex>t we will secure <ex>the</ex>m from all such obiected inconveniencies. And we are confident <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            this o<ex>u</ex>r 1st reco<ex>m</ex>mendac<ex>i</ex>on wilbe so complied w<ex>i</ex>thall, as it may not only affoord not <lb/>
            only us satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on, but also facilitation towards <ex>thei</ex>r owne Advantages.
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            A Coppy of <ex>th</ex>e Letter sent from the Superiours tou-<lb break="no"/>
            ching <ex>th</ex>e Contribution money to be collected of Catholiques <lb/>
            towards his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes Northerne Iorney.
         </p>
         <p>
            The enclosed advices, &amp; motiues being so ample as yo<ex>u</ex> will p<ex>er</ex>ceiue by p<ex>er</ex>using <lb/>
            of <ex>the</ex>m, <ex>tha</ex>t it will not be needfull for us to enlarge o<ex>u</ex>rselues upon any p<ex>ar</ex>ticular concer-<lb break="no"/>
            ning the conduct of the business, w<ex>hi</ex>ch they direct the way in. This <ex>the</ex>rfore serveth <lb/>
            only for to convey <ex>the</ex>m to yo<ex>u</ex>, as we are entreated by <ex>th</ex>os who haue mett here, &amp; <lb/>
            haue undertaken to do, &amp; to desire yo<ex>u</ex> to repaire im<ex>m</ex>ediatly unto the Collector to w<ex>ho</ex>m <lb/>
            the enclosed motiues are directed, &amp; to deliver <ex>th</ex>e same unto him in <ex>th</ex>e name of all <lb/>
            the Noblemen, &amp; Gent<ex>lemen</ex>, together w<ex>it</ex>h o<ex>u</ex>rselues assembied here in London by <ex>th</ex>e Queens <lb/>
            com<ex>m</ex>andm<ex>en</ex>t, to sett forward <ex>th</ex>e work. And we pray yo<ex>u</ex> assure him in <ex>th</ex>e most effi-<lb break="no"/>
            cacious manner yo<ex>u</ex> can (engaging all o<ex>u</ex>r creditts for <ex>th</ex>e truth <ex>the</ex>rof) <ex>tha</ex>t it is <ex>th</ex>e sense of <lb/>
            us all both Eccl<ex>es</ex>i<ex>astic</ex>all, &amp; Lay-p<ex>er</ex>sons, <ex>tha</ex>t (besides <ex>th</ex>e discharging of <ex>thei</ex>r, and o<ex>u</ex>r duties to g<ex>o</ex>d, <lb/>
            &amp; <ex>th</ex>e K<ex>ing</ex>) it mainly importeth <ex>th</ex>e good of Catholiques to have <ex>th</ex>e business take good success. <lb/>
            Therfore entreate him to deale very actiuely, efficaciously, &amp; speedily according to these <lb/>
            advices, &amp; motiues. We are so well p<ex>er</ex>swaded of his devoc<ex>i</ex>on to putt forward so pious <lb/>
            a worke, as <ex>tha</ex>t we doubt not but he wilbe well satisfied in the needfullness of the thing; <lb/>
            &amp; are as ready to imply hims<ex>elf</ex> in it (receiving <ex>th</ex>e assurance <ex>the</ex>rof, &amp; <ex>th</ex>e p<ex>er</ex>swasions <ex>the</ex>runto only <lb/>
            from o<ex>u</ex>r hands) as if they came by all the most-formall waies <ex>tha</ex>t can be imagined, w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            in a business of this nature cannot be expected. And although <ex>th</ex>e advices, &amp; motiues be di-<lb break="no"/>
            rected only to Lay Gent<ex>lemen</ex>, yet we desire yo<ex>u</ex>, &amp; we haue answeared for yo<ex>u</ex>, <ex>tha</ex>t yo<ex>u</ex> will <lb/>
            imploy yo<ex>u</ex>rselfe, &amp; all <ex>th</ex>os <ex>tha</ex>t depend on yo<ex>u</ex>, sincerely to solicite, &amp; dispose all <ex>thei</ex>r minds, w<ex>ho</ex>m yo<ex>u</ex> haue <lb/>
            relac<ex>i</ex>on unto, as powerfully as yo<ex>u</ex> can, to contribute cheerfully, &amp; bountifully on this occa-<lb break="no"/>
            sion, w<ex>hi</ex>ch as it is <ex>th</ex>e 1st, <ex>tha</ex>t we ever laboured in, in this kind, so we hope in God it <lb/>
            will be <ex>th</ex>e last, <ex>the</ex>r being noe p<ex>ro</ex>bability of so pressing, &amp; urgent a necessity to occurred <lb/>
            any more./.
         </p>
         <p rend="align-right">
            Yo<ex>u</ex>rs &amp;c
         </p>
         <p>
            London April 4. 1638 /.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f031r/harley_ms_4931_f031r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f031v/harley_ms_4931_f031v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="3" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f032r/harley_ms_4931_f032r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="4" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f032v/harley_ms_4931_f032v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="5" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f033r/harley_ms_4931_f033r.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>