<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Arguments Exhibited in Parliament Regarding Contempt in Chancery</title>
            <author>
               <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0240">Lord Keeper Nicholas Bacon</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="VA">
                    <name>Victoria Anker</name>
                    <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="CMcC">
               <name>Charlie McClean</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="PMcC">
               <name>Penny McClean</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TW">
               <name>Tim Wales</name>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/NorfRO_RYE_20.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="NorfRO_RYE_20">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>Norwich</settlement>
               <repository>Norfolk Record Office</repository>
               <collection/>
               <idno>RYE 20</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">Norfolk Record Office,  RYE 20</p>
            </msDesc>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated">
                    <bibl/>
                </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1572">c.1572</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
            <language ident="LA">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term>law</term>
               <term>Chancery</term>
               <term>legal jurisdiction</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-09-28" who="#RB" status="proofread"/>
            <change when="2018-09-24" who="#RB" status="drafted"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#VA" status="transcribed"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#CMcC" status="transcribed"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#PMcC" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb ed="Item 2" n="1r" facs="/nro/rye_20/rye_20-012/rye_20-012.jpg"/>
         <head rend="align-centre">
            The Arguments exhibited by the Lord <lb/>
            Keeper S<ex>i</ex>r Nicholas Bacon in Parliament, <lb/>
            proving the Noblemens p<ex>er</ex>sons to be Attacheable <lb/>
            for contempt com<ex>m</ex>itted by them in the Queenes <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties Court of Chancery, disobeying the <lb/>
            decrees in that Court, which came in <lb/>
            question vpon an attachement ordered out <lb/>
            of the same Court to the Sheriff of Norff<ex>olk</ex> <lb/>
            to attach the body of the Lord Cromwell <lb/>
            for disobeying a decree made in the said <lb/>
            Court betweene one Taverner plaintiff and <lb/>
            the said Lord Cromwell defend<ex>an</ex>t, which <lb/>
            Attachment so executed by the said <lb/>
            Sheriff, and the body of the said Lord <lb/>
            Crumwell brought prisoner in the said <lb/>
            Court of Chancery / 
         </head>
         <p>
            First hee saith that by a contempt comitted by a <lb/>
            Nobleman against his Prince, his p<ex>er</ex>son is <lb/>
            attacheable by the lawe, but if a nobleman disobey <lb/>
            a decree made in the Chancery in a matter <lb/>
            examinable there, hee com<ex>m</ex>itteth a contempt ag<ex>ains</ex>t <lb/>
            his Prince, and therefore by the com<ex>m</ex>on lawe his <lb/>
            body for his contempt is attachable, and this is <lb/>
            rather, because the decrees are given <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">coram nobis <lb/>
            in Cancellaria nostra.</hi>
                </foreign>/
         </p>
         <p>
            Secondly hee saith, That if a Nobleman com<ex>m</ex>itt a <lb/>
            contempt against the Queenes Maiesties <lb/>
            prerogative, in one of the highest degrees hee <lb/>
            com<ex>m</ex>itteth the contempt aforesaid, and his body is <lb/>
            attacheable for that by lawe, But if a nobleman <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">disobey</fw>
            <pb ed="Item 2" n="1v" facs="/nro/rye_20/rye_20-013/rye_20-013.jpg"/>
            disobey a decree made in the Chancery and warranted <lb/>
            to be made by her highnes prerogative, in one of the <lb/>
            highest degrees hee com<ex>m</ex>ittes a contempt against that <lb/>
            prerogative, and therefore his body for the same is <lb/>
            attacheable by the lawe, and the cause why hee <lb/>
            thincketh is this, For <add place="above">that</add> the Prince by his prerogative <lb/>
            hath power to order causes otherwise then the lawe <lb/>
            is, and to helpe the subiectes in a cause, wherein hee <lb/>
            hath no helpe, by which seemes in reason as great as <lb/>
            may bee./
         </p>
         <p>
            Thirdly it hath byn allwayes vsed and accustomed, that <lb/>
            Noblemen have byn and yet are called into the <lb/>
            Chancery for matters examined in the same Court, <lb/>
            and the same proceeded in and ordered and if vse &amp; <lb/>
            custome have allowed of this, then of all congruity <lb/>
            it must allow the necessary dependentes of the same, <lb/>
            which is the execuc<ex>i</ex>on of theis orders, for otherwise <lb/>
            that vse should have byn altogether in vayne, and <lb/>
            other meanes in <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> Chancery for execuc<ex>i</ex>on of theis <lb/>
            orders, there is none but by Attachment, And <lb/>
            therefore of necessary depend<ex>en</ex>tes vpon such orders thus <lb/>
            vsed, they are to be allowed. And as to that w<ex>hi</ex>ch hath <lb/>
            byn said, that there hath byn no vse of that execuc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            by Attachment. it hath byn aunsweared That <lb/>
            Noblemen were of that considerac<ex>i</ex>on, that they never <lb/>
            disobeyed any of those orders, and therefore no cause <lb/>
            of that vse.
         </p>
         <p>
            Fowerthly to graunt a Court power to heare and <lb/>
            order, and not to execute the same, is a playne <lb/>
            absurdity. And againe to leave all Coppyholders <lb/>
            of Noblemen <del rend="strikethrough">in matters</del> without remedy, if they <lb/>
            be removed from their coppyholdes by their Lordes <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">and all</fw>
            <pb ed="Item 2" n="2r" facs="/nro/rye_20/rye_20-013/rye_20-013.jpg"/>
            and all other men against Noblemen in matters of <lb/>
            equity, seemes a great inconvenience and much <lb/>
            preiudicall to the com<ex>m</ex>on weale considering how great <lb/>
            the number of theis may be, besides what an <lb/>
            inconvenient thing it is, to have a Nobleman bring a <lb/>
            matter in the Chancery, and the Court shall have <lb/>
            power to doe Iustice for him, but not against him. <lb/>
            This is not <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">Ius aequabile</hi>
                </foreign>, and all the thinges are <lb/>
            to followe in his opinion, except theis Attachm<ex>en</ex>tes <lb/>
            in the cases afore remembred be allowed ./
         </p>
         <p>
            Fiftly, for as much as the Chancery is warranted <lb/>
            to heare and order causes by vertue of the <lb/>
            Queenes Maiesties prerogative, where otherwise <lb/>
            by lawe the subiect hath an helpe and also to <lb/>
            qualifie the extremity of the lawe, Therefore if <lb/>
            all causes examinable in Chancery for the respect <lb/>
            aforesaid betweene a Nobleman and another man <lb/>
            should be taken from the hearing and ordering of <lb/>
            that Court, that must needes be in derogation of <lb/>
            the same, which hee thincketh ought not to be <lb/>
            without the Queenes Maiesties privity, And <lb/>
            therefore prayeth as hee hath aforedone, and that <lb/>
            her highnes may be made acquainted with this <lb/>
            cause, before any order be taken herein ./
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/nro/rye_20/rye_20-012/rye_20-012.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/nro/rye_20/rye_20-013/rye_20-013.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>