<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Speech to Justice Finch</title>
            <author>
               <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0148">Lord Keeper Thomas Coventry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SWc">
               <name>Serena Woodcock</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SW">
               <name>Susan Ward</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/NorfRO_RYE_20.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="NorfRO_RYE_20">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>Norwich</settlement>
               <repository>Norfolk Record Office</repository>
               <collection/>
               <idno>RYE 20</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">Norfolk Record Office,  RYE 20</p>
            </msDesc>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated">
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLLansdowneMS211.xml">British Library, Lansdowne MS 211, ff. 87r–97x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Houghton_fMS_Eng_1266.xml">Houghton Library,  fMS Eng 1266, volume I, ff.225r–229v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1634">1634</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
            <language ident="LA">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term>speech</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-09-13" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#SWc" status="transcribed"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#SW" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb ed="Item 4" n="11r"/>
         <head rend="indent">
            The Lord Coventry Lord Keeper of the
            great Seale of England his speech to <lb/>
            the Lord cheif Justice Finch at the
            tyme of his installation in the Court of <lb/>
            Co<ex>m</ex>mon Pleas the 16th of October 1634
         </head>
         <p>
            M<ex>aste</ex>r Sergeant Finch
         </p>
         <p>
            The Kinges Ma<ex>ies</ex>tie calling to mynde yo<ex>ur</ex> many services to <lb/>
            himselfe and the Queene, and knowing well yo<ex>u</ex>r great <lb/>
            learning accompanied with much dexteritie in accomplishing <lb/>
            of busines of weight, hath appointed yo<ex>u</ex> to succeed the
            place vacant in this Court, and here to sitt as cheife <lb/>
            Justice; In this you see manifest argument of the
            singular goodnes of the King and Queene so myndefull <lb/>
            of their servantes imitating God above, that rewardes <lb/>
            not <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">secundum, sed supra bona opera</hi>
                </foreign>, Now, as many
            heretofore, so you in yo<ex>u</ex>r due tyme, have cause to <lb/>
            acknowledge with David, that yo<ex>u</ex>r cupp doeth <lb/>
            overflowe; and this is a great comfort to see yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            indeavors not onely favoured with acceptance, but <lb/>
            crowned with reward, So it will instruct you, <lb/>
            (your service having brought you to promotion) and <lb/>
            putt you in mynde of yo<ex>u</ex>r service,  The guifte of <lb/>
            Princes, though they are <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">sine aliquo reddendo</hi>
                </foreign>, yet <lb/>
            they are not to be received so by them that have <lb/>
            them, but as fruites sowne in fruitfull ground to
            them that receive them: And of this nature is yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            place, which yo<ex>u</ex>r Master gives you to serve him in, <lb/>
            And yett you must serve so as you may be
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">fruitfull</fw>
            <pb ed="Item 4" n="11v"/>
            fruitfull to his people: I remember in Rotulo <lb/>
            Parliamenti <unclear/> 20o Edw:<ex>ardi</ex> primi in a great cause <lb/>
            betwixt Humfry de Bohun and Gilbert de Clare <lb/>
            it was said of that King, who was as great a <lb/>
            lawgiver, as a victorious Prince, and therefore <lb/>
            stiled the Iustinian of England <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">Rex omnibus <lb/>
               Justitiae debitor</hi>
                </foreign>, The King our Master, as much <lb/>
            as any, makes the same acknowledgement in <lb/>
            practise, (never any king, I may say never any <lb/>
            man of a Iuster or more upright hath) that <lb/>
            equall Iustice should be minstred to his subiectes: <lb/>
            For hee knowes well, that <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">Rex et subditus</hi>
                </foreign> are
            correlatives even as man and wife, and the <lb/>
            Emblemme of the king not wanting betwixt them, <lb/>
            <unclear>As</unclear> the subiect owes obedience to the king protection <lb/>
            and Iustice. This debt is <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">debitum Justitiae</hi>
                </foreign>, too <lb/>
            great and heavy a burden to be borne by a king <lb/>
            compounded onely of mortall flesh, were it not <lb/>
            that his Counsell were as religious and Iust, as <lb/>
            hee wise and politique, and thereby the load of <lb/>
            kinges busines is lighted by laying a part <add place="above">of</add> that <lb/>
            great and insupportable burden <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> <add place="above">on</add> Iudges: for <lb/>
            this <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">debitum Justitiae</hi>
                </foreign>, which is the debt of a <lb/>
            King primarily by secondary meanes becomes the <lb/>
            debt of Iudges, and under as great bonde as may <lb/>
            be, greater there cannot be to bynde the <lb/>
            consciences of men, The first Bond is <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">debitum <lb/>
               Patriae</hi>
                </foreign> due to all the Kinges people, whose causes <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">and pleas</fw>
            <pb ed="Item 4" n="12r"/>
            and pleas are the proper subiectes of this <lb/>
            Tribunall, and whose flourishing estate dependes <lb/>
            much upon the iust proceedinges of this Court, were <lb/>
            there no other motive, yet this that prevailes <lb/>
            among the heathen <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">amor Patriae</hi>
                </foreign> were strong enough <lb/>
            to make Iudges desirous of this duty. The second is <lb/>
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">debitum Regi</hi>
                </foreign>, For hee trustes them with his richest <lb/>
            treasure, that which is dearer then the apple of his <lb/>
            eye. This Iustice is one prime and principall part <lb/>
            of his oath at his Coronation <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">facies eis in omnibus <lb/>
               Justitiam aequam et rectam</hi>
                </foreign>, And what you are to give <lb/>
            the king for this you shall need to goe no further <lb/>
            then yo<ex>u</ex>r oath, the neglect of which puttes you in the <lb/>
            will of the king for body, landes and goodes. The third <lb/>
            the greatest of all is <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">debitum Deo</hi>
                </foreign>, and hee is the <lb/>
            Fountayne of all Iustice, and a fearefull revenger <lb/>
            of all them, that doe the contrary. And three <lb/>
            wayes shall mynde you how this is a debt to God. <lb/>
            First <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">Ratione iuramenti</hi>
                </foreign>, by reason of yo<ex>u</ex>r oath, for <lb/>
            the imediate relation it hath to God. That it is <lb/>
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">Religio Juris iurandi</hi>
                </foreign> and therfore under this oath <lb/>
            you are bound to God in a full discharge, Secondly <lb/>
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">Ratione loci</hi>
                </foreign>, for the seate of Iudges, God sittes <lb/>
            whereon you sitt, And you assure yo<ex>u</ex>r selfe, that hee <lb/>
            that settes you there, will take a strict accompt of <lb/>
            you. Thirdly <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">Ratione Judicij</hi>
                </foreign> the iudgement it <lb/>
            selfe is Godes, if you be upright as you ought: It is <lb/>
            said in the <unclear>8</unclear>2 psalme, God standes in the <lb/>
            congregation of Princes, hee is the Judge among Godes. <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">And so</fw>
            <pb ed="Item 4" n="12v"/>
            And so when you sitt here, you must think that <lb/>
            God is in yo<ex>u</ex>r face to give Iudgement, as it is <lb/>
            right, or otherwise to punish, And therefore, <lb/>
            whensoever you shall sett yo<ex>u</ex>r selfe on yo<ex>u</ex>r cushion either <lb/>
            here or in any other place, you have cause to say, <lb/>
            as Iacob did when hee slept in Bethell, how <lb/>
            wonderfull is this place, this is the house of God. <lb/>
            Thus upon the generall I feare I have spent too=<lb break="no"/>
            much tyme, I will make amendes in the p<ex>ar</ex>ticular, <lb/>
            somewhat for order, <unclear>Co<ex>mmun</ex>ia Pl<ex>ac</ex>ita</unclear> is the pleas of <lb/>
            the people, and as they are numberles, so necessarily <lb/>
            must their pleas and causes; therefore they are <lb/>
            all civill, whether for landes, goodes, reall, p<ex>er</ex>sonall <lb/>
            or mixt: they are the proper obiect of this Court. <lb/>
            First therefore you must use diligence in attending <lb/>
            and dispatching the multitude of businesses in this Court: <lb/>
            <unclear>Com<ex>m</ex>on</unclear> Industry may discharge com<ex>m</ex>on imploymentes; <lb/>
            but this is a sup<ex>er</ex>lative and transcendent, And therefore <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r diligence must be extraordinary: Secondly you must <lb/>
            use great patience in matters brought before you: <lb/>
            I must confesse, that a multitude of busines and a <lb/>
            good will to dispatch will as soone trye ones patience <lb/>
            as any thing yet whatsoever tryall you are putt <lb/>
            to, be not from yo<ex>u</ex>r tryall: nothing better becomes <lb/>
            a Iudge then patience. Thirdly you must use <lb/>
            great caution in discerning those thinges brought <lb/>
            before you: For those that have ill causes, will <lb/>
            omitt no indeavour to beguile you: Therefore you <lb/>
            must keepe watch and ward and try every thing, <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">that no</fw>
            <pb ed="Item 4" n="13r"/>
            That no counterfett coyne be putt upon you. <lb/>
            Then in the fowereth place it is necessary to use <lb/>
            all expedic<ex>i</ex>on: <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">nulli differrimus</hi>
                </foreign> is coupled with <lb/>
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">nulli negabimus, nulli vendemus Justitiam</hi>
                </foreign>: all three <lb/>
            are nought, and none can tell, which is worst, In <lb/>
            the first place I shall advise and wish you in all <lb/>
            your Iudgementes to insist upon the auncient wayes <lb/>
            of our co<ex>m</ex>mon lawe<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>: New opinions are many tymes <lb/>
            in a Counsellor retayned to defend a side<unclear>;</unclear> but they <lb/>
            stand not with the gravity of a Iudge; To invent <lb/>
            or finde out anything is com<ex>m</ex>endable in a Counsellor, <lb/>
            but lett a Iudge stand <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">super antiquas vias</hi>
                </foreign>: For
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">Lex loci et consuetudo Angliae</hi>
                </foreign> is all in all. One
            p<ex>ar</ex>ticular more, which I think conduceth much to <lb/>
            Justice, to give all encouragement to the good and <lb/>
            expert Clarkes of this Court: It hath ever byn <lb/>
            the great co<ex>m</ex>mendac<ex>i</ex>one and honor of this Court to be <lb/>
            furnished with the best Clarkes: These encourage <lb/>
            others, reforme and reduce to the same purity of <lb/>
            pleading: which (as M<ex>aste</ex>r Littleton saith) is one of <lb/>
            the most honorable thinges of the lawe, And if a <lb/>
            man observe, what a multitude of Just causes <lb/>
            are overthrowne by vicious entries and pleadinges, <lb/>
            hee will have cause to beleeve it: And therefore, <lb/>
            as yo<ex>u</ex>r power is great to doe this, forgett not to <lb/>
            doe it. I know to whome I speake, yo<ex>u</ex>r great <lb/>
            understanding and Iudgement, and that dexterity <lb/>
            in you neede not, that I should say halfe this, and <lb/>
            yet, considering what order is, and the duty of my <lb/>
            place and affection to yo<ex>u</ex>r p<ex>er</ex>son, I could doe no lesse. <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">I shall</fw>
            <pb ed="Item 4" n="13v"/>
            I shall shutt upp all in twoe mementoes; the <lb/>
            one, the Iustices of this Court are stiled by <lb/>
            the name of Iusticiarij without addic<ex>i</ex>on, and the <lb/>
            processe likewise <unclear>coram</unclear> Iusticiarijs without <lb/>
            addic<ex>i</ex>on: Addic<ex>i</ex>on for the most part diminishes. <lb/>
            That is an honor and somewhat more, in that it <lb/>
            hath byn more attributed to this Court, then any <lb/>
            other: Think on it, and lett it be an occasion <lb/>
            unto you to think what it is, and to follow it, <lb/>
            The next memento is to remember the catalogue <lb/>
            of yo<ex>u</ex>r predecessors, For I may be bould to say, <lb/>
            As many reverend men have byn upon the <lb/>
            cushion in this Court, as ever satt in any, especially <lb/>
            the remembrance of the best is all the best <lb/>
            instrucc<ex>i</ex>on and lesson to yo<ex>u</ex>r selfe: Out of my <lb/>
            true and harty affecc<ex>i</ex>on to you, I wish that <lb/>
            you may often think of them, and so think of <lb/>
            their wayes, that yo<ex>u</ex>r wayes may exceed and out=<lb break="no"/>
            runn the best of all./
         </p> 
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>