<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Forerunner of Revenge</title>
            <author>
               <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0163">George Eglisham</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <name>Elaine Brown</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLAddMS22591.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_22591">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Additional</collection>
                <idno>MS 22591</idno>
                <msName/>
             </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Additional MS 22591</p>
            </msDesc>
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated">
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Alnwick_Castle_MS_527.xml">Alnwick Castle,  MS 527, ff. 45r–67v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHarleyMS6865.xml">British Library, Harley MS 6865, ff. 11x–24x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Harley_MS_405.xml">British Library, Harley MS 405, ff. 72r–77v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Sloane_MS_1779.xml">British Library, Sloane MS 1779, ff. 160r–188v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Ashmole_749.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Ashmole 749, item 3, 17–21</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Rawlinson_C_573.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Rawlinson C 573, ff. 94r–126r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Rawlinson_D_171.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Rawlinson D 171, ff. 26r–45v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/CUL_MS_Dd1428.xml">Cambridge University Library,  MS Dd.14.28, Part II item 1, ff28</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/CUL_MS_Ee232.xml">Cambridge University Library,  MS Ee.2.32, ff. 159r–182v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/CUL_MS_Gg413.xml">Cambridge University Library,  MS Gg.4.13, pp137–145</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Folger_MS_V_a_470.xml">Folger Shakespeare Library,  MS V.a.470</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Folger_MS_X_d_236.xml">Folger Shakespeare Library,  MS X.d.236, ff. 1r–13v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/SHC_LM132710.xml">Surrey History Centre,  LM/1327/10</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Senate_House_MS_309.xml">Senate House, University of London,  MS 309, ff. 105r–135x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/WYL2302959.xml">West Yorkshire Archive Service,  WYL230/2959</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Wellcome_Library_MS_254.xml">Wellcome Library,  MS 254, ff12</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            <listBibl xml:id="C17_print_witness">
               <bibl>
                  <author>
                     <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0163">George Eglisham</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title>The forerunner of reuenge Vpon the Duke of Buckingham</title>
                  <date when="1626">1626</date>
                  <idno type="STC">7548</idno>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <author>
                     <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0163">George Eglisham</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title>The fore-runner of revenge, being two petitions</title>
                  <date when="1642">1642</date>
                  <idno type="Wing">E256</idno>
                  <idno type="Wing">E256bA</idno>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl xml:id="modern_print_witness">
               <bibl>
                  <title type="shorttitle">The Harleian Miscellany</title>
                  <edition>1st ed.</edition> 
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="71">61-71</biblScope>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="shorttitle">Somers Tracts</title>
                  <edition>2nd ed.</edition> 
                  <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="444">437-444</biblScope>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1626">1626</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
            <language ident="LA">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-09-19" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2018-09-19" who="#EB" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="31r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f031r/add_ms_22591_f031r.jpg"/>
         <head rend="align-centre">
            The <lb/>
            fore-run<ex>n</ex>er of Reuenge <lb/>
         </head>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            vpon <lb/>
            the Duke of Buckingha<ex>m</ex> for <ex>th</ex>e poy=<lb break="no"/>
            soning <lb/>
            of <ex>th</ex>e most potent K<ex>ing</ex> James of hapye <lb/>
            memory <lb/>
            K<ex>ing</ex> of g<ex>rea</ex>t Brittaine, And <ex>th</ex>e lorde <lb/>
            Marq<ex>uess</ex> <lb/>
            Ha<ex>m</ex>bleton, And others of the Nobi<lb break="no"/>
            litye
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            disco=<lb break="no"/>
            uered by Mr George Eglisha<ex>m</ex> Doc<ex>tor</ex> <lb/>
            off <lb/>
            Phisicke, &amp; latelye one of K<ex>ing</ex> Ia<ex>mes</ex> <lb/>
            his <lb/>
            phis<ex>ician</ex> for his Ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s person aboue <lb/>
            the <lb/>
            space of those tenne yeares
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="align-centre">From <lb/>
            </hi>FranckeForte 1626
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre"> 
            Iohn Sudbury et George Humble <lb/>
            Londini excuderunt <lb/>
         </p>
         <pb n="31v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f031v/add_ms_22591_f031v.jpg"/>
         <gap reason="elision" extent="1" unit="side"/>
         <pb n="32r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f032r/add_ms_22591_f032r.jpg"/>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            To the <lb/>
            most potent Monarch Charles Kinge of <lb/>
            greate <lb/>
            Brittaine Fraunce and Ireland
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="italic">
               The humble Compl<ex>ain</ex>t of George Eglisham <lb/>
               Doctor of Phisicke, and lately one <lb/>
               of Kinge Iames his Phisitons for <lb/>
               his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes Person aboue <ex>th</ex>e space <lb/>
               of tenn yeeres.
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            Sir noe <add place="above">bett<ex>e</ex>r</add> motive there is for A sincere safe <lb/>
            governem<ex>en</ex>t then the sincere meditac<ex>i</ex>on of death (equallinge <lb/>
            Kinges to Baggars) and of the severe and exact Iustice of God, <lb/>
            requiringe of him that the good suffering miserie in this liffe <lb/>
            should receive Ioye in the other: and the wicked flourishing se=<lb break="no"/>
            curelye in this, might be punished in the other. That w<ex>hi</ex>ch pleaseth <lb/>
            lasteth but A mom<ex>en</ex>t, that w<ex>hi</ex>ch tormenteth is everlasting, many <lb/>
            thinges wee see vnrewarded or vnpunished in this inferior <lb/>
            world, w<ex>hi</ex>ch in the vniversall waights of Gods Iustice must be <lb/>
            cou<ex>n</ex>terpoysed elswhere: but willfull and secrett murther hath <lb/>
            seldome bine observed to escape vndiscovered or vnpunished <lb/>
            ever in this liffe, such A p<ex>ar</ex>ticuler and notable revenge p<ex>er</ex>pe:<lb break="no"/>
            tuallye followeth it, to the end that they whoe are either A=<lb break="no"/>
            theists Lucianists or Machiavellists maie not trust to much <lb/>
            in their owne Witts in doeing soe horrible Iniustice
         </p>
         <p>
            Would to God yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye would consider well what I haue <lb/>
            often saide to my M<ex>aste</ex>r. Kinge Iames, <hi rend="italic">The greatest Pollicye is <lb/>
            Honestie</hi> And howsoever anye man seemes to him selfe wise <lb/>
            in compassinge his desire by Trickes yet in the ende he will <lb/>
            prove A Foole, for falshood ever deceaveth her owne m<ex>aste</ex>r <lb/>
            at lengthe, as the devill (author of all Falshood) doth, leaving <lb/>
            his adherents desolate when they have greatest need of <lb/>
            helpe, Noe Falshood w<ex>i</ex>thout Iniustice / Noe Iniustice with <lb/>
            out Falshood, albeit it were in the p<ex>er</ex>son of <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> <add place="above">a</add> Kinge. Ther <lb/>
            is noe Iudge in the world more tyed to doe Iustice then a <lb/>
            Kinge, whose Coronation tyeth him vnto it by solempne oath <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch if he Violate, he is false and p<ex>er</ex>iured, It is Iustice that <lb/>
            maketh kinges, Iustice that mainetaineth Kinges &amp; Iustice <lb/>
            that bringeth both Kingdomes and kinges to distrucc<ex>i</ex>on, to <lb/>
            fall in miserye, to dye like Asses in ditches, or more beastly <lb/>
            deathes w<ex>i</ex>th eternall Infamye after death, as all <ex>th</ex>e Histories <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">fro<ex>m</ex>
                </fw>
            <pb n="32v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f032v/add_ms_22591_f032v.jpg"/>
            from time to time doe declare and testifie, what need hath <lb/>
            mankinde of Kings but for Iustice? men are not borne for <lb/>
            them but they for men; what greater, what more royall occa=<lb break="no"/>
            sion in the world could bee offered vnto yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye to shewe <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r vnpartiall dispotition in matter of Iustice at <ex>th</ex>e first e<ex>n</ex>trie <lb/>
            of yo<ex>u</ex>r raigne, then this w<ex>hi</ex>ch I offer, my Iust complaint against <lb/>
            Buckingham! by whom yo<ex>u</ex>r Maiestie suffereth yo<ex>u</ex>r selfe soe farr <lb/>
            to be ledd, that yo<ex>u</ex>r best subiects are in doubte, whether hee is <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r kinge, or you his. If yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye knowe and consider how he <lb/>
            hath terannized over his Lord and M<ex>aste</ex>r Kinge Iames, <ex>th</ex>e world <lb/>
            lye creator of his Fortunes, howe insolent, howe ingrate an <lb/>
            oppressor, what A Murtherer and Traytor he hath proved him=<lb break="no"/>
            selfe towards him, howe treacherous to his vpholding Freind <lb/>
            the Marquesse of Hamelton and others, yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye maye thinke <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            givinge waye to the lawes comaunded against him to yeild A <lb/>
            most glorious Feild for yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye to walke in, and displaye <lb/>
            the banner of yo<ex>u</ex>r royall vertues; yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye maye p<ex>er</ex>happs <lb/>
            demaunde what interest I haue therein! what have to doe ther<lb break="no"/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th <ex>tha</ex>t I should stirr all others being quiett Sir <ex>th</ex>e quiettnes <lb/>
            or stirring of others expecteth onlye A begining fro<ex>m</ex> me, who<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            they knowe to be soe much obliged to stirr, as <ex>tha</ex>t none cann bee <lb/>
            more, both in respect of knowledge of passages, and regard of <lb/>
            humaine obligation, and of my independencie fro<ex>m</ex> <ex>th</ex>e accused, <lb/>
            or anye one <ex>tha</ex>t his power or Creditt can reache vnto.  Manye <lb/>
            knowe not what I knowe therein, others are little or nothinge <lb/>
            beholdinge to the dead, others albeit they knowe as well as I <lb/>
            and are obliged as deepe as I, yet dare not complaine as safely <lb/>
            as I, being out of theire reache, whoe are inseperable fro<ex>m</ex> him <lb/>
            by his inchauntm<ex>en</ex>tes, and able to obscure himselfe vntill that <lb/>
            the Power of iust revenge vpon him and his adherentes bee <lb/>
            obtayned fro<ex>m</ex> God, what I knowe sufficient ag<ex>ain</ex>st him I haue <lb/>
            sett downe in my Petition to the Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t, vnto w<ex>hi</ex>ch if yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye dismisse him, sequestred fro<ex>m</ex> yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye, cheiffelye in an <lb/>
            accusation of Treason, yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye shall doe w<ex>ha</ex>t is most iust, and <lb/>
            deliver yo<ex>u</ex>r selfe and yo<ex>u</ex>r kingdomes fro<ex>m</ex> <ex>th</ex>e Captivitie in w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            he holdeth them and yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye oppressed. Howe easilye maye <lb/>
            I ecclipse myselfe fro<ex>m</ex> his power to doe mee harme vnlesse he <lb/>
            haue legions of infernall spirritts at his comaund to pursue <lb/>
            mee, yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye maye well know, I being <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">vltra mare</hi>
                </foreign> vnto these <lb/>
            dominions where he raigneth and rageth, howe farr I am <lb/>
            obliged to complaine more then others, I will onlye in few words <lb/>
            expresse, <ex>tha</ex>t neither yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty nor anye man maye thinke other <lb/>
            wise, but <ex>tha</ex>t I haue most iust reason not to be silent in wro<ex>n</ex>ges <lb/>
            soe intollerable. The Interest of bloude w<ex>hi</ex>ch I haue to anye <lb/>
            of them of whose death I complaine either by the house of <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Balgony Landy</hi> or by the house of <hi rend="italic">Silvertonhill</hi>, albeit it is <lb/>
            easye to be made manifest and sufficient to move mee, yet is <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">it</fw>
            <pb n="33r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f033r/add_ms_22591_f033r.jpg"/>
            it not the sole motive of my breache of silence /
         </p>
         <p>
            For birthe and Ancestors and what <lb/>
            wee haue not done scarce call I ours /
         </p>
         <p>
            But the Interest of received courtesies and the heape <lb/>
            of infallible tokens of true affection is more then sufficient <lb/>
            to stirr mee thereto, vnlesse I would prove the most ingrate <lb/>
            in the world, and sencelesse of the greatest inuiryes cann bee <lb/>
            done to my selfe. For whoe hath killed kinge Iames and the <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Marquesse Hamelton</hi>, in that parte of iniurye w<ex>hi</ex>ch is don<ex>n</ex>e to <lb/>
            mee, therein he hath done as much as robbed mee of my liffe and <lb/>
            all my Fortunes, Freindes w<ex>i</ex>th such constant &amp; loving impr<ex>e</ex>sio<ex>n</ex>s <lb/>
            of mee are neither to be recovered nor dulye valued. For his <lb/>
            ma<ex>jes</ex>tye fro<ex>m</ex> the third yeere of my Age did practise hono<ex>ra</ex>ble tokens <lb/>
            of singuler favor towards mee, daylye augmented them in word <lb/>
            in writte, in deeds, accomplished them w<ex>i</ex>th guifts, Patents, offices <lb/>
            recomendacio<ex>n</ex>s, both in private and publique graced mee. soe <lb/>
            farre that I could scarce haue asked him anye thinge w<ex>hi</ex>ch I could <lb/>
            not allsoe obtaine, Howe much honor he hath done to mee there <lb/>
            needeth noe wittnes vnto yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tye, whoe is sufficient for many. <lb/>
            Noe lesse was my Lord marquesse of Hamelton his Freindship <lb/>
            established by mutuall obligac<ex>i</ex>on of most accepted offices <lb/>
            continued by our Ancestors these 3: generations, ingraven in <lb/>
            the tender myndes and yeeres of the Marquesse and mee, in <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            pr<ex>e</ex>sence of our Soveraigne Kinge Iames. For when <ex>th</ex>e Marquesses <lb/>
            Father, w<ex>i</ex>th the right hand vpon his head and the left vpo<ex>n</ex> myne, <lb/>
            did offer vs younge in yeares soe ioyned to kisse his ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s hand, <lb/>
            recomending mee vnto his ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s Favor, said, I take God to my <lb/>
            wittnes that this young mans Father was the best Freind that <lb/>
            ever I had, or shall haue in this world. Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> the younge <lb/>
            lord resolved to put trust in mee, and I fullye to addicte my <lb/>
            selfe vnto him, to deserue of him as muche comendac<ex>i</ex>ons as <lb/>
            my Father did of his Father. This royall celebrac<ex>i</ex>on of our <lb/>
            Freindshipp rooted it selfe soe deepelye in my mynde, that to <lb/>
            my selfe I p<del rend="strikethrough">er</del>
                <ex>ur</ex>posed this reme<ex>m</ex>brance, giveing it to the younge <lb/>
            Lord and to my Familyar Freindes,and sett it vpo<ex>n</ex> all <ex>th</ex>e Books <lb/>
            in my Studdye / <hi rend="italic">Semper Hameltonu<ex>m</ex> &amp;c. /</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="align-right">
            <hi rend="italic">
               <lg>
                  <l>Alwaies <ex>th</ex>e Kinge &amp; Halmelton</l>
                  <l>within thy Breast p<ex>re</ex>serue</l>
                  <l>What euer be thy action</l>
                  <l>Let Princes two deserue /</l>
               </lg>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            Neither was it in vaine, for both our loves increased with <lb/>
            our Age, the marquesse promisinge to engage his liffe, and his <lb/>
            whole estate if need were, and to share his Fortunes w<ex>i</ex>th mee, <lb/>
            and not onlye p<ex>ro</ex>missing, but allsoe p<ex>er</ex>form<ex>m</ex>ing when ever there <lb/>
            was occasion, yea for my Cause offering to hazard his liffe <lb/>
            in combate, whose mynde in wishing mee well, whose tongue in <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">honoringe</fw>
            <pb n="33v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f033v/add_ms_22591_f033v.jpg"/>
            honoringe mee, and whose handes and meanes in defendinge me, <lb/>
            both absent and pr<ex>e</ex>sent vnto the last period of his liffe, hath assis<add place="above">t</add>ed <lb/>
            mee, I should be more tedious then were fitt, <ex>i</ex>f I rehearsed eu<ex>er</ex>y <lb/>
            p<ex>ar</ex>ticuler Favor, soe manifestlye knowne to the whole Court, and <lb/>
            to the Freindes of both.  Whoe then can iustlye blame me for demau<ex>n</ex>d=<lb break="no"/>
            inge Iustice as well for the slaughter of the marquesse Hamelto<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            as of my most gratious Soveraigne Kinge Iames. seeing I know <lb/>
            whom to accuse. My P<ex>ro</ex>fessio<ex>n</ex> of Phisicke nor my educatio<ex>n</ex> to l<ex>ett</ex>res <lb/>
            cannot serve to hinder mee fro<ex>m</ex> vndertaking the hardest e<ex>n</ex>terprise <lb/>
            that ever anye Romane vndertooke, soe farr as the lawe of co<ex>n</ex>science <lb/>
            will give waye
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">
               <lg>
                  <l>why shall I staye at thy decaye of Hameltons the hope </l>
                  <l>why shall I see thy foe soe free vnto his Ioye giue scope </l>
                  <l>Rather I praye a dolefull daye set me in cruell fate </l>
                  <l>Then thy death strange without revenge or him in safe estate./</l>
               </lg>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">
               <lg>
                  <l>This Soule to Heauens hand to the dead I vowe </l>
                  <l>noe fraudfull mynde, noe trembling hand I haue </l>
                  <l>If Pen it shun, the Sworde reuenge shall followe </l>
                  <l>Soule Pen and Sword w<ex>ha</ex>t thinge but iust doe craue /</l>
               </lg>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            What affection I bore to the living, the same shall acco<ex>m</ex>panye <lb/>
            the dead. For when one whose truthe and sinceritie was well <lb/>
            knowne to mee, told mee that it were better for the cheiffest of <lb/>
            my Freindes the Marquesse Hamelton to be quiett at home <lb/>
            in Scottland then to be eminent in the Courte of England, to who<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            by the opynion of all the wisest sorte, his being at Courte woulde <lb/>
            cost him noe lesse then his liffe, such that I stretching forth my <lb/>
            Arme (appr<ex>e</ex>hending some plottes laid against him) answered, If no <lb/>
            man dare revenge his death I vowe to God this hand shall reveng <lb/>
            it Scarcelye any other cause can be found then the bond of o<ex>u</ex>r most <lb/>
            close Freindshipp. Whye in the scroll of the Noblemens names <lb/>
            whoe <add place="above">w</add>ere to be killed, should I be sett downe next to <ex>th</ex>e ma<ex>r</ex>quesse <lb/>
            of Hamelton) in these wordes (<hi rend="italic">The Marquesse of Hamelton &amp; doctor <lb/>
            Eglisham to Embalme him</hi>) to witt, to the end that noe discoverer <lb/>
            or Revenger should be left. This Roll of names (I knowe not <lb/>
            by what destinie) was found nere vnto Westminster about the <lb/>
            tyme of the duke of Richmondes deathe, and, brought to the Lorde <lb/>
            marquesse by his Cozin the daughter of the Lord Oldbar one of <lb/>
            the pr<ex>i</ex>vye Councell of Scottland, did cause noe terror in mee <lb/>
            vntill that I did see the marquesse poysoned, and remembred <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            the rest therein noted were dead, and my selfe next pointed <lb/>
            at survivinge, whye staye I anye more. the case requireth the <lb/>
            pen noe more, but the sworde /
         </p>
         <p>
            I doe not writte soe boldlye because I am among Bucking<ex>hams</ex> <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Enimyes</fw>
            <pb n="34r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f034r/add_ms_22591_f034r.jpg"/>
            Enemies, but I haue retired my selfe to his Enemies, because <lb/>
            I was resolved to write, &amp; doe earnestlye against him as <del rend="strikethrough">m</del> <lb/>
            maye appeare/
         </p>
         <p>
            For since the Marquesse of Hameltons death, the most noble <lb/>
            Marquesse of Fiatta Ambassador for the most Christian Kinge of <lb/>
            Fraunce, and allsoe Buckinghams Mother sent on everye side to seeke, <lb/>
            invitinge mee to them, but I did forsake them, knowing certainelye <lb/>
            the falshood of Buckingham, whoe would rather haue suffered <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Ambassador to haue receaved an affront, then to be vnsatisfyed of <lb/>
            his bloudthirstie desire of my bloud, to silence mee w<ex>i</ex>th death (for <lb/>
            according to the Proverbe <hi rend="italic">The dead man cannot bite</hi>) <ex>i</ex>f he could <lb/>
            haue found mee. For my Lord Duke of Lenox, whoe was ofte<ex>n</ex> crosed <lb/>
            by Buckingham, w<ex>i</ex>th his Brother, and the Earle of Southampto<ex>n</ex> and <lb/>
            others nowe dead, was one of the Roll found of those that were to <lb/>
            be murthered, well assured mee, that were Buckingha<ex>m</ex> once mis=<lb break="no"/>
            liked, noe Apologie, noe Submission, noe reconciliac<ex>i</ex>on could kepe <lb/>
            him from doinge mischeife, Neither doe I write this in this fashio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            soe freelye for any entertainem<ex>en</ex>t here pr<ex>e</ex>sent, which I haue not <lb/>
            now anye future, w<ex>hi</ex>ch I haue noe ground to looke for, seeinge <lb/>
            Buckingham hath soe misledd yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty, that he hath caused not <lb/>
            onlye heere, but also allsoe vnto all nations, all Brittaines natives <lb/>
            to be disgraced and mistrusted, yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tyes royall worde w<ex>hi</ex>ch should <lb/>
            be inviolable, yo<ex>u</ex>r hand and seale w<ex>hi</ex>ch should be true to be most <lb/>
            shamefullye violated, and yo<ex>u</ex>rselfe to be held most ingrate for <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r most kinde vsage in Spaine, w<ex>hi</ex>ch Buckingha<ex>m</ex> maketh to be requited <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th iniuries in A most base and false manner, vnder p<ex>ro</ex>testation <lb/>
            of Friendshipp, (A bloudye warre being kindled on both sydes) <lb/>
            whereby he hath buryed w<ex>i</ex>th Kinge Iames the glorious title of <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Peace-maker Kinge</hi>, whoe had done much more iustlye &amp; advisedly <lb/>
            if he had procured peace vnto Christendome, whereby small <lb/>
            hope I haue obteyning pardon in my iust complainte, vnto wh<ex>i</ex>ch <lb/>
            my true affection vnto my dead Freindes murthered and the <lb/>
            extreame detestac<ex>i</ex>on of Buckingha<ex>m</ex> his violent pr<ex>o</ex>ceedinge hath <lb/>
            brought mee. yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ty maye finde most iust forces of reason to <lb/>
            accuse him in my Petition to the Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t, w<ex>hi</ex>ch shall serue for a <lb/>
            t<add place="above">o</add>uchstone to yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tye, and A Whetstone to mee and many other <lb/>
            Scottishmen. And w<ex>hi</ex>ch (yf it be neglected) will make yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ty to <lb/>
            incurr such A censure amonge all vertuous men in the world, <lb/>
            that yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tye will be loathe to heare of, and I astonished to ex=<lb break="no"/>
            presse at this tyme. <hi rend="italics">A Serpent lurketh in the Grase</hi>. Noe oth<ex>e</ex>r way <lb/>
            there is to be found to save yo<ex>u</ex>r honor, but to give waye to Iustice <lb/>
            against the Traytor Buckingha<ex>m</ex>, by whom manifest daunger ap=<lb break="no"/>
            proached vnto Kinge Iames. If yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tye will take anye cou<ex>r</ex>se <lb/>
            therein the examinac<ex>i</ex>on vpo<ex>n</ex> oath of all those that were about the <lb/>
            kinge and the marquesse of Hamelton in their sicknes, or at <ex>the</ex>ir <lb/>
            deathes, or after their deathes, before indifferent Iudges (noe <lb/>
            depend<ex>e</ex>rs vpo<ex>n</ex> Bucking<ex>ham</ex>) will serue for sufficient proffe of Buc<ex>kinghams</ex> <lb/>
            guiltines. In <ex>th</ex>e meane tyme vntill I see what shalbe <ex>th</ex>e yssue of <lb/>
            my co<ex>m</ex>plainte w<ex>i</ex>thout anye more speech I rest / yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s daly suppl<ex>ican</ex>t <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">
                    <hi rend="italic">Geo<ex>rge</ex> Eglisha<ex>m</ex>
                    </hi> To</fw> 
         </p>
         <pb n="34v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f034v/add_ms_22591_f034v.jpg"/>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="bold">
               To the <lb/>
               Most hono<ex>ra</ex>ble <ex>th</ex>e Nobillitye Knights and <lb/>
               Burgeses of Both <ex>th</ex>e houses of Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t <lb/>
               of the <lb/>
               Kingdome of Englande
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">
               The humble Petition of Mr George <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Eglisham</hi> Doctor of Physick and <lb/>
               one of the Phisitians to K<ex>ing</ex> Iames <lb/>
               of happie memorie for his ma<ex>jes</ex>ties <lb/>
               Person aboue the space of 10: yeeres /
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            Whereas <ex>the</ex> Cheiffe humaine care of Kinges and Courtes <lb/>
            of Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t is the pr<ex>e</ex>servation and protection of the subiects <lb/>
            lyves, Liberties, and estates from private or publique iniuryes, <lb/>
            to the end that all thinges maye be carryed w<ex>i</ex>thin the equall bal=<lb break="no"/>
            lance of Iustice, w<ex>i</ex>thout the w<ex>hi</ex>ch noe Monarstie, noe Como<ex>n</ex> wealthe <lb/>
            noe Societie, noe Familie, yea noe mans liffe or estate canne <lb/>
            consist, albeit never soe litle, It cannot be thought vniust to de=<lb break="no"/>
            maund of Kinges and Parlyam<ex>en</ex>ts the censure of wrongs. The <lb/>
            Considerac<ex>i</ex>on whereof was soe greate in our late monarche <lb/>
            of happye Memorye Kinge Iames, that he hath often publiquelye <lb/>
            p<ex>ro</ex>tested even in the presence of his apparant heire, <ex>tha</ex>t if his <lb/>
            owne Sonne should com<ex>m</ex>itt Murther, or anye such execrable act <lb/>
            of iniustice, he would not spare him, but would haue him dye <lb/>
            for it, and would haue him more severelye punished then anye <lb/>
            other. For hee well observed noe greater iniustice, noe iniquity <lb/>
            more intollerable can be done by man to man then murther In <lb/>
            all other wronges Fortune hath recourse, the losses of honor or <lb/>
            Goodes maye be repayred, satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on maye be made, reconcilyac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            maie be p<ex>ro</ex>cured, soe longe as the p<ex>ar</ex>tie iniured is alive, but when <lb/>
            the person murthered is bereft of his liffe, what can restore <lb/>
            it. what satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on can be given him, where shall the murtherer <lb/>
            meete w<ex>i</ex>th him to be reconciled to him, vnlesse he be sent out of <lb/>
            this world to followe his spirritt, w<ex>hi</ex>ch by his wickednesse he hath <lb/>
            sep<ex>ar</ex>ated fro<ex>m</ex> his bodye. Therefore of all iniuries, of all <ex>th</ex>e acts <lb/>
            of iniustice, and of all thinges most to be looked into, murther <lb/>
            is the greatest, and of all murthers the poysoning, vnder trust <lb/>
            and profession of Freindshipp, is the most haynous, w<ex>hi</ex>ch if you <lb/>
            suffer to goe vnpunished, lett noe man thinke themselves soe <lb/>
            secure to live amongst you, as amongst the wildest and most <lb/>
            furious Beasts in the world. For by vigilancie &amp; industrie <lb/>
            meanes maye be had to resist or evite the most violent beast <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">that</fw>
            <pb n="35r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f035r/add_ms_22591_f035r.jpg"/>
            that ever nature bredd, by whom false and treacherous harts <lb/>
            from poysoning murtherers what witt or wisedome can defend, <lb/>
            This concernes yo<ex>u</ex>r Lo<ex>rdshi</ex>pps everye one in p<ex>ar</ex>ticuler aswell as any, <lb/>
            They of whose poysoning yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner Co<ex>m</ex>playneth, to witt King <lb/>
            Iames, The Marquesse Hamelton, and others whose names aft<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            shalbe expressed, haue bine the most eminent in the kingedome, and <lb/>
            sate on those honorable Benches whereon yo<ex>u</ex>r honors nowe doe sitt <lb/>
            The p<ex>ar</ex>tie whom yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner accuseth, the duke of Buckingha<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            is soe powerfull that vnlesse the whole bodye of Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t laye <lb/>
            hold on him, noe Iustice can be had of him. For what place is <lb/>
            there of Iustice? what office of the Crowne? what degree of hon<ex>o</ex>r <lb/>
            in the Kingdome, w<ex>h</ex>ich he hath not sold? and sould w<ex>i</ex>th such craft <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            he can shake the buyers out of them and intrude others at his plea=<lb break="no"/>
            sure. All the Iudges of the Kingdome, all <ex>th</ex>e officers of the State <lb/>
            are his bound Vassalls or Allies, or affraide to become his out=<lb break="no"/>
            casts, as is notorious to all his ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s true and loving Subiects yea <lb/>
            soe farr hath his ambitious practise gone, <ex>tha</ex>t what he would haue <lb/>
            done, should haue bine p<ex>er</ex>formed whether the kinge would or not, <lb/>
            and what the Kinge would have done, could not be done yf hee <lb/>
            opposed, whereof manye instances maye be given whensoever <lb/>
            they shalbe required, neither are they vnknowne to this hon<ex>or</ex>able <lb/>
            assemblye. Howsoever the meanes he vseth be lawfull or vnlaw=<lb break="no"/>
            full, humaine or diabolicke, soe hee tortureth the kingdome, that <lb/>
            he p<ex>ro</ex>cures the calling, breaking or continewing of Parlyam<ex>en</ex>tes at <lb/>
            his pleasure, placing or displacinge the officers of Iustice, of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Cou<ex>n</ex>cell, of the Kings Cou<ex>r</ex>te, of the Courtes of Iustice to his viole<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
            pleasure, and his ambitious vilanie moveth him. What hope <lb/>
            then can yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tye haue that this complaint shall be heard, or being <lb/>
            heard, shall take effect, to obtaine Iustice he maye dispaire, to <lb/>
            p<ex>ro</ex>voke the duke to send forth A poysoner, or other murtherer to <lb/>
            dispatche him, and to send him after his dead Freindes allready <lb/>
            murthered, he maye be sure this to be the event. Let the event be w<ex>ha</ex>t <lb/>
            it will, come whatsoever can come the losse of his owne liffe yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Petitioner valueth not, having suffered the losse of the lives of <lb/>
            such eminent Freindes, esteeming his liffe can be noe better besto=<lb break="no"/>
            wed then vpon the discoverye of the haynous murtherers. yea the <lb/>
            iustnes of the cause, the dearnes and neerenes of his Freindes <lb/>
            murthered, shall pr<ex>e</ex>vayle soe farr w<ex>i</ex>th him, that he shall vnfolde <lb/>
            vnto yo<ex>u</ex>r honors and to the whole world these reasonns ag<ex>ain</ex>st <ex>th</ex>e accused <lb/>
            and named by him the author of soe great murthers <hi rend="italic">Georg Villiers <lb/>
            Duke of Buckingham</hi> w<ex>hi</ex>ch ag<ex>ain</ex>st anye pr<ex>i</ex>vate man are sufficient for <lb/>
            his appr<ex>e</ex>henc<ex>i</ex>on and torture.  And to make his complaint not very <lb/>
            tedious, he will onlye for the pr<ex>e</ex>sent declare vnto yo<ex>u</ex>r honors the <lb/>
            two most eminent murthers committed by Buckingham, to witt of <lb/>
            the Kings ma<ex>jes</ex>tye, and of the Marquesse of Hamelton, w<ex>hi</ex>ch for all <lb/>
            the subtiltie of his poysoninge art could not be soe cunninglye <lb/>
            conveyed as the Murtherer thought, but that God hath discovered <lb/>
            manifestlye the Author. And to obserue the order of the tyme <lb/>
            of their deathe, because the Lord Marquesse of Hamelton dyed <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">first</fw>
            <pb n="35v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f035v/add_ms_22591_f035v.jpg"/>
            first, his death shall be first related, even from the roote of his <lb/>
            last quarrell w<ex>i</ex>th Buckingham, albeit manye other quarrells <lb/>
            haue p<ex>ro</ex>ceeded fro<ex>m</ex> tyme to tyme betwixt them /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               ❀ <hi rend="italic">Concerninge the <lb/>
               Poysoninge of the <lb/>
               Marquesse <lb/>
               of Hameltonne /</hi>
            </add>
            ❀ Buckingha<ex>m</ex> once raysed from the bottome to the toppe of <lb/>
            Fortunes wheele, by what deserte by w<ex>ha</ex>t right or wronge, noe <lb/>
            matter is it by his carryage verified the p<ex>ro</ex>verbe <hi rend="italic">Nothinge more <lb/>
            Proude then baser bred when it doth rise aloft</hi> suffered his <lb/>
            ambition to carrie himselfe soe farr, as to aspire to match <lb/>
            his bloude with the bloud royall both of England &amp; Scottlande, <lb/>
            and well knowing that the Lord marquesse of Hamelton was ac=<lb break="no"/>
            knowledged by Kinge Iames to be the prime man in his dominio<ex>n</ex>s <lb/>
            whoe next to his owne lyne in his proper season might clame an <lb/>
            hereditarie Title to the kingdome of Scottland by the daughter of <lb/>
            Kinge Iames the Second, and to the Crowne of England by Iohan <lb/>
            of Somersett wiffe to king Iames the First, declared by Act <lb/>
            of Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t heretrixe of England in her due ranke, neu<ex>er</ex> suffered <lb/>
            the Kinge to be at rest, but vrged him allwayes to send some of <lb/>
            the privye Cou<ex>n</ex>sell to sollicite the marquesse to matche his eldest <lb/>
            Sonne w<ex>i</ex>th Buckinghams Neece, making great p<ex>ro</ex>misses of co<ex>n</ex>dit<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>s <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch the meane Familye of the Bride could not p<ex>er</ex>forme, without <lb/>
            the kings liberallitie, to witt fiftye thowsand pounds sterling (val=<lb break="no"/>
            luinge five hundred thousand Florins) w<ex>i</ex>th the Earledome of <lb/>
            Orkenay vnder the Tytle of A duke, whatsoever the Marquesse <lb/>
            would accept, even to be the First Duke of Brittanie. The glorious <lb/>
            Title of A duke <ex>th</ex>e marquesse refused twice vpo<ex>n</ex> severall reasons <lb/>
            reserved to himselfe. The matter of monye was noe motive to <lb/>
            cause the Marquesse to matche his sonne soe vnequallye to his <lb/>
            degree, Seeing Buckingham himselfe the cheiffe of his kindred <lb/>
            was but A novice in Nobillitye, his Father obscure among Gntle=<lb break="no"/>
            men, his mother A serving Woman, and he being infamous for <lb/>
            his Frequent consultac<ex>i</ex>ons w<ex>i</ex>th the Ringlead<ex>e</ex>rs of Witches, prin=<lb break="no"/>
            cipallye w<ex>i</ex>th that false doctor Lambe, publiquelye condemned for <lb/>
            witchcraft, whereby the marquesse knowing that the kinge was <lb/>
            soe farr bewitched to Buckingham <ex>tha</ex>t if he refused <ex>th</ex>e Matche <lb/>
            demaunded, he should finde the kings deadlye hate against him, <lb/>
            and seeing that Buckinghams Neece was not yett <hi rend="italic">nubile</hi> in yeares, <lb/>
            and that before the mariage should be confirmed, a waye might <lb/>
            be found out to annull it, vnto w<ex>hi</ex>ch he was forced by a deceiptfull <lb/>
            importunitie, therefore he yeilded vnto the Kings desire of the <lb/>
            matche, Wherevpon Buckingham and his faction, fearinge that <lb/>
            delaies might breed letts, vrged my Lord Marquesse to send <lb/>
            for his Sonne vpo<ex>n</ex> A Sunday Morning betymes in all hast fro<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            London to Courte at Greenewitch, where never A word was <lb/>
            spoken of marriage to the young Lord till a little before supp<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            And to make it more authenticke Buckingham caused his <lb/>
            Neece to be laid A bedd w<ex>i</ex>th the marquesse his sonne for a <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">short</fw>
            <pb n="36r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f036r/add_ms_22591_f036r.jpg"/>
            shorte tyme in the kings Chamber, and in his ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s pr<ex>e</ex>sence <lb/>
            albeit the Bride was yet <hi rend="italic">innubile</hi>. manye were astonished <lb/>
            at the suddaine newes thereof, all the marquesse his Freindes <lb/>
            fretting thereat, and writting vnto him verye scornefull <lb/>
            letters for the same. The marquesse having satisfyed <ex>th</ex>e Kinges <lb/>
            demaund, did what he could to pr<ex>e</ex>vent the confirmation of <lb/>
            the Marriage, and intended to send his Sonne beyond <ex>th</ex>e Seas, <lb/>
            to travell throughe Fraunce and Italye, and soe to passe his <lb/>
            tyme abroad, vntill the tyme that meanes were found to vntie <lb/>
            that knott w<ex>hi</ex>ch Buckingha<ex>m</ex> had vrged the kinge to fasten vpo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            his Sonne. But Buckingham to controvert the marquesses designe, <lb/>
            caused the Kinge and the Prince to make the marquesses Sonne <lb/>
            to be sworne gent<ex>leman</ex> of the Princes Bed Chamber, and soe to be <lb/>
            deteyned w<ex>i</ex>th him w<ex>i</ex>thin the kingdome vntill that <ex>th</ex>e Bride should <lb/>
            bee of yeares ripe for marriage /
         </p>
         <p>
            The tyme expired that Buckinghams Neece became mar<lb break="no"/>
            riagable, Buckingham sent to the Marquesse to desire him <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            the Marriage might be compleatlye confirmed. The Marquese <lb/>
            not willing to heare of anye such matter, answered breiffelye <lb/>
            he scorned the Motion. This answere reported to Buckingham, <lb/>
            and he seeing himselfe vnlikelye of his ambitions matchinge of <lb/>
            his Neece, and p<ex>er</ex>ceaving that the Lord Marquesse was able to <del rend="strikethrough">ra</del> <lb/>
            raise a great Faction against him, whether Kinge Iames did <lb/>
            live or dye, was mightelye incensed against the Marquesse, <lb/>
            and at his first encounter w<ex>i</ex>th him did challenge him of speak=<lb break="no"/>
            inge disdainefullye of him and his house. The Marquesse re=<lb break="no"/>
            plyed that he did not remember of any offensive words vttered <lb/>
            by himselfe against Buckingham. Then Buckingham prowdlye <lb/>
            said <del rend="strikethrough">aut</del> vnto him, Out of thine owne wordes I will iudge thee, <lb/>
            for you haue said you scorned the motion of matchinge w<ex>i</ex>th my <lb/>
            house, w<ex>hi</ex>ch I made vnto you. The Marquesse answered that if <lb/>
            he had said soe, it became not the duke to speake to him in that <lb/>
            fashion, Soe Buckingham threatned to be revenged, <ex>th</ex>e Mar=<lb break="no"/>
            quesse vttered his defyance, and thus the quarrell began: w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            fower or five times reiterated, and as often recounted by the <lb/>
            Marquesse <hi rend="italic">de Fiatta</hi> a litle before the Marquesse of Hamelto<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            fell sicke: where it is evident that the quarrell hath bine very <lb/>
            violent that need soe manye reconciliations. The dukes fyre <lb/>
            of his anger being inextinguished as king Iames oft did censure <lb/>
            him in his absence albeit a Favorite, that he was wonderfully <lb/>
            vindicative, whose mallice insatiable to my Lord Marquesse <lb/>
            of Hamelton did well shewe itselfe as shall appeare heere=<lb break="no"/>
            after, Hardlye can any man tell whether by the Marquesse <lb/>
            in his Sicknes Buckingham was more supported then accused <lb/>
            of the poison given, or to be given him, For he would not trust <lb/>
            of anye thinge that was sent vnto him by any of Buckinghams <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Freindes</fw>
            <pb n="36v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f036v/add_ms_22591_f036v.jpg"/>
            Freindes, but he would first haue some of his Servantes tast <lb/>
            it before, and for the love that was mutuall betwixt him and <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner, whom he would never suffer to goe out of his <lb/>
            sight, during his sicknesse, yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner allsoe tasted of all <lb/>
            that he tooke at that tyme, vnto whom his suspic<ex>i</ex>on of Bucking<ex>ham</ex> <lb/>
            he expressed by name and to other sufficient wittnesses, whoe <lb/>
            will iustifye it vpo<ex>n</ex> Oathe, yf there be anye course taken ther<lb break="no"/>
            in for the searche therof. All the tyme of his Sicknesse hee <lb/>
            intreated yo<ex>u</ex>r Petioner not to suffer my Lord of Buckingha<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            to come neere him, But yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner hauing often sent word <lb/>
            and allsoe sometymes signified himselfe to Buckingham that <lb/>
            there was noe fitt oppertunitie to see the Marquesse p<ex>re</ex>ten<lb break="no"/>
            dinge some thinge to be ministred vnto him. But when yo<ex>u</ex>r Pet<ex>itioner</ex> <lb/>
            could finde noe more excuses, hee told my Lord Marquesse <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            he had put my Lord of Buckingha<ex>m</ex> awaye soe often, that he could <lb/>
            not keepe him awaie anye longer, but that he must needes see <lb/>
            him. Then he knowing Buckinghams visitt to p<ex>ro</ex>ceed of dissimu=<lb break="no"/>
            lation, requested yo<ex>u</ex>r Pet<ex>itioner</ex> at least, to find the meanes to gett <lb/>
            him awaye quicklye, w<ex>hi</ex>ch yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner did, interrupting Buc<ex>kinghams</ex> <lb/>
            discourse, and intreating him to suffer my Lord Marquesse to <lb/>
            be quiett, This did evidentlye shewe my Lord Marquesse his dis=<lb break="no"/>
            liking and distrusting of Buckingham, whereas he was well <lb/>
            pleased w<ex>i</ex>th other Noble Mens companye all the time of his <lb/>
            Sicknes. The duke and my Lord Denbigh would not suffer his <lb/>
            owne Sonne to come to him, pr<ex>e</ex>tending <ex>tha</ex>t he was sicke w<ex>hi</ex>ch was <lb/>
            false, For at the tyme that my Lord Marquesse called for him <lb/>
            after <ex>tha</ex>t yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner advised his L<ex>ordshi</ex>pp to dispose of his Estate <lb/>
            and of his conscience, because his sicknes was not w<ex>i</ex>thout dau<ex>n</ex>g<ex>e</ex>r, <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch yo<ex>u</ex>r Petiotioner foure dayes before my Lords death, did in <lb/>
            such manner, that he gaue him noe cause to dispayre of his health <lb/>
            but intreated him to comitt all the care of his health to God <lb/>
            and his Phisitions, assuring him howsoever hee had gotten <lb/>
            wronge abroad, hee should gett none in <ex>th</ex>e Cure of his disease <lb/>
            At length his Lo<ex>rdshi</ex>pp burst out into these wordes to my Lorde <lb/>
            Denbigh. It is A great crueltie in you, <ex>tha</ex>t you will not suffer <lb/>
            my Sonne to come to me whilest I am a dying <ex>tha</ex>t I maye see <lb/>
            him and speake to him before I dye. Soe they delayed his <lb/>
            cominge w<ex>i</ex>th excuses vntill my Lord his agonye of death was <lb/>
            neere <del rend="strikethrough">him</del>, to the end that hee should not haue tyme to give his <lb/>
            Sonne private Instructions, to shun the mariage of Bucking<ex>hams</ex> <lb/>
            Neece, or to signifye vnto him the suspic<ex>i</ex>on <ex>tha</ex>t he had of Poyso<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            For they had rather his Sonne should knowe anye thinge then eith<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            of these. yet manye did suspect his poyson before he dyed. For <lb/>
            two dayes before his death two of his servantes dyed w<ex>i</ex>th manifest <lb/>
            Signes and simptomes of poyson, one belonging to his wine <lb/>
            Celler and another to his Kitchin /
         </p>
         <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">The</fw>
         <pb n="37r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f037r/add_ms_22591_f037r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            The Fatall houre being come <ex>tha</ex>t my Lord marquesse de=<lb break="no"/>
            ceased, yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner entreated them that were present <lb/>
            to suffer noe man to touch his Bodye vntill <ex>tha</ex>t he retourned <lb/>
            to see it opened, for then he p<ex>ro</ex>tested earnestlye, that all the time <lb/>
            of his Sicknes, he iudged himselfe to be poysoned, and in all con=<lb break="no"/>
            sultac<ex>i</ex>ons vrged Antidotes to be administred. But this poyson <lb/>
            was such and soe farre gon, that none could helpe. Neu<ex>er</ex>thelesse <lb/>
            to haue the matter concealed Buckinghams Folkes would haue <lb/>
            had him buryed that same <del rend="strikethrough">daye</del> night in Westminster Church, &amp; <lb/>
            the Ceremonyes of the Buriall to be made afterwards, saying <lb/>
            that such delicate bodyes as his could not be longe kept. But his <lb/>
            Freindes taking hold of the caveat given them by yo<ex>u</ex>r Petition<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            refused soe to doe, and replyed that they would haue him (as <lb/>
            became him) buryed in Scottland in his owne Chappell, where <lb/>
            his Ancestors haue bine buyed about these 400: yeeres agoe, <lb/>
            and that his Bodye must be first visited by his Phisitions. /
         </p>
         <p>
            Noe sooner was he dead, when the force of the Poyson had <lb/>
            overcome the Forces of his Bodye, but it began to swell in <lb/>
            such sort, that his thighes were as bigg as sixe times <ex>th</ex>e natu<ex>r</ex>all <lb/>
            Proporc<ex>i</ex>on his Bellye became as bigg as the bellye of an Oxe, <lb/>
            his Armes as Bige, as the naturall quantitye of his thighes, <lb/>
            his Necke soe broade as his Shoulders, his Cheekes over the <lb/>
            topp of his Nose, that his Nose could not be seene or extingui<lb break="no"/>
            shed, the Skynne of his Forehead over his Eyes, and the same <lb/>
            skinne w<ex>i</ex>th all the rest of the skynne of his head two fingers <lb/>
            highe swelled, his haire of his beard Eyebrowes &amp; head soe <lb/>
            farre distant one fro<ex>m</ex> another as if an hundred had bine taken <lb/>
            out betwixt everye one, and when one did touch his haire it <lb/>
            came awaye w<ex>i</ex>th the Skynne as easilye as if one had pulled hay <lb/>
            out of A heape of haye, He was all over his breast Necke, <lb/>
            Shoulders and Armes blistered w<ex>i</ex>th Blisters as bigge as <lb/>
            ones Fist, w<ex>i</ex>th Blisters I saye of sixe divers colours full of <lb/>
            Waters of the same colours, some whit, some Blacke, some red, <lb/>
            some yellowe, some greene, some blewe, and that as well w<ex>i</ex>thin <lb/>
            his bodye as without. Allsoe the Carities of his Liver greene, <lb/>
            his Stomacke in some places a litle purpurated, w<ex>i</ex>th a blewish <lb/>
            calami<ex>n</ex>e matter adheringe to the sides of it, his mouthe and <lb/>
            Nose fominge bloude mixt w<ex>i</ex>th Froth of divers collors a yard high
         </p>
         <p>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner being sent for to come visitt his Bodye, <lb/>
            and his Servants all flocking about him, sayinge, see, see pre=<lb break="no"/>
            sentlye weepinge said he was poysoned, and that it was a thing <lb/>
            not to be suffered. Moreover he said that albeit his speech might <lb/>
            cost him his liffe, yet seeing his sorrowe had extorted <ex>tha</ex>t speech <lb/>
            out of him, hee would make it manifest, and would haue a Iury <lb/>
            of Phisitians pr<ex>e</ex>sent.  Some of my Lord Marquesse of Hamelt<ex>on</ex>s <lb/>
            Freindes saide, wee must send to my Lord duke that hee maye <lb/>
            send his Phisitians. But yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner replyed, what haue <lb/>
            wee to do w<ex>i</ex>th the dukes Phisitians. Let vs haue indiffere<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
            men. Captaine Hamelton hearinge yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner soe boldlye <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">take</fw>
            <pb n="37v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f037v/add_ms_22591_f037v.jpg"/>
            take excepc<ex>i</ex>ons at Buckingham, and iudging that he had good <lb/>
            reason for w<ex>ha</ex>t he had spoken, said, for all that let vs send to the <lb/>
            duke, and signifye <ex>tha</ex>t they all whoe see the Marquesses body both <lb/>
            Phisitions and Surgions and others, thinke that he is poysoned, &amp; <lb/>
            that his Freindes desire more Phisicons out of the Colledge of <lb/>
            London besides the dukes Phisitions to beare wittnes in w<ex>ha</ex>t case <lb/>
            the marquesses bodye is in, and then if the dukes conscience be <lb/>
            guiltie (said the Captaine) it will shewe itself, w<ex>hi</ex>ch indeed it did, <lb/>
            For the duke being advertised thereof, sent for his owne Phisici<ex>on</ex>s <lb/>
            and others out of London, whom he caused first to be brought <lb/>
            to him before they went to see the marquesses bodye giveinge <lb/>
            them his direcc<ex>i</ex>ons in these wordes. My m<ex>aste</ex>rs there is A bruite <lb/>
            spread abroade that the marquesse of Hamelton is poysoned. <lb/>
            Goe and see, but beware what you speake of Poyson (w<ex>hi</ex>ch he said <lb/>
            in A threatning forme of deliverye) for nowe everye Nobleman <lb/>
            that dyeth must be poysoned. If his conscience had not bine guilty <lb/>
            should he not haue comaunded the Phisitions to enquire by all <lb/>
            meanes possible, and make it knowne rather then to suppresse <lb/>
            the speech of the poysoninge. These Phisitions being come, your <lb/>
            Petitioner w<ex>i</ex>th the one hand leading doctor More to the Table wher <lb/>
            the marquesses bodye was layd to be opened, and w<ex>i</ex>th the other <lb/>
            hand throwing of the Clothes from the Bodye, said to him, looke you <lb/>
            heerevpon this pittifull spectacle. At the sight whereof doctor <lb/>
            Moore lifting vpp both his handes, and his Hatt, and his eyes to <lb/>
            the Heavens astonished, said Iesus blesse mee, I never sawe the <lb/>
            like I cannot knowe him, I cannot distinguish A Face vppo<ex>n</ex> him, <lb/>
            And in like manner all the rest of the doctors and allsoe <ex>th</ex>e Su<ex>r</ex>gio<ex>n</ex>s <lb/>
            affirmed <ex>tha</ex>t they never sawe the like, albeit they had travelled and <lb/>
            practised throughe the greatest p<ex>ar</ex>te of Europe, Onlye one that <lb/>
            sawe my Lord of Southamptons bodye opened in Holland (w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            Lord was allsoe one of Buckinghams opposites) said that my Lord <lb/>
            of Southampto<ex>n</ex>s bodye was blistered all w<ex>i</ex>thin the breast as my Lord <lb/>
            Marquesses was. doctor Lister one of my Lord of Buckinghams <lb/>
            Creatures, seeing doctor Moore and others soe amazed at <ex>th</ex>e sight <lb/>
            of my Lords Bodye, drewe first him aside, and then the oth<ex>e</ex>rs one <lb/>
            after another, and whisp<ex>er</ex>ed them in the Eare to silence them. Where <lb/>
            vpon manye went awaye w<ex>i</ex>thout speaking one word, the others <lb/>
            whoe remayned acknowledged those accidents of the dead bodye <lb/>
            could not be w<ex>i</ex>thout poyson, but they said the could not know how <lb/>
            such A subtile art of poysoning could be brought into England <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r Petition<ex>er</ex> replying <ex>tha</ex>t monye could bringe both the Arte and <lb/>
            the Artist fro<ex>m</ex> the farthest p<ex>ar</ex>tes of the world into England. From <lb/>
            whence since yo<ex>u</ex>r Petition<ex>er</ex> dap<ex>ar</ex>ted, hee hath conferred w<ex>i</ex>th the <lb/>
            skillfullest Pestmakers that could be found, whoe visitt <ex>th</ex>e bodys <lb/>
            of those that dye, of the Venim of the Pest, They all admire the <lb/>
            discripc<ex>i</ex>on of my Lord Marquesses bodye, and testifye <ex>tha</ex>t never <lb/>
            anye of the Pest haue such accidents, but Carbuncles, bubons, or <lb/>
            the Spotts, noe such huge blisters with waters, and such huge <lb/>
            vnifirme swellinge to such dimensities about sixe tymes <ex>the</ex> natu<ex>r</ex>all <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">p<ex>ro</ex>portio<ex>n</ex>
                </fw>
            <pb n="38r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f038r/add_ms_22591_f038r.jpg"/>
            p<ex>ro</ex>portion. But he hath mett w<ex>i</ex>th some whoe haue practised <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            poysoning of doggs, to trye the forces of some Antidotes, &amp; they <lb/>
            haue found that some poysonns haue made theire doggs sicke for <lb/>
            A Fortnight or more, w<ex>i</ex>thout anye swelling, vntill they were <lb/>
            dead, and then they swelled above measure, and became blistered <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th waters of divers colors, and the haire came awaye w<ex>i</ex>th the <lb/>
            skynne when it was touched
         </p>
         <p>
            The Phisitions then whoe remayned were willing to tes=<lb break="no"/>
            tifye w<ex>i</ex>th their owne hand written <ex>tha</ex>t my Lord marquesse was poy<lb break="no"/>
            soned, but yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner tould them it was not needfull, seeing <lb/>
            wee must attend Gods leasure to discover the Author, <ex>th</ex>e matter <lb/>
            being soe apparent and soe manye hundreds having seene his body <lb/>
            to wittnes it, for the dores were kept open for everye man to <lb/>
            behold &amp; to be wittnes whoe would, The duke of Buckingham <lb/>
            making some cou<ex>n</ex>terfeited shewe of Sorrowe to men of g<ex>rea</ex>t quallitie, <lb/>
            found noe other shift to divert the suspic<ex>i</ex>on of <ex>th</ex>e poysoning of the <lb/>
            marquesse fro<ex>m</ex> himselfe, but to laye it vppo<ex>n</ex> his m<ex>aste</ex>r the King, say=<lb break="no"/>
            inge that the marquesse for his p<ex>er</ex>son, Spirritt and carriage, was <lb/>
            such, <ex>tha</ex>t he was borne worthye to raigne, but the Kinge his mast<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            hated him to deathe, because he had A Spirritt too much for the <lb/>
            Comon wealth, whereby the duke shewed himselfe noe good sub=<lb break="no"/>
            iecte of the kings, whoe made the kings humor to be tyrannicall &amp; <lb/>
            the King a bloudthirstie murtherer, and A most vild dissembl<ex>e</ex>r, <lb/>
            haueing heaped soe manye honors daylye vpo<ex>n</ex> the marquesse even <lb/>
            to the verye last, making him Lord high Steward of his ma<ex>jes</ex>ties <lb/>
            house and Iudge of the Verge Court, who<ex>m</ex> he had made before vic<lb break="no"/>
            roye of Scotland, for <ex>th</ex>e time of Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t in Scotland, Earle of <lb/>
            Cambridge, A Privye Cou<ex>n</ex>sellor in England, &amp; K<ex>nigh</ex>t of the Garter, <lb/>
            as yf he had raysed him to all these honors, that <ex>th</ex>e murtheringe <lb/>
            of him might be the lesse suspected to p<ex>ro</ex>ceed fro<ex>m</ex> him
         </p>
         <p>
            The Kings nature hath bine allwayes observed to bee soe <lb/>
            gratious and soe free harted to everye one, <ex>tha</ex>t he would neu<ex>er</ex> haue <lb/>
            wished <ex>th</ex>e Marquesse anye harme, vnlesse <ex>tha</ex>t Bucking<ex>ham</ex> had put great <lb/>
            feares &amp; iealousies in his mynde, for yf anye other had done it, he <lb/>
            would haue acquainted his Favorite therew<ex>i</ex>th, &amp; then was it Bucking<ex>hams</ex> <lb/>
            dutie to remove fro<ex>m</ex> the Kinge such sinister conceipts of <ex>th</ex>e m<ex>ar</ex>quesse, <lb/>
            as the Marquesse hath often done for Bucking<ex>ham</ex>, vpholding him in all <lb/>
            occasions, &amp; keeping <ex>th</ex>e Kinge fro<ex>m</ex> giving waye to introduce anye <lb/>
            other Favorite Wherefore Buckingha<ex>m</ex> in <ex>tha</ex>t diverc<ex>i</ex>on of <ex>tha</ex>t cryme <lb/>
            fro<ex>m</ex> himselfe hath not onlye made the Kinge, but allsoe himselfe <lb/>
            guiltie of the marquesses death, But Buckinghams Falshood <lb/>
            &amp; evill intention long before was rightlye discou<ex>er</ex>ed, when he did <lb/>
            what he could to make the Earle of <hi rend="italic">Nithesdale</hi> and my L<ex>ord</ex> Gordon <lb/>
            both neere kinsmen to my Lord Marquesse soe incensed at him, that <lb/>
            they had likelye all three killed one another, yf it had not bine <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            my Lord Marquesse by his wisdome did let them all knowe howe <lb/>
            they were abused, yf anye dissimulation be greater the<ex>n</ex> Bucking<ex>hams</ex> <lb/>
            lett anye man iudge, For when my Lord Marquesses Bodye was <lb/>
            to be transported fro<ex>m</ex> w<ex>hi</ex>t hall to his house at Bishopsgate, Bucking<ex>ham</ex> <lb/>
            came out mufled and furred in his Coache, giving out that he was <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">sicke</fw>
            <pb n="38v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f038v/add_ms_22591_f038v.jpg"/>
            sicke for sorrowe of my Lord marquesses deathe, But soe soone <lb/>
            as he went to his house out of London before his Cominge to the <lb/>
            kinge he triumphed and deminered w<ex>i</ex>th his Faction soe excessively <lb/>
            as yf he had gayned some greate victorye, &amp; the next daye com<ex>m</ex>ing <lb/>
            to the kinge, put on A most lamentable &amp; mournefull cou<ex>n</ex>ten<ex>n</ex>ance <lb/>
            for the deathe of the Marquesse of Hamelton, Noe greater victorye <lb/>
            could he have gott to his Mynde then to haue distroyed <ex>tha</ex>t man, who <lb/>
            could and would haue fetched his head fro<ex>m</ex> his Shoulders, yf he had <lb/>
            out lived kinge Iames, to have knowne his carriage in <ex>th</ex>e poysoning <lb/>
            him in his sicknes, wherefore he thought it necessarye to remove <lb/>
            the marquesse before hand, The same daye <ex>tha</ex>t my Lord marquesse <lb/>
            dyed, Buckingham sent my Lord marquesse his sonne out of <ex>th</ex>e towne <lb/>
            keeping him as A Prisoner, <ex>tha</ex>t none could haue pr<ex>i</ex>vate co<ex>n</ex>ference <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th him, vntill his mariage of Bucking<ex>hams</ex> Neece was co<ex>m</ex>pleat, but all<lb break="no"/>
            wayes either my Lo<ex>rd</ex> Denbighe, or my Lady Denbighe or my Lord of <lb/>
            Bucking<ex>ham</ex> or <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse of Bucking<ex>ham</ex>, or <ex>th</ex>e Dutchesse of Bucking<ex>ham</ex> was <lb/>
            pr<ex>e</ex>sent, <ex>tha</ex>t none could lett him vnderstand how his Father was mu<ex>r</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            thered, yea yo<ex>u</ex>r Petition<ex>er</ex> himselfe when he went to see him w<ex>i</ex>thin <lb/>
            some fewe daies after his Fathers death, was intreated not to tell <lb/>
            him of <ex>th</ex>e poysoning of his Father, w<ex>hi</ex>ch he did conceale at his first mee=<lb break="no"/>
            tinge, because their sorrowe was too recent, Neither would Bucking<ex>ham</ex> <lb/>
            suffer the younge Lord to goe into Scottland to his Fath<ex>e</ex>rs funeralls <lb/>
            and to take order w<ex>i</ex>th his Freindes co<ex>n</ex>cerninge his Fathers estate, <lb/>
            for feare that <ex>the</ex>ir intended marriage should be overthrowne.  This <lb/>
            Captivitye of the Lo<ex>rd</ex> Marquesse lasted soe longe vntill <ex>tha</ex>t Bucking<ex>ham</ex> <lb/>
            caused his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye King Charles to take <ex>th</ex>e young Lord with himselfe <lb/>
            &amp; Bucking<ex>ham</ex> into S<ex>ain</ex>t Iames Parke, discharging all others to follow them <lb/>
            &amp; there to p<ex>er</ex>swade and vrge the young Lord w<ex>i</ex>thout anye more delay <lb/>
            to accomplish his marriage w<ex>i</ex>th Bucking<ex>hams</ex> Neece, w<ex>hi</ex>ch instantlye was <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>formed, soe <ex>tha</ex>t Bucking<ex>ham</ex> trusteth &amp; p<ex>re</ex>sumeth, <ex>tha</ex>t albeit the young Lo<ex>rd</ex> <lb/>
            should vnderstand how his Father was poysoned by his meanes,  yet <lb/>
            being marryed to his Neece, should not stirr to revenge it. To all w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            is observed before, it is worthie to be added, that <ex>th</ex>e bruite went <del rend="strikethrough">thro <lb/>
            </del>throughe London long before my Lord Duke of Richmonds deathe, or <lb/>
            his Brothers, or my Lord of Southamptons, or the Marquesses <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            all the Noblemen that were not of Buckinghams faction should be <lb/>
            poysoned, &amp; soe removed out of his waye, Allsoe A Paper was fou<ex>n</ex>d <lb/>
            in kingstreete about the tyme of the Duke of Richmonds death, where<lb break="no"/>
            in the names of all those Noblemen whoe haue dyed since were ex=<lb break="no"/>
            pressed, and yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioners name allsoe sett next to <ex>th</ex>e Lo<ex>rd</ex> Marqus <lb/>
            of Hameltons name, w<ex>i</ex>th these wordes to <hi rend="italic">embalme him</hi>. This pap<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            was brought him by my Lo<ex>rd</ex> <hi rend="italic">Oldbarres</hi> daughter cosen germaine <lb/>
            to the marquesse.  Likewise A Mountebanke about <ex>tha</ex>t time was great<lb break="no"/>
            lye cou<ex>n</ex>tenau<ex>n</ex>ced by the Duke of Bucking<ex>ham</ex>, &amp; by his meanes p<ex>ro</ex>cured <lb/>
            l<ex>ett</ex>res Patents &amp; recom<ex>m</ex>endac<ex>i</ex>on fro<ex>m</ex> <ex>th</ex>e kinge to practise his skill thro<add place="above">gh</add> <lb/>
            all Eng<ex>land</ex> whoe com<ex>m</ex>ing to Londo<ex>n</ex>, offered to sell poysons to kill men <lb/>
            or Beasts w<ex>i</ex>thin a yeare, or halfe yeare, or two yeares, or a month <lb/>
            or two, or what tyme pr<ex>e</ex>fixed anye man desired, in such sorte that they <lb/>
            could not be helped nor discovered, Moreover <ex>th</ex>e Christmas before <lb/>
            my Lord marquesse his death one of <ex>th</ex>e Princes Footemen saide <lb/>
            That some of <ex>th</ex>e great ones at Courte had gotten poyson in his <lb/>
            bellye but he could not tell whoe it was
         </p>
         <p>
            Heere yo<ex>u</ex>r honors considering <ex>th</ex>e pr<ex>e</ex>misses of my Lo<ex>rd</ex> of Bucking<ex>ham</ex> <lb/>
            his ambitious and most vindicative nature, his frequent quarrells <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">w<ex>i</ex>th</fw>
            <pb n="39r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f039r/add_ms_22591_f039r.jpg"/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th my Lord marquesse after soe manye reconciliac<ex>i</ex>ons, his threat=<lb break="no"/>
            ning of him, his threatning of the Phisitions to speake of poyson, <lb/>
            his triumphinge after my Lo<ex>rd</ex> marquesses death, his deteyninge of <lb/>
            his Sonne, allmost as A Prisoner vntill <ex>th</ex>e Marriage compleate w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            his Neece, th<ex>e</ex> pr<ex>e</ex>ceeding bruite of poysoning Bucking<ex>hams</ex> Adversaryes, <lb/>
            the pap<ex>er</ex> of their names found w<ex>i</ex>th sufficient intimation of <ex>the</ex>ir deathe <lb/>
            by the co<ex>n</ex>clusicon of <ex>th</ex>e word <hi rend="italic">Embalminge</hi>, <ex>th</ex>e poyson monger mounte=<lb break="no"/>
            bancke graced by Bucking<ex>ham</ex>, maye suffice for ground to take him &amp; tor=<lb break="no"/>
            ture him, yf he were A private man, And heerein yo<ex>u</ex>r Petition<ex>er</ex> most <lb/>
            hu<ex>m</ex>blye &amp; most earnestlye demau<ex>n</ex>deth Iustice ag<ex>ains</ex>t <ex>tha</ex>t Traytor, seeing by <lb/>
            Act of Parly<ex>am</ex>ent it is made Treason to co<ex>n</ex>spire the death of a privye <lb/>
            Cou<ex>n</ex>cellor, Out of this declarac<ex>i</ex>on Interrogatories maye be drawne <lb/>
            for examination of wittnesses, wherein more is discovered to begin <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thall, then was laid open at the begin<ex>n</ex>ing of the discoverye of the <lb/>
            poysoninge of S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas <hi rend="italic">Ouerbuye</hi> /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
                    <hi rend="italic">
               ❀ Conserning <ex>th</ex>e poyso=<lb break="no"/>
               ninge of Kinge Iames <lb/>
               of happye memory King <lb/>
               of greate Brittaine &amp;c</hi>
            </add>
            ❀ The duke of Buckingham being in Spaine advertised by <lb/>
            letters howe <ex>tha</ex>t the kinge began to censure him in his absence freelye, <lb/>
            and that manye spoke boldlye to the Kinge against him, and how <ex>th</ex>e Kinge <lb/>
            had intelligence fro<ex>m</ex> Spaine of his vnworthie carriage in Spaine, &amp; how <lb/>
            the Marquesse Hamelton vpo<ex>n</ex> <ex>th</ex>e suddaine newes of <ex>th</ex>e Princes dep<ex>ar</ex>ture <lb/>
            had noblie repr<ex>e</ex>hended the Kinge for sending the Prince with such a <lb/>
            young Man w<ex>i</ex>thout experience, and in such A private &amp; suddaine man<ex>ner</ex> <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout acquaint<del rend="strikethrough">e</del>ing the Nobillitye or Cou<ex>n</ex>cell therew<ex>i</ex>th, wrote A <lb/>
            verye bitter Letter to the Marquesse of Hamelton, conceaved newe <lb/>
            ambitious courses of his owne, and vsed all <ex>th</ex>e Devises he could to <lb/>
            disgust <ex>th</ex>e Princes mynde of the Matche w<ex>i</ex>th Spaine soe farr intended by <lb/>
            the kinge, made hast home, where when he came, he soe carryed himselfe <lb/>
            that w<ex>ha</ex>tsoeu<ex>er</ex> the kinge comau<ex>n</ex>ded in his Bed-Cha<ex>m</ex>ber, he co<ex>n</ex>trowlled in <ex>th</ex>e next <lb/>
            Cha<ex>m</ex>ber, yea a receaved packetts to <ex>th</ex>e king fro<ex>m</ex> forraine Princes, &amp; dispatched <lb/>
            Answeres w<ex>i</ex>thout acquainting <ex>th</ex>e kinge therew<ex>i</ex>th not in a great tyme there=<lb break="no"/>
            after, whereat p<ex>er</ex>ceaving <ex>th</ex>e king highlye offended, &amp; <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e kings mynde <lb/>
            was begin<ex>n</ex>ing to alter towards him, suffering him to bee quarelled and <lb/>
            affronted in his ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s pr<ex>e</ex>sence &amp; observing <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e kinge receaved my Lo<ex>rd</ex> of <lb/>
            Bristall to bee A rodd for him, vrging daylye his dispatch for Frau<ex>n</ex>ce, <lb/>
            and expecting <ex>th</ex>e Earle of Gondomar his coming into Eng<ex>land</ex> in his absence, <lb/>
            feared much that that <ex>th</ex>e Earle of Gondomar, whoe as it seemed was gr<ex>ea</ex>tlye <lb/>
            esteemed &amp; wonderfullye credited by the Kinge, would second my Lo<ex>rd</ex> <lb/>
            of Bristalls accusations ag<ex>ain</ex>st him, He knowing allsoe <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e kinge had <lb/>
            vowed <ex>tha</ex>t in dispight of all <ex>th</ex>e Divells of hell he would bring <ex>th</ex>e Spanish <lb/>
            matche about againe, and that the Marquesse of <hi rend="italic">Enechosa</hi> had given the <lb/>
            kinge badd impressions of him:  By whose Articles of accusations <del rend="strikethrough">of <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough"/>
                </del>
                <del rend="strikethrough">him</del> the kinge himselfe had examined some of <ex>th</ex>e Nobillitie and privye <lb/>
            Councell, &amp; found out in the examinac<ex>i</ex>on <ex>tha</ex>t Bucking<ex>ham</ex> had said after his <lb/>
            com<ex>m</ex>ing from Spaine. That <ex>th</ex>e king was an old man, it was now tyme for <lb/>
            him to be at his rest, and to be confined to some Parke, to passe <ex>th</ex>e rest <lb/>
            of his time in hunting, and <ex>th</ex>e Prince to be crowned. The more the kinge <lb/>
            vrged him to be gone to Fraunce <ex>th</ex>e more shifts he made to stay, for <lb/>
            he did evidentlye see <ex>th</ex>e king was fullye resolved to ridd himselfe of <lb/>
            the oppr<ex>e</ex>sion wherein he held him /
         </p>
         <p>
            The kinge being sicke of A tertian Ague &amp; <ex>tha</ex>t in <ex>th</ex>e springe, w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            was of it selfe never found deadlye.  The Duke tooke his opp<ex>or</ex>tunitie <lb/>
            when all the kings Doctors were at Dinner, vpon <ex>th</ex>e mundaye before <lb/>
            the kinge dyed, w<ex>i</ex>thout their knowledge or consent, offered a whit <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">powder</fw>
            <pb n="39v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f039v/add_ms_22591_f039v.jpg"/>
            powder to the kinge to take, the w<ex>hi</ex>ch the kinge longe time refused, <lb/>
            but overcome by his flatteringe oppertunitie, at length tooke itt, <lb/>
            dranke it in whit wine, and ymediatlye became worse and worse <lb/>
            falling into manye soundings and paynes or violent Fluxes of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Bellye, soe tormenting that his ma<ex>jes</ex>tye cryed out alowd O this w<ex>hi</ex>t powd<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            this whit Powder, would to God I had never taking it, it will cost mee <lb/>
            my liffe, In like manner the Countisse of Buckingham my Lorde of <lb/>
            Buckinghams Mother vpo<ex>n</ex> the Frydaye thereafter, <ex>th</ex>e Phisic<ex>i</ex>ons allsoe <lb/>
            being absent &amp; at dinner, &amp; not made acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th her doings, applyed <lb/>
            A Plaster to the Kings harte &amp; breast, wherevpo<ex>n</ex> his ma<ex>jes</ex>tye grewe fainte, <lb/>
            shorte breathed &amp; in greate agonie. Some of <ex>th</ex>e Phisitians after dinner re=<lb break="no"/>
            tourned to see the kinge, by <ex>th</ex>e offensive smell of <ex>th</ex>e Plaster, p<ex>er</ex>ceaved some=<lb break="no"/>
            thinge to be about <ex>th</ex>e kinge hurtfull vnto him, &amp; searched what it could be, <lb/>
            found it out, &amp; exclaymed <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e kinge was poysoned. Then Bucking<ex>ham</ex> entering <lb/>
            comau<ex>n</ex>ded the Phisicons out of the Roome, caused one to be comitted pr<ex>i</ex>son<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            to his owne Chamber, and another to remove fro<ex>m</ex> Courte, quarrelled w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            others of the kings servants in <ex>th</ex>e sicke kings owne pr<ex>e</ex>sence, soe farre <lb/>
            that he offered to drawe his sworde against them in the Kings sighte, <lb/>
            And Buckinghams mother kneeling before the kinge w<ex>i</ex>th A brazen face <lb/>
            cryed out <hi rend="italic">Iustice Iustice S<ex>i</ex>r</hi> I demaund Iustice of yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tye, The kinge <lb/>
            asking her for what? shee answered for that w<ex>hi</ex>ch their lives is noe suffi=<lb break="no"/>
            cient satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on, for saying that my Sonne and I haue poysoned <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r maj<ex>es</ex>tye, Poysoned mee said the kinge, w<ex>i</ex>th that he turninge himselfe <lb/>
            sounded, The Sunday thereafter the king dyed, &amp; Bucking<ex>ham</ex> desired <lb/>
            the Phisicians whoe attended the kinge to signe w<ex>i</ex>th their hands, writts, <lb/>
            A testimonye, that the Powder w<ex>hi</ex>ch he gave the kinge was a good suffi=<lb break="no"/>
            cient and safe medicine, w<ex>hi</ex>ch they refused to doe; Bucking<ex>hams</ex> Creatures <lb/>
            did spread abroad A rumor in London <ex>tha</ex>t Bucking<ex>ham</ex> was soe sorrie at the <lb/>
            kings deathe, that he would haue dyed, that he would haue killed him=<lb break="no"/>
            selfe yf they had not hindered him, w<ex>hi</ex>ch yo<ex>u</ex>r Petitioner pu<ex>r</ex>poselye in=<lb break="no"/>
            quired of them that were neere him at that time, whoe said, <ex>tha</ex>t neith<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            in the time of the kings sicknes, nor after his deathe, hee was any more <lb/>
            moued then yf there had neither happened either sicknes or deathe to <lb/>
            the kinge. One daye when the kinge was in great extremitie, hee rode <lb/>
            post to London to pursue his sister in lawe, to haue her stand in sack <lb/>
            Clothe at Paules for Adulterye, Another time in <ex>th</ex>e kings Agony, he <lb/>
            was busie co<ex>n</ex>triving &amp; co<ex>n</ex>cluding a maryage for one of his cosens, yme=<lb break="no"/>
            diatlye after <ex>th</ex>e kings death, <ex>th</ex>e Phisitian w<ex>hi</ex>ch was comau<ex>n</ex>ded to his Cha<ex>m</ex>ber <lb/>
            was sett at libertie w<ex>i</ex>th A Caveat to hold his Peace, <ex>th</ex>e others threatned <lb/>
            if they kept not good tonges in their heades. But in <ex>th</ex>e meane tyme <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            kings Bodye and head swelled aboue measures, his haire w<ex>i</ex>th the skinne <lb/>
            of his head stucke to the Pillowe, his nayles became loose vpon his <lb/>
            Fingers and Toes, yo<ex>u</ex>r Petition<ex>er</ex> needeth to saye noe more to vnder=<lb break="no"/>
            standing men. Onlye <del rend="strikethrough">hee</del> one thinge he beseecheth, <ex>tha</ex>t taking <ex>th</ex>e traytor <lb/>
            whoe ought to be taken, w<ex>i</ex>thout anye feare of his greatnes the other <lb/>
            matters be examined, the Accessaries w<ex>i</ex>th the guiltie punished/
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="bold">Finis</hi>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f031r/add_ms_22591_f031r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f031v/add_ms_22591_f031v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="3" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f032r/add_ms_22591_f032r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="4" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f032v/add_ms_22591_f032v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="5" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f033r/add_ms_22591_f033r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="6" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f033v/add_ms_22591_f033v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="7" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f034r/add_ms_22591_f034r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="8" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f034v/add_ms_22591_f034v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="9" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f035r/add_ms_22591_f035r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="10" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f035v/add_ms_22591_f035v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="11" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f036r/add_ms_22591_f036r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="12" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f036v/add_ms_22591_f036v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="13" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f037r/add_ms_22591_f037r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="14" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f037v/add_ms_22591_f037v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="15" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f038r/add_ms_22591_f038r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="16" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f038v/add_ms_22591_f038v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="17" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f039r/add_ms_22591_f039r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="18" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f039v/add_ms_22591_f039v.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>