<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter Concerning the Disputation Between Featley, White, Fisher and Sweet</title>
            <author>
               <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0116">John Fisher</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="VA">
                    <name>Victoria Anker</name>
                    <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLAddMs28640.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_28640">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Additional</collection>
                <idno>MS 28640</idno>
                <msName>John Rous's diary</msName>
             </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Additional MS 28640</p>
            </msDesc>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1623-07-01">1 July 1623</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
            <language ident="LA">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term>letter</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term>confessional conflict</term>
               <term>religious disputation</term>
               <term>Jesuits</term>
               <term>Catholicism</term>
               <term>primitive church</term>
               <term>Protestantism</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-03-20" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2010" who="#NM" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         
         <pb n="113r" facs="/bl/add_ms_28640/add_ms_28640_f113r/add_ms_28640_f113r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            Anno. 1623. There was a disputation betweene doctor White &amp; <lb/>
            doctor Featly on our side &amp; Mr Fisher &amp; Mr Sweete Iesuites <lb/>
            on the other in the house of S<ex>i</ex>r Humfrey L. in London, which was <lb/>
            abruptely broken of, yet the proceeding so farre as it went is set <lb/>
            out in print. This letter following (either true or fained) concernes it./
         </p>
         <milestone type="separator" unit="nonstructural" rend="horizontal-line"/>
         <p>
            Right Hon. Lord <space extent="4" unit="chars"/> I knowe it the especiall prouidence of God <lb/>
            that yo<ex>u</ex>r Lordship was present at a late conference wherein do<ex>cto</ex>r <lb/>
            White &amp; doctor Featlie vndertooke to shewe against me &amp; my com=<lb break="no"/>
            panion, that the protestant Church had beene visible in all ages <lb/>
            &amp; that <del rend="strikethrough">there</del> theire professors might be named especially in the <lb/>
            ages before Luther/ <space unit="chars" extent="10"/> Yo<ex>u</ex>r Lordship may remember the <lb/>
            substance of all theire proofe to haue consisted in this that the true <lb/>
            Church was alwaies so visible as that the professors thereof in <lb/>
            all ages might be named/ <space unit="chars" extent="10"/> We refused to dispute of <lb/>
            the Minor because it transferred the question, <del rend="strikethrough">that</del> &amp; avoyded that <lb/>
            plaine proofe of the visible Church which was propounded &amp; ex=<lb break="no"/>
            pected/ <space extent="8" unit="chars"/> If as they conclude they are able to name theire <lb/>
            professors in all ages, why did they refuse to giue vs a Catalogue <lb/>
            of theires as we were readye to haue giue<ex>n</ex> them another of <lb/>
            ours? Why went they about to proue they were able to name <lb/>
            them, when with as litle adoe they might haue named them? <lb/>
            Where deedes are justly expected, wordes without deedes are <lb/>
            worthely <del rend="strikethrough">expected</del> suspected/ <space extent="9" unit="chars"/> Certainly hereby they <lb/>
            are so farre from discharging themselues of the greate enterprise <lb/>
            they vndertooke as they stande more ingaged the<ex>n</ex> before to the <lb/>
            performance of it; for hauing nowe professed &amp; acknowledged <lb/>
            that the true Church, or (to vse theire owne wordes) the Church <lb/>
            which is visible as the <del rend="strikethrough">Ch</del> Catholike Church ought to be, &amp; the <lb/>
            Church whose faith is eternall, must be able to name her professors <lb/>
            in all ages; either for theire owne honour &amp; for the satisfac=<lb break="no"/>
            tion of the world, they must set downe the names of theire p<ex>ro</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            fessors in all ages; or else they shamefully discouer themselues <lb/>
            not to be that true &amp; visible vnchanged Church which is able to <lb/>
            name them./ <space extent="8" unit="chars"/> Very Noblie therefore &amp; prudently
            <pb n="113v" facs="/bl/add_ms_28640/add_ms_28640_f113v/add_ms_28640_f113v.jpg"/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r Lordship in the ende desired another meeting, not doubting <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r owne partie within ij or iij dayes would be contente to giue <lb/>
            vs the names of theire professors in all ages, as we were rea=<lb break="no"/>
            dy to giue them the names of ours, that thereby both sides <lb/>
            might be the better prepared for a further triall: <space extent="4" unit="chars"/> Which <lb/>
            when they haue performed we shall not faile to encounter <lb/>
            with them, either by way of speech or writing, as yo<ex>u</ex>r Lord<ex>shi</ex>[ <lb/>
            (all things considered) shall thinke fitte &amp; fayrest, safest or <lb/>
            most convenient for discouery of truth./ <space unit="chars" extent="8"/> But if yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Lordship shall not be able to obteine at theire hands, this yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            most just &amp; important request, the defecte of proofe on theire <lb/>
            parte must needes be accompted a plaine flight / &amp; no man <lb/>
            hereafter <hi rend="underline">can prudently relye his saluation vpon that Church <lb/>
               which (for wante of perpetuall visibility sufficiently prooved) <lb/>
               they themselues shall haue concluded to be false &amp; feined./</hi> <lb/>
            Thus expecting the issue hereof &amp; yo<ex>u</ex>r Lordships further plea=<lb break="no"/>
            sure from the mouth of this bearer I remaine <space extent="4" unit="chars"/> this 1 of Iuly 1623 <lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="align-right">
            Yo<ex>u</ex>r L<ex>ordshi</ex>ps servant in Christ <lb/>
            I. F.
         </p>
         <milestone type="separator" unit="nonstructural" rend="horizontal-line"/>
         <p>
            I thinke the publishing of this letter, caused the printing of that priuate Disputation, or <lb/>
            else some speeches or writings of this kind, as the booke it selfe declareth.
         </p>
         <p>
            This letter is craftely dispersed by copies thereof into Papists hands to <lb/>
            confirme them &amp; into the handes of others dazle them &amp;c.
         </p>
         <p>
            Who so readeth the booke shall finde that the causes why the Iesuites <lb/>
            <add place="LM">
               finit. +
            </add>
            were not satisfyed in the Catalogue of Successors might be these. 1° <lb/>
            It was a priuate conference &amp; disputation vnto which (it may well be) <lb/>
            they were not requested to bring such a  Catalogue. 2° They were in=<lb break="no"/>
            terrupted when they beganne to recite. 3° It was not allowed <lb/>
            them to beginne at Christ &amp; his Apostles. 4° The Iesuites must also <lb/>
            haue begunne there for theire Church which it seemeth they durst not. <lb/>
            5° The doctors only yeelded to shewe this successio<ex>n</ex> because of the Papiste <lb/>
            bragges, shewing that it is no sound arguing/ These cannot name suc<lb break="no"/>
            cessor visible &amp; <ex>er</ex>go are no <del rend="strikethrough">Ch</del> true Church/ These can, <ex>er</ex>go are a true <lb/>
            Church. 6° The naming of Successors would be an endlesse quarrell <lb/>
            because they counte for theires, many of the first age that are not theirs <lb/>
            &amp; much Cavilling there would be about those hich in truth are ours.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/add_ms_28640/add_ms_28640_f113r/add_ms_28640_f113r"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/add_ms_28640/add_ms_28640_f113v/add_ms_28640_f113v"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>