<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Five Years of King James</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="VA">
                    <name>Victoria Anker</name>
                    <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TW">
               <name>Tim Wales</name>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLAddMS22591.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_22591">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Additional</collection>
                <idno>MS 22591</idno>
                <msName/>
             </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Additional MS 22591</p>
            </msDesc>
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated">
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Alnwick_Castle_MS_528.xml">Alnwick Castle,  MS 528, ff89</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHarleyMS4888.xml">British Library, Harley MS 4888, ff. 213x–251x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHarleyMS6242.xml">British Library, Harley MS 6242, ff. 1*r–64x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Add_MS_38680.xml">British Library, Additional MS 38680, ff. 5r–83r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Add_MS_62527.xml">British Library, Additional MS 62527, ff. 1r–76v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Harley_MS_4302.xml">British Library, Harley MS 4302, ff44</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Stowe_MS_280.xml">British Library, Stowe MS 280, ff. 2x–73x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Beinecke_Osborn_File_19125.xml">Beinecke Library, Osborn File 19125</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Rawlinson_D_655.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Rawlinson D 655, ff. 1r–95</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/CUL_MS_Ee414.xml">Cambridge University Library,  MS Ee.4.14, ff. 1r–60v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/CUL_MS_Gg518.xml">Cambridge University Library,  MS Gg.5.18, ff. 2r–65v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/HALS_XIIB8.xml">Hertfordshire Archives and Local Studies,  XII.B.8</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/JRL_Mainwaring_MS_15.xml">John Rylands Library, Mainwaring MS 15, ff. 1r–91v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Queens_College_Oxford_MS_32.xml">Queen's College,  MS 32, ff. 48r–101r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/TNA_SP_14_89.xml">The National Archives,  SP 14/89, /136 [ff.280r–340v]</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/University_College_Oxford_MS_83.xml">University College,  MS 83 [on deposit at the Bodleian], ff. 58v–70v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Woburn_Abbey_MS_18.xml">Woburn Abbey,  MS 18, ff. 110v–113v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            <listBibl xml:id="C17_print_witness">
               <bibl>
                  <author/>
                  <title>The Five Years of King Iames, or, The condition of the state of England and the relation it had to other provinces</title>
                  <date when="1643">1643</date>
                  <idno type="Wing">W2886</idno>
                  <idno type="Wing">W2887</idno>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl xml:id="modern_print_witness">
               <bibl>
                  <title type="shorttitle">The Harleian Miscellany</title>
                  <edition>1st ed.</edition> 
                  <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="418">385-418</biblScope>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="shorttitle">Somers Tracts</title>
                  <edition>2nd ed.</edition> 
                  <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="304">265-304</biblScope>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1625">c.1625-1628</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
            <language ident="LA">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-08-23" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2018-07-17" who="#TW" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="2r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f02r/add_ms_22591_f02r.jpg"/>
         <head rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="bold">
               Parte <lb/>
               of the liffe of kinge Iames of <lb/>
               Fa=<lb break="no"/>
               mous Memorye w<ex>i</ex>th diuers Mat <lb/>
               ters <lb/>
               of Consequence which hapned in his  <lb/>
               Raigne <lb/>
            </hi>
         </head>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">
               Iohn Sudbury et George Humble <lb/>
               Londini excu=derunt
            </hi>
         </p>
         <pb n="2v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f02v/add_ms_22591_f02v.jpg"/>
         <gap reason="blank"/>
         <pb n="3r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f03r/add_ms_22591_f03r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Of the Condition of <lb/>
                  the State of Eng<ex>land</ex> <lb/>
                  and the relation it <lb/>
                  had to oth<ex>e</ex>r Proui<ex>n</ex>ces
               </hi>
            </add>
            Howsoever everye Kingdome and Comon-Wealthe maye be <lb/>
            both well and vprightlye governed, and that good men maye be the <lb/>
            meanes to supporte it; yet there cann be noe such como<ex>n</ex>-Wealthe, <lb/>
            but amongst the good, there wilbe ever some evill p<ex>er</ex>sonns those (whether <lb/>
            by nature induced, or throughe envye and Ambition; to the intent <lb/>
            to satisfye those appetites p<ex>er</ex>swaded) doe oftentymes enter into ac-<lb break="no"/>
            tions repugnant vnto the felicitye of good governem<ex>en</ex>t &amp; Como<ex>n</ex> wealthes, <lb/>
            and by evill Courses and p<ex>er</ex>verse deedes doe secretlye &amp; vnd<ex>e</ex>rhand <lb/>
            seeke to hasten and sett forward the ruyn and decaye of the same. <lb/>
            These things because they happen contrarye and beyond expectatio<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            are soe much the more remarkable <del rend="strikethrough">ho</del> by how much they are sudden <lb/>
            and vnexpected. And from hence it cometh that noe State of gou<ex>er</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            ment can be said p<ex>er</ex>manent, but <ex>tha</ex>t often times those <ex>tha</ex>t are good, are  <lb/>
            by litle and litle converted vnto those that are evill, and those <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            are evill are oftentimes changed from worse to worse, till they <lb/>
            come to vtter desolation
         </p>
         <p>
            Neither is this alone prop<ex>er</ex> to one como<ex>n</ex> wealthe, but to all, nor <lb/>
            to forraine Kingdomes, but to our owne, For although his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye  <lb/>
            at his coming to the Crowne, found vs vexed w<ex>i</ex>th many defensive <lb/>
            warrs, as <ex>tha</ex>t in Ireland, that in the lowe countryes, and allmost <lb/>
            publique against Spayne, auxiliarye in France, and co<ex>n</ex>tinuallye <lb/>
            in Millitarye ymploym<ex>en</ex>t, Allthoughe he found it lacerate and <lb/>
            torne w<ex>i</ex>th divers factions of Protestants Papist and oth<ex>e</ex>rs fro<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            amongst whom sprunge some evill men that endeavored to sett <lb/>
            into Combustion the whole State / Yet neverthelesse he established <lb/>
            a peace both honorable and p<ex>ro</ex>fitable w<ex>i</ex>th all neighbor Princes, <lb/>
            and by relation through all Europe; Soe that neither our Freinds, <lb/>
            nor our Enemies might be either feared or suspected
         </p>
         <p>
            After this generall peace was concluded, and <ex>th</ex>e workinge <lb/>
            heades of daungerous Papists were confyned to A certaine <lb/>
            course of liffe, that is Peace / they nowe Petition for tolleratio<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            for release of vexation, to have libertie of Conscience; And <lb/>
            forsooth because they cannot haue these thinges, amongst the<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            they contrive and most horrible and devellish plott, by Gun=<lb break="no"/>
            Powder to blowe vp in Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t even the whole State &amp; com<ex>m</ex>o<ex>n</ex>s <lb/>
            of this kingdome; and soe at one Puffe, to conclude all this peace, <lb/>
            and by that meanes to p<ex>ro</ex>cure an vnrulye and vnseemely Anar=<lb break="no"/>
            chie of this settled Governem<ex>en</ex>t. And this not soe much to establish <lb/>
            their owne religio<ex>n</ex>, for w<ex>hi</ex>ch purpose they pr<ex>e</ex>tended it, but to <lb/>
            establish their owne power and pr<ex>e</ex>heminencye, and to raise some <lb/>
            private familyes to greatnes and dignitye, that soe faction <lb/>
            being nourished, and <ex>tha</ex>t Jurisdiction established, they might <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th greate facilitie suppresse whom they please, and support <lb/>
            theire owne state. Thus maye wee see that setled Governem<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            doe cherrish in them selves, their owne distructions, and their <lb/>
            owne subiects are oftentimes, the cause of their owne ruyne, <lb/>
            vnlesse God of his mercye prevent it /
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">
                    <hi rend="bold">This</hi>
                </fw>
         </p>
         <pb n="3v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f03v/add_ms_22591_f03v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Of <ex>th</ex>e domestick af-<lb break="no"/>
                  faires, and of <ex>th</ex>e laci-<lb break="no"/>
                  ous courses of Such on <lb/>
                  whome <ex>th</ex>e Kinge had be=<lb break="no"/>
                  stowed the honour of <lb/>
                  knighthood
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">This</hi> euill being discovered by the Lord Mou<ex>n</ex>teagle, and ou<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            passed; divers discontentments happened, some betweene <ex>th</ex>e Civilians <lb/>
            and comon lawyers concerning prohibitions: And for that there <lb/>
            was one Docter Cowell stood stifelye against my Lord Cooke, <lb/>
            divers  discontents were nourished, betweene the Gentrye &amp; Com=<lb break="no"/>
            minaltie concerning enclosure, and it burst out into A pettye  <lb/>
            rebellion, w<ex>hi</ex>ch by some was coniectured, not to happen soe much for  <lb/>
            the thinge it selfe, as for to finde howe the people Stood affected to <lb/>
            the pr<ex>e</ex>sent state, whereby divers pr<ex>i</ex>vate quarrells and secrett <lb/>
            Combustions were daylye breaking out, pr<ex>i</ex>vate Familyes one sy=<lb break="no"/>
            ded against another, and of these Protestant<ex>es</ex> ag<ex>ains</ex>t Papists, they <lb/>
            thereby endeavoring to gett A head, and from small beginnings <lb/>
            to raise greater Rebellons. Nowe discontents shewed the<ex>m</ex>selves <lb/>
            headye, and spake publiquelye w<ex>ha</ex>t durst not heretofore haue bine <lb/>
            spoken in Corners: In outward appearance Papist were favored, <lb/>
            Masses allmost publiquelye administred, Protestants disco<ex>n</ex>te<ex>n</ex>ted <lb/>
            discounten<add place="above">a</add>nced, dishonest men honoured, those that were litle lesse <lb/>
            then sorcerers and witches preferred, pr<ex>i</ex>vate quarrells nouri=<lb break="no"/>
            shed, but espetiallye betweene the Scottish and English duells <lb/>
            in everye street maynteyned: divers sects of vicious p<ex>er</ex>sons <lb/>
            vnder p<ex>ar</ex>ticuler titles passe vnpunished, or regarded as the  <lb/>
            secte of roringe Boyes, Beneventoyes, Bravadors, Quarterors, <lb/>
            and such like, being p<ex>er</ex>sons prodigall and of great expence, when <lb/>
            hauing run themselves into debt, were constrayned to run into <lb/>
            faction to defend them from the danger of the lawe, these received <lb/>
            mayntenance from divers of the Nobillitye, and not a litle as <lb/>
            was suspected from the Earle of Northa<ex>m</ex>pton, W<ex>hi</ex>ch p<ex>er</ex>sons though <lb/>
            of themselves they were not able to attempt any enterprise, <lb/>
            yet Faith, honestie, and other good acts being nowe little sett <lb/>
            by / and Citizens through laciviousnes consuming their estates, <lb/>
            it was likelye <ex>tha</ex>t their number would rather increase the<ex>n</ex> dymini=<lb break="no"/>
            nish / And vnder these pr<ex>e</ex>tences they entred into manye desperat <lb/>
            enterprises, and scarse anye durst walke the Streets w<ex>i</ex>th safty <lb/>
            after nyne at night. Soe that to conclude, in outward shew <lb/>
            there appeared noe certaine affection, noe certaine, obedience, <lb/>
            noe certaine Goverm<ex>en</ex>t amongst vs /  
         </p>
         <p>
            Such personns on whom the kinge had bestowed p<ex>ar</ex>rticuler honors, <lb/>
            either throughe pride of that or their owne p<ex>ro</ex>digallitye, lived at <lb/>
            highe rates, and w<ex>i</ex>th their greatnesse brought in excesse of ryot <lb/>
            both in Clothes and dyett / soe our au<ex>n</ex>tient customes were aban=<lb break="no"/>
            doned, and that stricknes and severitye <ex>tha</ex>t had wont to be amongst <lb/>
            the English scorned and contemned, everye one applauding stra<ex>n</ex>g <lb/>
            or newe thinges, though never soe costlye, And for attayninge <lb/>
            of thyem neither sparing purse nor creditt, that prises of all sort<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            of Comodities are raysed: And those au<ex>n</ex>tent Gent<ex>le</ex>men whoe <lb/>
            had left their Inheritaunce whole and well furnished with  <lb/>
            Goods and Cattell (hauing thereof kept good houses) vnto <ex>the</ex>ir <lb/>
            Sonnes, lived to see p<ex>ar</ex>te consumed in ryott and excesse, and  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">the</fw>
            <pb n="4r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f04r/add_ms_22591_f04r.jpg"/>
            the rest in possibilitie to be vtterlye lost. The holy State of <lb/>
            matrimonye most p<ex>er</ex>fidiouslye broken, and amongst manye made <lb/>
            but A May-game, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes divers private Familyes haue <lb/>
            bine subverted, brothell houses in abou<ex>n</ex>dance tollerated, and eve<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            great p<ex>er</ex>sons p<ex>ro</ex>stituting their bodyes, to the intent to satisfye and <lb/>
            consume their substance in lascivious appetites of all sort<ex>es</ex>. Such  <lb/>
            Knights or gent<ex>le</ex>men as either th<add place="above">r</add>oughe Pride or Prodigallitye  <lb/>
            had consumed substance repayring to the Cittye, and to the intent <lb/>
            to consume their vertues allsoe lived dissolute lives / And many <lb/>
            of their Ladyes and daughters, to the intent to mainetaine the<ex>m</ex>selves <lb/>
            according to their dignitie, p<ex>ro</ex>stitute their bodyes in shaemfull mann<ex>er</ex> / <lb/>
            Alehouses, diceing houses, Taver<ex>n</ex>s, and places of vice &amp; iniquitie, <lb/>
            beyond measure abounding in most places, there being as much ex=<lb break="no"/>
            torc<ex>i</ex>on for Sinne as there is racking of Rentes, and as many wayes <lb/>
            to spend monye as are windings and turnings in Townes &amp; Streetes, <lb/>
            Soe <ex>tha</ex>t to outward appearance the evill seeme to overtop <ex>th</ex>e good, <lb/>
            and evill intent<ex>i</ex>ons &amp; Cou<ex>n</ex>cells rather prosp<ex>er</ex>ed then those <ex>tha</ex>t were <lb/>
            profitable to the Comon well  //
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Of my Lo<ex>rd</ex> of North<ex>amp</ex>to<ex>n</ex>s <lb/>
            coming to honor, <ex>th</ex>e cause <lb/>
            of the deuision betwene <lb/>
            <ex>th</ex>e Hollander, &amp; <ex>th</ex>e Eng<ex>lish</ex> <lb/>
            betweene <ex>th</ex>e Scottish  <lb/>
            and Eng<ex>lish</ex>, betweene <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            English and Irish /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Nowe</hi> Henrye Howard youngest Sonne <del rend="strikethrough">t</del>of the Duke of  <lb/>
            Norfolke continuing A Papist fro<ex>m</ex> his Infancie even vnto this <lb/>
            tyme, begin<ex>n</ex>ing to growe eminent and being made famous heere=<lb break="no"/>
            tofore for his learning, hauing bine trayned and brought vpp a <lb/>
            longe time in Cambridge, by the p<ex>er</ex>swation of the kinge, changeth <lb/>
            his opinion of Religion in outward appearance, and to <ex>th</ex>e intent  <lb/>
            to reape vnto himselfe more honors, became A Protestant. For <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch cause he was created Earle of North<ex>ampton</ex> and had the kings Fa=<lb break="no"/>
            vours bountifullye bestowed on him. First the office of Privye <lb/>
            Seale, then the Wardenshipp of the Cinque Ports, and lastlye the  <lb/>
            refusall of being treasuror. This man was of A subtill &amp; fine <lb/>
            witt, of a good p<ex>ro</ex>portion, excellent in outwarde Courteshipp, <lb/>
            famous for secrett insinuac<ex>i</ex>on and for cun<ex>n</ex>ing flatteries, and <lb/>
            by reason of those quallities became A fitt man for <ex>th</ex>e co<ex>n</ex>ditions <lb/>
            of those times, and was suspected to be scarse true to his sou<ex>er</ex>agn<ex>n</ex>e, <lb/>
            but rather endeavouring by some secrett wayes and meanes to <lb/>
            sett abroache newe plotts for to procure innovac<ex>i</ex>ons And for <lb/>
            the purpose it was thought had A hand in the Contentio<ex>n</ex> <ex>tha</ex>t hap=<lb break="no"/>
            pened among the Holland<ex>e</ex>rs and English concerning <ex>th</ex>e fishing <lb/>
            in the Levant / and the English clayming right vpo<ex>n</ex> this Co<ex>n</ex>tention <lb/>
            they fell fro<ex>m</ex> Clayme to wordes of Anger, fro<ex>m</ex> words of Ang<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            to blowes, soe that there dyed manye of them, and a scarr was <lb/>
            left for A further quarrell, but that it was salved by wise <lb/>
            governors, and the expectation of some disapointed: Neverthe=<lb break="no"/>
            lesse the Papist being A strong faction, and soe great A man <lb/>
            being theire favorer, grewe into heades, mallice &amp; endeavour <lb/>
            to make the insolencie of the Scottish to appeare, whoe to the <lb/>
            intent That they might be the more hated of the English not <lb/>
            contented w<ex>i</ex>th their present Estate would enter into outrag<ex>es</ex>,
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">some</fw>
            <pb n="4v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f04v/add_ms_22591_f04v.jpg"/>
            some cou<ex>n</ex>terfeite the Seale Manuall, others whipp <ex>th</ex>e Nobillitye <lb/>
            in disdaine, and A third Sorte secretlye contrive the Englishes <lb/>
            deathe / whereby it happened besydes como<ex>n</ex> clamor <ex>tha</ex>t there were <lb/>
            added secrett discontents of pr<ex>i</ex>vate p<ex>er</ex>sons, w<ex>hi</ex>ch caused a Iealousy <lb/>
            to happen betweene those two nations, But his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye being both <lb/>
            wise and worthy foresawe the evill and pr<ex>e</ex>vented it by Proclama=<lb break="no"/>
            tion, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes theis Clamors are stopt, and the Iniuryes &amp; <lb/>
            offences of both p<ex>ar</ex>ties redressed. The Irish seeing theis Soares <lb/>
            and hearing of their misdemeanors (for they haue theire Intelli <lb/>
            gencers heere allsoe) begunne to growe obstinate, and make <lb/>
            religion a pr<ex>e</ex>tence to coulor their intentions / For w<ex>hi</ex>ch cause they <lb/>
            stand out, and protest losse of liffe and goods rather then to  <lb/>
            be forced fro<ex>m</ex> their opynion, being wavering and vnconstant, ra=<lb break="no"/>
            ther thirsting for Rebellion to the intent to p<ex>u</ex>rchase theire owne  <lb/>
            libertie then peace / everye newe alteration gives occasion of <lb/>
            discontent, and causes new complaynts to be brought to <ex>th</ex>e Kings <lb/>
            Eare, vnder pr<ex>e</ex>tence whereof they growe contemptuous to their <lb/>
            Governors, and haters of the English lawes / The Captaines and <lb/>
            Souldiers growe negligent for want of paye, the greatest me<ex>n</ex> envy=<lb break="no"/>
            ing one another through private Covetuousnes, and many Inso=<lb break="no"/>
            lencies being suffered  cause there allsoe to be nourished manye <lb/>
            misdemeanors to the ruine of <ex>tha</ex>t goverm<ex>en</ex>t /
         </p>
         <p>
            These thinges thus handled administer occasion to the <lb/>
            Popish to hope for some alteration and change, and that as a body <lb/>
            that is violent consumeth yt selfe w<ex>i</ex>thout some sp<ex>ec</ex>iall Cause to <lb/>
            mayntayne it, soe these occurrences wilbe the cause of their owne <lb/>
            distruction. At this tyme there was a Leaguer in Denmarke &amp; <lb/>
            shortlye after another in the lowe countryes / But to what end <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            beginni<ex>n</ex>gs were intended is yet unknowne
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The rising of <ex>th</ex>e E<ex>arl</ex> <lb/>
                  of Som<ex>er</ex>sett his fauor &amp; <lb/>
                  greatnes with <ex>th</ex>e K<ex>ing</ex> <lb/>
                  and his parentage &amp; <lb/>
                  discente /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Amonge</hi> other accidents that happened about these times, <lb/>
            the rysing of one Mr Carr was most remarkable / A man borne <lb/>
            of meane parentage, Inhabitant in a village neere Edenborough <lb/>
            in Scotland, and there through the favor of Freindes was pr<ex>e</ex>fered <lb/>
            to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye to be one of his Pages, for he kept twelve accordinge  <lb/>
            to the Costome of <ex>th</ex>e French, and soe continued it as long as hee <lb/>
            was in Scotland. Afterwardes coming into England, <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>cell <lb/>
            thought it much more honorable to haue soe manye Footeme<ex>n</ex> to <lb/>
            runn w<ex>i</ex>th his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye as the Queene had before him / wherevpon <lb/>
            these youthes had Clothes put <del rend="strikethrough">th</del> to their Backes accordinge to <lb/>
            their places, and 50 l a peece in their Purses, and soe were dis=<lb break="no"/>
            missed the Courte. This youthe amongst the rest hauing thus lost <lb/>
            his Fortunes, to repare them againe makes hast into France, <lb/>
            and there continued vntill he had spent all his meanes and <lb/>
            monye, soe that nowe being bare in a strange Cou<ex>n</ex>trye w<ex>i</ex>thout<hi rend="bold"> <lb/>
            </hi>Freindes or hope to attaine his expectacons retournes backe <lb/>
            for England, bringing nothing w<ex>i</ex>th him but the language, and <lb/>
            a few Frenche fashions: Nevertthelesse by the helpe of some
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">of</fw>
            <pb n="5r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f05r/add_ms_22591_f05r.jpg"/>
            of his Countrye men and au<ex>n</ex>tient acquaintance, hee was <lb/>
            pr<ex>e</ex>ferred vnto the Lord Hayes a Scotishman and Favorite <lb/>
            of the kinges to waite vpon him as his Page / Not longe after <lb/>
            this Lord amongst other was appointed to p<ex>er</ex>forme a tiltinge, <lb/>
            whoe bearing an affection to this yong man, aswell in respecte <lb/>
            that he was his Countryeman, as <ex>tha</ex>t he found him to be of A <lb/>
            bold disposition, comelye visage, and p<ex>ro</ex>portionable personage, <lb/>
            mixt w<ex>i</ex>th a Courtlye pr<ex>e</ex>sence, pr<ex>e</ex>ferrs him to carry his device, <lb/>
            to the kinge according to the Custome of those pastimes vsed / <lb/>
            Nowe when he should come to light from his horse to p<ex>er</ex>forme  <lb/>
            his office, his horse starts, throwes him downe, breakes his leg, <lb/>
            This accident being noe lesse strange then suddaine in such a <lb/>
            place, causes the kinge to demaund whoe it was, answere was <lb/>
            made his name was Carr, he taking notice of his name, and <lb/>
            calling to remembrance <ex>tha</ex>t such A one was his Page causes <lb/>
            him to be had into the Courte, and there p<ex>ro</ex>vides for him vntill <lb/>
            such time as he was recovered of his hurte.  After in p<ex>ro</ex>cesse <lb/>
            of time, this yong man was called for, and made one of the  <lb/>
            Bedchamber to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye, He had not longe continued in  <lb/>
            this place before (by his good endeavors and deligent service <lb/>
            in his office) the king shewed extraordynarye favour vnto him, <lb/>
            doubling the valew of every Action in his estimation, soe <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            manye are obscured, that he maye be grated and dignified / Thus <lb/>
            the hand of the deligent maketh ritche, and <ex>th</ex>e dutifull serva<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
            cometh to honor. He of all other (either w<ex>i</ex>thout Fraude to obtay<ex>n</ex>e <lb/>
            it, or desert to continue it) is made the kings Favorite. Noe suite, <lb/>
            noe petition, noe graunt, noe letter, but Mr Carr must haue a <lb/>
            hand in it, soe <ex>tha</ex>t great reward<ex>es</ex> are bestowed vpo<ex>n</ex> him by Sutors <lb/>
            and large somes of monye by his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes his welth <lb/>
            encreased w<ex>i</ex>th his Favour, and w<ex>i</ex>th both honor, for vertue and <lb/>
            riches dignifieth their owners, being of A Page raised to the <lb/>
            dignitie of knighthood. After his Favor still encreased w<ex>i</ex>th his <lb/>
            honor, there was no demaund but he had it, noe suite but he ob=<lb break="no"/>
            tayned it, whether it were Crowne Lands, lands forfeited, or  <lb/>
            confiscated , nothing soe deere but the King bestowed vpo<ex>n</ex> him, <lb/>
            whereby his revenues were enlarged, and his glorye so res=<lb break="no"/>
            plendant, that he drowned the dignitye of the best of the nobillity, <lb/>
            and the eminencie of such, as were much more excellent By w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            meanes Envie (the Como<ex>n</ex> Companion of Greatnes) p<ex>ro</ex>cures him <lb/>
            much discontent, but yet passing through all disadventures, con=<lb break="no"/>
            tinues his favor. And men being drawne to aplaude <ex>tha</ex>t w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            is either strange or newe, began to saye to him, and most to <lb/>
            purchase him to be theire Freinde and assistant in Court, soe <lb/>
            and emine<ex>n</ex>t is his Favor.    
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Of <ex>th</ex>e breach that <lb/>
                  happened betweene <lb/>
                  the E<ex>arl</ex> of Essex and <lb/>
                  his
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Nowe</hi> the Eares of the vulgar being filled w<ex>i</ex>th the fortu<ex>n</ex>es <lb/>
            of this Gentleman, it ministreth occasion to them to passe theire <lb/>
            opinions concerning his worthe and deserte: some extoll &amp; loue <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">his</fw>
            <pb n="5v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f05v/add_ms_22591_f05v.jpg"/>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  his countess, her ha <lb/>
                  tred towards him, his  <lb/>
                  lenitie, her lightnes, <lb/>
                  his constancie / 
               </hi>
            </add> <lb/>
            his vertues, others to p<ex>ro</ex>portion of his p<ex>er</ex>sonage, manye his out=<lb break="no"/>
            ward Courtshipp, and most as they stood affected, other praised or <lb/>
            dispraysed him / in soe much <ex>tha</ex>t amongst the rest / the Countisse of Essex <lb/>
            (a woman that at that time did not greatlye affect her husband, and <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thall being of A lustfull appetite, prodigall of expence, covetous <lb/>
            of applause, ambitious of honor, and light of behaviour / haveinge <lb/>
            taken notice of this yonge Gentell<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> mans p<ex>ro</ex>speritie, &amp; great favor <lb/>
            that was shewed to him aboue others, in hope to make some p<ex>ro</ex>fitt of  <lb/>
            him, most admires him to everye one, comending his worth, spirit, <lb/>
            audatitye, and agillitye of bodye, soe that her lawfull au<ex>n</ex>tient and <lb/>
            accustomed love towards her Lord, begins to be obscured, &amp; those <lb/>
            imbraces <ex>tha</ex>t heretofore seemed pleasing are turned into frownes, <lb/>
            and harsh and vnseemelye wordes vsher her discontents vnto her <lb/>
            husbands Eares, The good Earle carrying an extraordinary affectio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            towards her, and being a man of A myld and Courteous conditio<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th all honest and religious, readye rather to suffer then to cor-<lb break="no"/>
            rect these outrages, patientlye admonisheth her to A bett<ex>e</ex>r Cou<ex>r</ex>se <lb/>
            of liffe, and to remember that all her fortunes nowe depend vpo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            his p<ex>ro</ex>speritye, and therefore shew in this offered more iniurye to her <lb/>
            selfe then hurte vnto him. Yet neverthelesse shee p<ex>er</ex>sisted, and fro<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            bare wordes returned into actions, thereby giving people occasio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            to passe their censure of this disagreem<ex>en</ex>t, some attributing it to the <lb/>
            vnconstancye and loosenes of the Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse, others to the Earles tra=<lb break="no"/>
            vells, and <ex>tha</ex>t in his absence shee continued most vnconstant, of a <lb/>
            loose liffe suffering her bodye to be abused, and others to make ship=<lb break="no"/>
            wracke of her modestie, and to abrogate the rights of marryage. <lb/>
            But most because she could not haue wherew<ex>i</ex>th to satisfye her insa=<lb break="no"/>
            tiate appetite and ambition, her husband living A private liffe. <lb/>
            For these Causes (I saye) she ran at randome, and playd her pranks <lb/>
            as the toye tooke her in the head, sometime publiquelye, some tyme <lb/>
            privatelye, whereby shee both disparaged her reputation, &amp; brought <lb/>
            herselfe into the contempt of the world. yet notw<ex>i</ex>thstanding <ex>th</ex>e Earle <lb/>
            retayned her w<ex>i</ex>th him, allowed her honorable attendance, gaue <lb/>
            her meanes according to her place, and shewed an extraordinary <lb/>
            affection, endeavoring rather by Freind<del rend="strikethrough">es</del>
                <add place="above">ly</add> and faire p<ex>er</ex>swations to <lb/>
            winne her then to become sup<ex>er</ex>fidious over her /  
         </p>
         <p>
            But these things litle avayle, where affections are carryed to <lb/>
            another stope, and those thinges that to the Iudgm<ex>en</ex>t of the wise became <lb/>
            fitt to be vsed, are of others contemned and dispised / Soe <ex>tha</ex>t almost <lb/>
            all men speake of the loosenes of her carriage, and wonders that the <lb/>
            Earle will suffer her in these Courses / wherevpo<ex>n</ex> he modestlye and <lb/>
            privatelye told her of it / giving her a checke for her inordinate <lb/>
            Courses, shewing her how much it both dishonor<ex>e</ex>d him &amp; disparaged her <lb/>
            in p<ex>er</ex>sisting in the Eye of the world, after soe loose and vnseemelye a <lb/>
            sorte, desiring her to be more civill at home, and not soe often a <lb/>
            broade and thus they parte /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Of my L<ex>ord</ex> Treasurors <lb/>
                  death, of Mr Ouerbury <lb/>
            	   com=
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">My</hi>
            Lord Treasuror Cicill growing into yeares, hauing bene <lb/>
            A good statsmen, the onlye Supporter of the Proestant faction, <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">the</fw>
            <pb n="6r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f06r/add_ms_22591_f06r.jpg"/>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  coming out of France, <lb/>
                  his entertaynement, <lb/>
                  he growes into fauor
               </hi>
            </add>
            the discloser of treasons, and the onlye Mercurye of our tymes, having <lb/>
            bine well acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th the affayres of this Como<ex>n</ex>-wealthe, falls in=<lb break="no"/>
            to a daungerous sicknes, and in p<ex>ro</ex>cesse of time throughe the extremitie <lb/>
            of the maladie dies, not w<ex>i</ex>thout suspition of poyson, according to the <lb/>
            opynion of some, others saye of A secrett disease, some naturallye, <lb/>
            and manye not w<ex>i</ex>thout the privitie of S<ex>i</ex>r Robert Carr / And the <lb/>
            reason of theire opinion was, because the kinge vpon a time, having <lb/>
            given S<ex>i</ex>r Rob<ex>er</ex>t the some of twentie thousand poundes to be paied <lb/>
            by my Lord Treasuror, S<ex>i</ex>r Rob<ex>er</ex>t was denied it, vpon w<ex>hi</ex>ch deniall <lb/>
            there grewe some difference betweene them. The kinge was made <lb/>
            privye to it after this manner; My Lord having told out five thousa<ex>n</ex>d <lb/>
            poundes, layd it in a passage gallerye in severall heapes, &amp; invites <lb/>
            the kinge to breakefast bringing throughe that Gallerye: The kinge de=<lb break="no"/>
            maundes whose that mony was; Answere was made by my Lorde <lb/>
            Treasuror, that it was but the fourth p<ex>ar</ex>te of <ex>tha</ex>t w<ex>hi</ex>ch his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye had <lb/>
            given to S<ex>i</ex>r Robert Carr. Wherevpon the kinge retired fro<ex>m</ex> his <lb/>
            former Graunt, and wish’t S<ex>i</ex>r Robert to satisfye himselfe with <ex>tha</ex>t, <lb/>
            holding it to be a great guifte. He being thus crost in his expecta=<lb break="no"/>
            tion<ex>n</ex>s, harbored in hart the hope of revenge, w<ex>hi</ex>ch aft<ex>e</ex>r happened <lb/>
            as was suspected, but it was not certaine, therefore I omitt it /
         </p>
         <p>
            Vpon the deathe of this Gent<ex>le</ex>man, one Mr Overbury a student <lb/>
            of the lawe in the mydle temple, was newlye arrived out of Fra<ex>nce</ex> <lb/>
            whoe having obtayned some favor in Courte before times, because <lb/>
            of some discontentments gott licence to travell, and nowe at his reto=<lb break="no"/>
            urne was entertayned into the favor of S<ex>i</ex>r Robert Carr, wheth<ex>e</ex>r  <lb/>
            this proceeded of anye love towardes him, or to the intent to <lb/>
            make vse of him is not certaine, yet neverthelesse he puts him <lb/>
            in trust w<ex>i</ex>th his most secrett imploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>; In w<ex>hi</ex>ch he behaves him <lb/>
            selfe honestlye and discreetlye, purchasing by his wise carriage <lb/>
            in that place the good affection and Favor not onlye of S<ex>i</ex>r Rob<ex>er</ex>t, <lb/>
            but others allsoe. In p<ex>ro</ex>cesse of time this Favor pro<add place="above">c</add>v<add place="above">r</add>es p<ex>ro</ex>fitt, p<ex>ro</ex>fit <lb/>
            treasure, treasure honor, honor large ymploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, and in him bett<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            execution; For <hi rend="italic">where diligence and humilitye are assotiate in <lb/>
            great affaires there fauour is accompanied with both</hi>, soe <ex>tha</ex>t many <lb/>
            Courtiers p<ex>er</ex>ceiving his greate hopes, growe into familiarity <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th him: the Knights expectac<ex>i</ex>on are p<ex>er</ex>formed, and his businesses <lb/>
            accomplished rather more then lesse according to his wishes / Soe <lb/>
            that takeing notice of his dilligence to outward appearance, gives <lb/>
            him an extraordinarye cou<ex>n</ex>tenau<ex>n</ex>ce vniting him into freindshipp <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th himselfe; In soe much that to the shewe of the world this bond <lb/>
            was vndissolvable / neither could there be more Freindship vsed <lb/>
            since there was nothing soe secrett, nor anye matter soe pr<ex>i</ex>vate, but <lb/>
            the knight imp<ex>ar</ex>ted it to the advise of Overburye /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Of mrs Turners life <lb/>
                  how <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse &amp; shee <lb/>
                  came acquainted, <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  combinac<ex>i</ex>on of the <lb/>
                  Earles deathe
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">The </hi>Countesse of Essex having harboured in her harte <lb/>
            envie towards her husband, even  vntill this time, makes her <lb/>
            repaire vnto M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner (a Gent<ex>le</ex>woman that fro<ex>m</ex> her youthe <lb/>
            had bine given over to A loose kinde of liffe, being of A lowe
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">stature</fw>
            <pb n="6v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f06v/add_ms_22591_f06v.jpg"/>
            Stature, Faire vissage, for outward behaviour comelye, but in pro=<lb break="no"/>
            digallitie and excesse most ryotous, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch course of liffe, she had <lb/>
            consumed the greatest parte of her husbands meanes &amp; her owne, <lb/>
            soe that nowe wanting wherew<ex>i</ex>th to fullfill her expectac<ex>i</ex>ons &amp; ex=<lb break="no"/>
            treeme pride, falls into evill courses, as to the p<ex>ro</ex>stituc<ex>i</ex>on of her <lb/>
            bodye to comon lust, to practise sorcerye and inchau<ex>n</ex>tm<ex>en</ex>t, &amp; to manie <lb/>
            litle lesse then a flatt bawde. Her husband dying left her in a desp<ex>er</ex>ate <lb/>
            estate, because of her wants, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes she is made apte to <lb/>
            enter into anye evill action, and to entertaine anye motion bee it <lb/>
            never soe faciuorous / A doctors wiffe; whoe was during his liffe, her <lb/>
            Phisition and in that time shee hauing entertayned into her co<ex>m</ex>panye <lb/>
            his saide wiffe, by that meanes p<ex>ro</ex>cured further acquaintance, being <lb/>
            neere of the same disposition and temp<ex>er</ex>ature, as <hi rend="italic">Paris cu<ex>m</ex> paribus <lb/>
            facile congregantur</hi> fro<ex>m</ex> thence it happened that she was suspected <lb/>
            even by her meanes and procurem<ex>en</ex>t before this to have lived a loose <lb/>
            liffe, for whoe can touche pitche and not be defiled, I saye having some <lb/>
            familiaritye w<ex>i</ex>th this woman, and nowe taking some discontentme<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
            at her husband more then heretofore by reason of her falling out <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th him and his sharpe answers (as she conceives) to her, repaires <lb/>
            to her house, and there (amongst other discourses) disgorges her=<lb break="no"/>
            selfe against her husband, whereby the cause of her greife might <lb/>
            easilye be p<ex>er</ex>ceived /  M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner as feeling p<ex>ar</ex>te of her paine pittyes <lb/>
            her, and in hope of profitt being nowe in necessitie and wante, is <lb/>
            easilye drawne to effect anye thinge that shee requires, wherevpo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            by the reporte of some it was concluded at this time betweene the<ex>m</ex>, <lb/>
            to administer poyson to the Earle, but not taking effecte according <lb/>
            to theire expectation, the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse writtes vnto her to this p<ex>u</ex>rpose
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">
               Sweet Turner, as thou hast bine hitherto Soe art thou <lb/>
               Still all my hopes of Good in this worlde. My Lord is as lus=<lb break="no"/>
               tie as euer he was, and hath complayned to my Broth<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
               Howard that hee hath not layne with mee nor used me as <lb/>
               his wife, this makes mee madd, Since of all men I loathe <lb/>
               Shall neuer enioye him whom I loue. /
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            The Earle haueing overpast this euill, and continuing still in <lb/>
            his pristine Estate, procures not anye affection, but more hatred <lb/>
            and loathsomnes, soe that it burst dailye fourth to my Lord, great <lb/>
            discontent, and drawes her headlonge into her owne distruction  /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  S<ex>i</ex>r Rob<ex>er</ex>t Carre <lb/>
                  made visc<ex>ount</ex> Rochest<ex>e</ex>r, <lb/>
                  the acquaintance be <lb/>
                  tweene my Lord of  <lb/>
                  North<ex>amp</ex>ton and him, <lb/>
                  <ex>th</ex>e new affection of <lb/>
                  <ex>th</ex>e countese.  / 
               </hi>
            </add>
            The kinge taking greater liking to this young Gentleman, to <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            intent that he might be noe lesse eminent in honor, then he was po=<lb break="no"/>
            erfull in wealthe and substance, adornes him w<ex>i</ex>th the title of v<add place="above">i</add>sc<ex>ount</ex> <lb/>
            Rochester, bestowes the secretaryshipp of State, vpo<ex>n</ex> him, soe that <lb/>
            his power and his wealthe makes him famous to other nations / 
         </p>
         <p>
            These thinges com<ex>m</ex>ing to my Lord of Northampton<ex>n</ex>s Eares, having <lb/>
            bine A long time A Favorite in Courte, and nowe growing into <lb/>
            <add place="above">y</add>Eares, and by reason thereof but shorte lived, and knowing <ex>th</ex>e favor  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">of</fw>
            <pb n="7r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f07r/add_ms_22591_f07r.jpg"/>
            of the king to depend vpo<ex>n</ex> many incertaineties, and <ex>tha</ex>t allthoughe at <lb/>
            this time he was greatest actor in State affaires, yet if this yonge <lb/>
            man continued his height of glorye, all his dignitie would either <lb/>
            be abated or overshadowed, and that he had not that free accesse to <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            kinges Eares w<ex>hi</ex>ch he had wont to haue, endeavoreth as much as in him <lb/>
            lyeth to make this Courtyer either to be wholye his, or dependant <lb/>
            vpon his Favor, that soe having relation to him, he might make vse <lb/>
            of his greatnes. And for this purpose he begins to applaude <ex>th</ex>e wise=<lb break="no"/>
            dome and governem<ex>en</ex>t of this viscount, his Vertues, outward Cou<ex>r</ex>tship, <lb/>
            comelye Carryage, and to conclude holding him to be A man noe lesse <lb/>
            worthe and desert, then any about the kinge, neither were these things <lb/>
            spoken to pr<ex>i</ex>vate or p<ex>ar</ex>ticuler p<ex>er</ex>sons alone, but even into the Eares  <lb/>
            of the kinge, to the intent the better to <del rend="strikethrough">obtayne</del> Confirme the Kinges <lb/>
            favor towards him
         </p>
         <p>
            These thinges com<ex>m</ex>ing to this yonge Noblemans Eare, hee takes <lb/>
            it as A greate Favor fro<ex>m</ex> soe greate A p<ex>er</ex>sonage, and therefore soe <lb/>
            much the more admires his owne worthe, raysing his carryage above <lb/>
            his wonted Course, an in hope of better thinges applauding eu<ex>er</ex>y <lb/>
            action is p<ex>er</ex>formed by the Earle: By w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes there growes A <lb/>
            kinde of Com<ex>m</ex>unitie betweene them, and there wants nothinge but <lb/>
            entercourse of speeche, for confirmance of acquaintance, &amp; pro=<lb break="no"/>
            curing further relation either to other. Tyme offers oppertunitie, <lb/>
            the Earle and he meete, each changeth acquaintance, w<ex>i</ex>th acqua<ex>n</ex>tance, <lb/>
            A greater familiaritie, soe that manye times letters passe betwene <lb/>
            them in theire absence, and Courtlye discourses being pr<ex>e</ex>sent, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            meanes on all handes A confident amitie is concluded
         </p>
         <p>
            In these times the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse of Essex being A Spectator of those <lb/>
            Fortunes, and p<ex>er</ex>ceiving the viscount to be Still raysed vp vnto hon<ex>o</ex>rs <lb/>
            daylye, in  hope of greater is th more fired w<ex>i</ex>th a lustfull desire, <lb/>
            and the greater is her endeavor by the instigation of some of her <lb/>
            best Freindes to accomplish w<ex>ha</ex>t shee determineth; For greatnesse <lb/>
            doth not quallifye but sett out an edge vpo<ex>n</ex> lustfull appetities, and <lb/>
            where the most meanes are to mainetaine it, there <ex>th</ex>e greater <lb/>
            affecc<ex>i</ex>ons are cherished.  /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The course shee <lb/>
                  takes to procure af <lb/>
                  fection, She co<ex>m</ex>bines <lb/>
                  with Do<ex>ctor</ex> Forma<ex>n</ex>, they <lb/>
                  conclude to bewitch <lb/>
                  the viscount /
               </hi>
            </add>
            In these furious fittes she makes her repaire to m<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner, <lb/>
            and begins A newe complainte, whereby shew makes manifest an <lb/>
            extraordinarye affection towards this yong Gentleman soe <ex>tha</ex>t shee <lb/>
            could not rest w<ex>i</ex>thout his Companye, neither knewe she any meanes <lb/>
            to attaine her endes, there being noe relation nor acquaintance be=<lb break="no"/>
            tweene them / Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> m<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner being Still her Second, &amp; ready <lb/>
            to put anye evill attempt into execution, concludes w<ex>i</ex>th <ex>th</ex>e Countesse <lb/>
            to enchaunt the Viscount to affect her. And for this purpose, they <lb/>
            fall acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th one Doc<ex>tor</ex> Forman that dwelt at Lambeth, be=<lb break="no"/>
            ing an au<ex>n</ex>tient Gent<ex>le</ex>man, and thought to haue Skill in <ex>th</ex>e Magicke <lb/>
            arte. This man by rewardes and guifts was wonne to wyne with <lb/>
            M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner whoe nowe to the intent to preye vpo<ex>n</ex> the Countisse, <lb/>
            endeavor the best they maye to enchaunt the Viscount<ex>es</ex> affecc<ex>i</ex>on  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">toward<ex>es</ex>
                </fw>
            <pb n="7v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f07v/add_ms_22591_f07v.jpg"/>
            towardes her, much time is spent, manye wordes of witchcraft, <lb/>
            great cost in making Pictures of waxe, crosses of Silver, little <lb/>
            bables for that vse, yet all to small purpose. At length they con=<lb break="no"/>
            tinuinge in their <del rend="strikethrough">securitie</del> socerie, advise her to liue at Court, wher <lb/>
            shee had free accesse w<ex>i</ex>thout controule, thoughe small acquainta<ex>n</ex>ce <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th him, whom shee most respected, neverthelesse shewing an affable <lb/>
            Countenance towards him, hoping in p<ex>ro</ex>sesse of time to obtayne w<ex>ha</ex>t <lb/>
            shee required. Time offers oppertunitie, and amongst oth<ex>e</ex>rs at length <lb/>
            these two fall into league, the Countesse being ioyfull of her preye, <lb/>
            admires him, vses all kindnes that maye be to intrapp him, hee <lb/>
            whether by these inchau<ex>n</ex>tm<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, or by the lightnes of his owne disposit<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            carryed, is as much besotted, nu<ex>m</ex>bring her amongst the best women, <lb/>
            and doubling every acc<ex>i</ex>on in his estimation, in soe much <ex>tha</ex>t he could <lb/>
            scarce rest but in her companie; wherevpo<ex>n</ex> their meetings growe <lb/>
            frequent, and discourses pleasant, by these meanes inflaminge <lb/>
            the fire of A lustfull appetite /
         </p>
         <p>
            These thinges hauing happened soe well to her expectatio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            causes A great love to these good Couple, vidh<ex>elici</ex>t Doc<ex>tor</ex> Forman, and <lb/>
            M<ex>ist</ex>tris Turner, solliciting them w<ex>i</ex>th letters, w<ex>i</ex>th monye, &amp; larg p<ex>ro</ex>mises, <lb/>
            to continue Still her Freindes. They willing to make vse of her <lb/>
            wealthe, more then expecting anie good they couldd accomplishe by <lb/>
            theire Arte, p<ex>er</ex>sist amongst her imploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> m<ex>is</ex>tris Turner makes trial<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            for herselfe, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes manye slight and vnaccustomed tricks  <lb/>
            are practised, and nowe reported to haue retourned to the hurte <lb/>
            of manye, For A womans hand being once entred into the acte of <lb/>
            Sinne, runs headlong to her distruction, turning those evill artes <lb/>
            to evill endes, and endeavoring to purchase by <ex>tha</ex>t p<ex>ro</ex>fit &amp; comodity 
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  How it was thought <lb/>
                  the E<ex>arl</ex> of North<ex>amp</ex>ton had <lb/>
                  a hand in this busi=<lb break="no"/>
                  nesse, inuits <ex>th</ex>e visc<ex>ount</ex> <lb/>
                  to Supper, <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tis <lb/>
                  and he meets, places <lb/>
                  of meeting are apppoin <lb/>
                  ted the Earle made <lb/>
                  Chau<ex>n</ex>cellor of Ca<ex>m</ex>bridg
               </hi>
            </add>
            It was vulgarlye opinionated that the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse of Essex hau=<lb break="no"/>
            ing sustayned those discontentm<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> w<ex>i</ex>th her husband, acquainted her <lb/>
            vncle the Earle of Northampto<ex>n</ex> of her affection, espetiallye to=<lb break="no"/>
            ward<ex>es</ex> this Viscount, whoe waighing the p<ex>ro</ex>fitt <ex>tha</ex>t might redound <lb/>
            to his owne imploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> , if there were such affinitie had betweene <lb/>
            them, seemed to give A likeing towards it, and endeavored rather <lb/>
            to further it, then at all to diswade her, or giving her that honest <lb/>
            and good Counsell to be dutifull to her husband as was fitting. <lb/>
            Howsoever the first meeting that they had, wherein there was any <lb/>
            Conference, was at this Earles house, whoe invited <ex>th</ex>e Viscount <lb/>
            to supper, and there finding the Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse, they at theire pleasure <lb/>
            appointed meetings for further discourses, but whether there <lb/>
            was anie one made privye to these thinges, is not evident; but <lb/>
            from this time, the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse and Viscount continewe theire loose <lb/>
            Course of liffe, and as was com<ex>m</ex>o<ex>n</ex>lye suspected, had furth<ex>e</ex>r rela=<lb break="no"/>
            tion then was fitting, to the great disparagem<ex>en</ex>t of them both, &amp; dishon<ex>o</ex>r <lb/>
            of soe noble A house, what the issues of these thinges are, continew <lb/>
            in obscuritie. Notw<ex>i</ex>thstanding the Earle of Northampto<ex>n</ex> is much <lb/>
            blamed, the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse defamed, and the Viscount himselfe for <lb/>
            his loosenes suspected /
         </p>
         <p>
            Nowe was thus Lord p<ex>ro</ex>pounded at the regent house to bee <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Chau<ex>n</ex>cellor</fw>
            <pb n="8r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f08r/add_ms_22591_f08r.jpg"/>
            Chau<ex>n</ex>cellor of Cambridge, the Schollers fall into divers opinions, <lb/>
            And the Ræmists p<ex>ro</ex>pound the Prince to oppose him, the Elect<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            passes of the Earles side / he refuses, but still flatters <ex>th</ex>e Schollors, <lb/>
            makes the kinge acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th it, and thoughe willing to vnder <lb/>
            take it, yet shewing an vnwillingnes, endeavored rather to bee <lb/>
            vrged to it, then receave it voluntarie, this was because impu=<lb break="no"/>
            ted because of his opposite the Prince, but the truthe was, to <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>ceave whether the Schollers affections were setled vpo<ex>n</ex> love, <lb/>
            and respect vnto himselfe, or meerelye to depend vpo<ex>n</ex> his great=<lb break="no"/>
            nes / The kinge writs in his behalfe to the Vice Chancellor, they <lb/>
            p<ex>ro</ex>ceed to A newe Election, the Earle againe is Chosen, his Title <lb/>
            sent him, and he in requitall sendes manye flattering letters, <lb/>
            and plausive / and that they might be the more acceptable, being <lb/>
            sent to Schollers, wrote to them in lattaine / it is intollerable <lb/>
            the flaterye he vsed /    
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Ouerburye growes <lb/>
                  into Grace with <ex>th</ex>e K<ex>ing</ex> <lb/>
                  is made K<ex>nigh</ex>t, <ex>th</ex>e inter-<lb break="no"/>
                  course betweene <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  countise &amp; <ex>th</ex>e visco<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
                  made Knowne vnto <lb/>
                  Ouerburye
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">After</hi> some continewance of time Mr Overburye growes <lb/>
            eminent in Courte, aswell by reason of the viscounts favor, <unclear>all</unclear> <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            good and Carefull diligence <ex>tha</ex>t he had in Courte ymploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, <lb/>
            soe that nowe Comparying his worthe with his wealthe, he is had <lb/>
            in more respect, and the honor of knighthood bestowed vpo<ex>n</ex> him <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th hope of better thinges; this howsoever in itselfe it bee not <lb/>
            valuable, yet in the Spectators it striketh a doubte especiallye <lb/>
            in the Viscount, For Soveraignetie  and love can abide noe parago<ex>n</ex>
         </p>
         <p>
            Thinges that at the beginni<ex>n</ex>g p<ex>ro</ex>ceed w<ex>i</ex>th Modestie are little <lb/>
            or nothing regarded; but when men growe old in such thinges <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            are hatefull, they make everye place alike, and with a blushlesse <lb/>
            Face comitt them to the open veiwe. By this meanes Overburye <lb/>
            came acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th this entercourse betweene the Viscou<ex>n</ex>t and <lb/>
            the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse, for nowe they having some tyme of Familiaritie  &amp; <lb/>
            intercourse  in remote p<ex>ar</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, Shame not to com<ex>m</ex>itt the Sinne of <lb/>
            Venerie in the Courte, and that to the privitie of S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas, who <lb/>
            both loathes and hates w<ex>ha</ex>t he sees, avoyding rather the<ex>n</ex> intrudinge <lb/>
            himselfe to the knowledge of it / neither medles he anye way or  <lb/>
            other w<ex>i</ex>th the knowledge of it, but lets them alone in their vitious <lb/>
            Courses, and rather seemes to be ignorant then to take anye <lb/>
            notice of it /
         </p>
         <p>
            Never thelesse he is ymployed to carrye letters to &amp; againe <lb/>
            betweene the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse and the Viscounte, some to Pater Noster <lb/>
            rowe, some to Hamer Smithe, and others to other plac<ex>es</ex> of meeting, <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch were appointed  betweene them / both w<ex>hi</ex>ch means co<ex>m</ex>paring <lb/>
            both acc<ex>i</ex>ons togither, he entred into the secrets of this misterie, <lb/>
            and became acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th more thinges then the Viscounte <lb/>
            would haue had time, from whence A kinde of Iealousie was <lb/>
            Carryed to wards him /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Of the Second Co<ex>m</ex>p<ex>lain</ex>t <lb/>
                  of the Earle of Essex, <lb/>
            		the
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Nowe </hi>the Earle of Essexe p<ex>er</ex>ceiving himselfe to be rather <lb/>
            lesse regarded then anye white at all esteemed, enters into <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">A</fw>
            <pb n="8v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f08v/add_ms_22591_f08v.jpg"/>
            <add place="LM">
                    <hi rend="italic">the Countiss co<ex>n</ex>tinues <lb/>
            with Turner to be=<lb break="no"/>
            witch him, it taketh <lb/>
            effect, Forma<ex>n</ex>s death <lb/>
            one Gresham is en=<lb break="no"/>
            tertayned in the bu <lb/>
            sines /</hi>
                </add> <lb/>
            A newe discourse with his ladye, w<ex>i</ex>th manye p<ex>ro</ex>testac<ex>i</ex>ons both of  <lb/>
            his Constancie and love toward<ex>es</ex> her, but with all tells her of <lb/>
            her loosnes, of <ex>th</ex>e reporte of the Vulgar, and what A Straung <lb/>
            Course of liffe she ledd, contrarye to all Pietie and honestie / <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch Stung the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse to the harte, and more incensed &amp; augm<ex>en</ex>ted <lb/>
            her mallice towards him, soe <ex>tha</ex>t in A greate furye, shee takes her <lb/>
            Coache, and repares to her au<ex>n</ex>tient acquaintance m<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner, <lb/>
            whoe according to her old custome is readye to p<ex>er</ex>forme anie evill <lb/>
            Acte, and there they Combine to bewitche the Earle, and p<ex>ro</ex>cure a  <lb/>
            Frigiditie <hi rend="italic">quoad hanc</hi>. For this purpose Doctor Foreman was <lb/>
            sent for, letters are written for the p<ex>ro</ex>curing of meanes, picturs <lb/>
            in waxe are made, Crosses and many Strange and vncooth thing<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            (for what will the evill leave vnattempted to accomplish theire <lb/>
            endes) manye attempts failed, and Still the Earle Stood  it out, <lb/>
            At last they framed A Picture in Waxe, and gott A thorne fro<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            A Tree that bore leaves, and Stucke vpo<ex>n</ex> the privitie of <ex>th</ex>e said <lb/>
            picture, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes they accomplished theire desires /
         </p>
         <p>
            This being done according to her expectatio<ex>n</ex>, she repaires to <lb/>
            her house at Chartlye, and thither the Earle<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> comes to her, but <lb/>
            whether he was more lustie then shee expected, or what other <lb/>
            accident happened, it is vnknowne; Neverthelesse she grewe <lb/>
            iealous of her art, and falls into A great feare that all theire <lb/>
            labor were lost: Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> shee writs A lett<ex>er</ex> to Doc<ex>tor</ex> Forman to <lb/>
            this Effecte / 
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The cou<ex>n</ex>t l<ex>ett</ex>re to <lb/>
                  Docter Forman
               </hi>
            </add> 
            <hi rend="bold">
               Sweet Father, allthough I haue found you readye at all <lb/>
               tymes to further mee. yet must I still crave yo<ex>u</ex>r help: wher=<lb break="no"/>
               fore I beseech you remember <ex>tha</ex>t you keepe the dores close, <lb/>
               and that you still retaine the Lord with mee, and his af=<lb break="no"/>
               fection towards mee, I haue noe Cause but to be co<ex>n</ex>fident <lb/>
               in you, allthoughe the world be against mee, yet Heaven <lb/>
               failes me not. Manie are the troubles I sustaine, <ex>th</ex>e dog=<lb break="no"/>
               gednes of my Lord, the Crostnes of my Enemyes, and the <lb/>
               subuersion of my fortunes vnlesse you by you<ex>r</ex> wisedome <lb/>
               doe deliuer me out of the myddest of this wildernes, w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
               I entreat for Gods sake. From Chartley <lb/>
               your affectionate louing daught<ex>e</ex>r
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="align-right">
            <hi rend="bold">
               Frances Essex
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            This letter (coming to the handes of the old man) p<ex>ro</ex>cures A <lb/>
            newe attempte, and nowe he goes and inchaunt<ex>es</ex> A nutmegg and <lb/>
            A letter, one to be given to the Viscounte in his drincke, the other <lb/>
            to be sent vnto him as a pr<ex>e</ex>sent / these thinges being accomplished <lb/>
            he not long after dies, leaving behinde him some of these letters, <lb/>
            whereby the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse had entercourse w<ex>i</ex>th him, in his pockett, w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            gaue some light into the busines, amongst w<ex>hi</ex>ch this same was one. /
         </p>
         <p>
            Docter Foreman being dead, M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner wanted one to assist <lb/>
            her, wherevpo<ex>n</ex> at the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesses coming vpp to London, one Gresha<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">was</fw>
            <pb n="9r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f09r/add_ms_22591_f09r.jpg"/>
            was nominated to be entertained in this busines, and in p<ex>ro</ex>cesse <lb/>
            of time was whollye interressed in it, this man was had in suspit<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            to haue had A hand in the Gunpowder Treason, he wrote soe neere <lb/>
            it in his Almanacks, but w<ex>i</ex>thout all question he was a very skill=<lb break="no"/>
            full man in his Mathematicks, and in his latter time in witchcraft, <lb/>
            as was suspected, and therefore the fitter to be employed in those <lb/>
            practises, w<ex>hi</ex>ch as they were Devilish, soe the Devill had A hand in the<ex>m</ex> /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The Countes Sends <lb/>
                  <ex>th</ex>e viscount this L<ex>ett</ex>re <lb/>
                  inchau<ex>n</ex>ted by D<ex>octor</ex> F<ex>orman</ex> <lb/>
                  places of meetinge <lb/>
                  appointed, their in=<lb break="no"/>
                  tollerable loosenes, <lb/>
                  Poetts verses vpon  <lb/>
                  them, <ex>th</ex>e begining of <lb/>
                  the fall
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Vpon </hi>her retourne shee sendes gratulac<ex>i</ex>ons to the Viscounte, <lb/>
            and w<ex>i</ex>th those the letters sent her by Docter Forman, he reads it, &amp; <lb/>
            the more he reads the more is intangled, for noe man knowes the <lb/>
            miseryes that are conteyned in evill Arts, and whoe can w<ex>i</ex>thstand  <lb/>
            the wordes of evill tonges. wherevpon he retournes answere, and  <lb/>
            newe places of meeting are assigned, amongst the rest one at Ha<ex>m</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            mer Smithe / In the meane time the Viscount makes dispatch of his <lb/>
            busines, leaves thinges halfe done, halfe vndone to the intent he <lb/>
            might meete her whoe had nowe stayed for his coming  aboue sixe <lb/>
            houres, And being mett they solemplye salute each other, fall into <lb/>
            divers discourses and insinuatinge phrases fro<ex>m</ex> wordes to deeds &amp; <lb/>
            fro<ex>m</ex> speaking to acting the Sinne of Venerie. The cou<ex>n</ex>tesse haveinge <lb/>
            obtayned that shee desired, and <ex>th</ex>e Viscount caught in the nett of <lb/>
            adulac<ex>i</ex>on, the more he Striveth to be loosned is caught <ex>th</ex>e faster, Soe <lb/>
            that lust haueing by these meanes gott libertie, being Covered w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            greatnes like A Fire long concealed in a pile of rotten wood, bursts <lb/>
            forthe w<ex>i</ex>th all loosnes and licentiousnes; places of more frequent <lb/>
            and pr<ex>i</ex>vate meetings being concluded betweene them, p<ex>er</ex>sons fitting <lb/>
            to their purposes being acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th their p<ex>ro</ex>ceedings, watch words <lb/>
            are given; All these things haueing relation to A certaine end, <lb/>
            make them more boldlie and safelye to accomplish that w<ex>hi</ex>ch both true  <lb/>
            and the memorye cannot demonstrate in former history. Now these <lb/>
            good p<ex>ar</ex>ts w<ex>hi</ex>ch seemed heretofore to be hopefull in the Viscount, co<ex>n</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            sumes to sinders, and <ex>th</ex>e corruption remaines to brand him in the <lb/>
            forehead for his ill living. His modestie becomes ecclipsed, his be=<lb break="no"/>
            haviour light, his Carriage vnseemelye in his place. Nothinge soe <lb/>
            costlye, nor tire soe vncouth, but at all Costs and Charges he obtay <lb/>
            nes it for <ex>th</ex>e encrease of Favor. Newe fash<ex>i</ex>ons are p<ex>ro</ex>duced that <lb/>
            soe he might shewe more beautifull and faire, and <ex>tha</ex>t his favor &amp; <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>sonage might be made manifest to the world. And for this p<ex>u</ex>rpos <lb/>
            yellowe Bandes, dusted heire, Curled, Crisped, frisled, slicked, <lb/>
            Skinnes, open breasts beyond accustomed modestie, w<ex>i</ex>th many oth<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            inordinate attires were worne on both sydes to the shew of <ex>th</ex>e world, <lb/>
            soe that for the encrease of dishonest appetites they were abunda<ex>n</ex>tly <lb/>
            practised and praysed. Surfiting thus vpo<ex>n</ex> pleasure, having bine <lb/>
            before accustomed vnto hardnes, Causeth him to fall into all man<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            of forgettfullnes, letting all thinges goe to wracke, Carelesse <lb/>
            in attendance, neglect in state affaires, ignorant of his owne worth <lb/>
            subiecting himselfe to the lustfull appetite of an evill woman, <lb/>
            accounting noe time soe well spent, nor houre deemed soe happy, <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">as</fw>
            <pb n="9v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f09v/add_ms_22591_f09v.jpg"/>
            as when dalliance and pleasant discourses passe betweene them <lb/>
            either in wordes or writtings: soe that in him maye be verifyed <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            old saying of the Poett /
         </p>
         <p>
            <cb/>
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  non facile invenium multis e millibus vnum <lb/>
               	virtutem precium qui putat esse suum <lb/>
                  Fallet eum vitiam Spetie virtutis et vmbra <lb/>
                  Cum sit Trust habita vultuq<ex>ue</ex>, Et veste Seberu<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
               	Nec dubie tanqua<ex>m</ex> fruge laudatur auarum<ex>m</ex>
               </hi>
            </foreign>
            <cb/>
            <hi rend="italic">
               Of thousand youthes there Scarce is one <lb/>
               that vertue valueth as his price <lb/>
            	For vice deceiues them: and alone <lb/>
            	the shewe of vertue blindes their Eyes <lb/>
            	Allthough their cou<ex>n</ex>tenau<ex>n</ex>ce pensiue bee <lb/>
            	theire Garments and their habit graue <lb/>
            	Yet all theire fruite doubtlesse wee See <lb/>
            	Is lust and glorye that they craue. /
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            These thinges laie him open to the ill affection of them <ex>tha</ex>t hate <lb/>
            him, and laies the foundation of his vtter subvertion since the <lb/>
            Eyes of all men are vpon such as are eminent / and as blacke vpo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            white is soonest discerned, soe evill Conditions and lascivious <lb/>
            affecc<ex>i</ex>ons are soonest p<ex>er</ex>ceived in such p<ex>er</ex>sons /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The faithfullnes <lb/>
                  of S<ex>i</ex>r Tho<ex>mas</ex> Ouerbury <lb/>
                  to <ex>th</ex>e viscount, the <lb/>
                  aduice he gaue him: <lb/>
                  contemned: fauors <lb/>
                  are more bestowed <lb/>
                  vpon him, made of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  priuye Councell
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">This</hi> course of liffe being some thinge Strange to those that <lb/>
            were ignorant of these designes, gives newe occosions of wonder, <lb/>
            and admiraation, how he should Still continew his favor, manye <lb/>
            thinges being left vndone, others done to the halfs, insomuch as <lb/>
            all must lye vpon Overburyes necke, And this doth he honestly <lb/>
            and to the Viscounts creditt attributing every action to his doinge <lb/>
            allthough of him neglected; Answeres for him in his absence, has=<lb break="no"/>
            tens dispatches in his pr<ex>e</ex>sence, furthers the request of sutors, and <lb/>
            thoughe the neglect and Carelesnes of the Viscount growes into <lb/>
            greater creditt and esteeme, soe <ex>tha</ex>t his Carefullnes, sufficiencie. <lb/>
            and deligence, makes him become eminent, and beloved both of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Kinge and Cou<ex>n</ex>cell, yet neverthelesse he lessens his owne worth, <lb/>
            gives all the dignitie to the Viscount, endeavoringe to searche out <lb/>
            how the people stood affected towards him / findes both many Co<ex>m</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            playnts and some Iniuryes to be done vnto him, whoe being blinded <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th pleasure overslippes them or letts them passe w<ex>i</ex>th small res=<lb break="no"/>
            pecte: Wherevpon he takes occasion at A tyme Convenient, to <lb/>
            vtter these or the like wordes to him. S<ex>i</ex>r howsoever oth<ex>e</ex>r thinges <lb/>
            maie passe either with small regard or be smoothered w<ex>i</ex>th honor <lb/>
            and greatnes, yet such thinges as laie a man open to obliquie <lb/>
            and contempt, can hardlye be obscured in a personne publique <lb/>
            ans eminent as yo<ex>u</ex>r Lordship is, w<ex>hi</ex>ch things are often esteemed <lb/>
            to be in a man that outwardlye seemeth light and effeminate, or <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">inwardlye</fw>
            <pb n="10r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f010r/add_ms_22591_f010r.jpg"/>
            inwardlye wanteth the ballast of Governemt to poyse externall <lb/>
            actions. Of a truthe Sir be it spoken w<ex>i</ex>thout offence, <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>r</ex>t calls <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r modestie into question, and feares that those honors that should <lb/>
            be hereditarye to noble p<ex>er</ex>sonages wilbe obscured w<ex>i</ex>th eminent <del rend="strikethrough">is</del> <hi rend="italic"> <lb/>
            </hi>evills, and blemished w<ex>i</ex>th levitie and vnconsta<ex>n</ex>cie; These w<ex>i</ex>th many <lb/>
            other discourses, having at this time past betweene them, sounded <lb/>
            somethinge harshlye to the Viscounts Eares, as all good counsell <lb/>
            becomes evill to those <ex>tha</ex>t are evill; And in a kinde of ang<ex>e</ex>r flung <lb/>
            from him thoughe vndeserved, yet neverthelesse all his Cou<ex>n</ex>tena<ex>n</ex>ce <lb/>
            and favor was not wholye obscured, but <ex>tha</ex>t he might Still enioye <lb/>
            that w<ex>hi</ex>ch <del rend="strikethrough">was</del> he expected w<ex>hi</ex>ch was hope of pr<ex>e</ex>ferm<ex>en</ex>t /
         </p>
         <p>
            More favors are bestowed vpo<ex>n</ex> the Viscount, being called to <lb/>
            be one of the pr<ex>i</ex>vie Counsell, w<ex>hi</ex>ch honor howsoever it was greate <lb/>
            and more then was expected / yet because he was young (one that <lb/>
            to the opinion of the world was of noe education literature or ex=<lb break="no"/>
            perience besides these inordinate Courses) brings him into fur=<lb break="no"/>
            ther contempt of the world, soe <ex>tha</ex>t everye man wo<add place="above">u</add>ld take the <lb/>
            freedome of their language, and speake harshlye of these p<ex>ro</ex>ceeding<ex>es</ex>, <lb/>
            some condemning his course of liffe, others his insufficiencie be=<lb break="no"/>
            cause of his youthe, and most his want of experience, by which <lb/>
            meanes his greatnes overtopps his substance: And as A Shipp <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout ballast is tottered to and againe to the terror of those <lb/>
            that are in it in a Storme and highe water; even soe these honors <lb/>
            thus suddainlye bestowed on him before the due time, laies him <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            more open to the evill opinion of the envious, and w<ex>i</ex>th some doth <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            sooner hasten his ruyn / For w<ex>hi</ex>ch cause it behooveth such as are thus <lb/>
            drawne vpp meerelye by Fortune either to be possessed of such <lb/>
            vertues before hand, that thereby they might mainetaine the<ex>m</ex>selvs <lb/>
            in theire greatnes, or els to expect a suddaine overthrowe at a  <lb/>
            time vnexpected / 
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  1: Speech of mar=<lb break="no"/>
                  riage w<ex>i</ex>th the Pals=<lb break="no"/>
                  graue / condicons co<ex>n</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
                  cluded vpon / <lb/>
                  2: The Prince <lb/>
                  taks dislike at <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  viscount, the Princes <lb/>
                  death. rumors vpon <lb/>
                  the Same
               </hi>
            </add>
            Nowe Prince Henrye was living, and having some intellige<ex>nce</ex> <lb/>
            of his loose kinde of liffe, w<ex>hi</ex>ch the Visocunt ledd, and beinge some <lb/>
            thing iealous of him, for because of <ex>tha</ex>t he heard, doth vtterlye <lb/>
            dislike him, forbeares his Companie, and whether for <ex>tha</ex>t or some <lb/>
            other cause it is vnknowne falls flatt at odds w<ex>i</ex>th him, not once <lb/>
            giving him anye cou<ex>n</ex>tenau<ex>n</ex>ce or vouchsafeing him his companye / <lb/>
            Not long after as it might be in the begining of Nove<ex>m</ex>ber he fell <lb/>
            sicke, continued soe some weeke or little more, the maladie incr=<lb break="no"/>
            easing (lying in his head,) he dies. A man maye saie of this Prince <lb/>
            as was said of Macenas both for wisedome and Strength of body <lb/>
            there was not the like to be found amongst the English / The hope <lb/>
            of England, Strange was the accident, and manye the rumors <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            ensued vpon his death, some saie that A French Physition killed <lb/>
            him, others <ex>tha</ex>t he was poysoned, againe others thought that he was <lb/>
            bewitched, yet noe certeinetye could be found but <ex>tha</ex>t he dyed <lb/>
            a naturall death. This accident filled all the kingdome with <lb/>
            lamentac<ex>i</ex>ons, and caused the wedding that followed at Candle <lb/>
            Masse after to be kept in sable / the Funeralls were p<ex>er</ex>formed <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">in</fw>
            <pb n="10v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f010v/add_ms_22591_f010v.jpg"/>
            in greate State, and, w<ex>i</ex>th more greiffe, much might be said, but I <lb/>
            leave it, my purpose being onlye in breiffe to sett out those matt<ex>e</ex>rs <lb/>
            to memorie, that after Ages maye see the evels of our times when <lb/>
            the greatest p<ex>ar</ex>te of manye Courtiers Actions are to find out tricks  <lb/>
            howe to circu<ex>m</ex>vent their fellow Servaunts, and some (if it were possi=<lb break="no"/>
            ble) to dispossesse the king of his dignitie and hereafter shalbe shewed, <lb/>
            soe manye are the discontents <ex>tha</ex>t are cherrished amongst them /
         </p>
         <p>
            These domesticke affaires hauing thus happened, and <ex>th</ex>e deathe <lb/>
            of the Prince filling the Courte w<ex>i</ex>th sorrowe, and the Court being <lb/>
            full of other implym<ex>en</ex>t  by reason of the Marriage <ex>tha</ex>t was to bee <lb/>
            had w<ex>i</ex>th the Palsgrave of the Rhyne and her grace (whoe was now <lb/>
            marriagable) past over the rest in Sylence. The match is concluded, <lb/>
            and great expectac<ex>i</ex>on &amp; provision for his coming over to p<ex>er</ex>forme <lb/>
            the Ceremonies of Matrimonie are made, at whose com<ex>m</ex>ing manye <lb/>
            rumors were spread abroade: First <ex>tha</ex>t the Spaniard tooke this to <lb/>
            harte, and therevpo<ex>n</ex> laide to doe him some mischeiffe by the waye, <lb/>
            That there was A Shipp of Pockett Pistols come oute of Spaine, &amp; <lb/>
            that it was intended by the Papists to have made A massacre, &amp; <lb/>
            that North<ex>amp</ex>ton did vtterlye oppose this matche, for he was as great <lb/>
            an Enemie to the Dutche and p<ex>ro</ex>testants, as even Cicill was their <lb/>
            Freinde, and <ex>tha</ex>t manye Preists were arrived and publiq<ex>ue</ex> pro=<lb break="no"/>
            cession had by the Papists and such like; yet neverthelesse it was <lb/>
            accomplished w<ex>i</ex>th great <del rend="strikethrough">Stren</del> pompe and State / All are <ex>th</ex>e grea=<lb break="no"/>
            test p<ex>ar</ex>te of the Nobillitye being theere p<ex>re</ex>sent: the Nobles present <lb/>
            A maske in the great banquiting house, the Gent<ex>le</ex>men of <ex>th</ex>e  Mydle <lb/>
            Temple another and Grayes end A thirde, besides three dayes <lb/>
            Tilting and run<ex>n</ex>ing at the Ringe, the kinge himselfe in p<ex>er</ex>son with <lb/>
            the young Prince <ex>tha</ex>t nowe is kinge besides manye other pastimes, <lb/>
            both statelye and becoming the dignitie of A Kinge /  
         </p>
         <p>
            At this tyme there was Proclamation against Farthingals, <lb/>
            but to litle purpose, for they rather encreased greater then de=<lb break="no"/>
            minished, for, where a thinge is once growne into A habitt, it is <lb/>
            hardlye to be restrayned.  There was another Proclamatio<ex>n</ex> vpo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            the former reporte of the Com<ex>m</ex>ing of A Shipp of Pockett Pistols <lb/>
            out of Spaine, that noe man should carrye A Pistole in his Pocket, <lb/>
            nor anye <ex>tha</ex>t should be lesse then A Foot longe in the barrell. About <lb/>
            this time allsoe the Papist were disarmed, and manye Straunge  <lb/>
            rumors raysed, w<ex>hi</ex>ch things because they were vncertaine I omitt <lb/>
            to relate them, being rather p<ex>er</ex>tinent to State / then vnto p<ex>ro</ex>fitt /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">Ambassadors sent in=<lb break="no"/>
               to Russia, Swethia, <lb/>
               and other Prouinces  <lb/>
               for the renewing of <lb/>
               freindship of <ex>th</ex>e Lea=<lb break="no"/>
               guer in the Low Cou<ex>n</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
               tryes <ex>th</ex>e Rumor of it /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Manye</hi> outrages haueing bine nowe of late committed, <lb/>
            by the Arche Duke vpo<ex>n</ex> the States, Divers rumors are raised, co<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            cerning A league, both Straunge and allmost vniversall, For <lb/>
            there were p<ex>ar</ex>ties; the Pope, the Emperor, the Kinge of Spaine, <lb/>
            and A Cardinall to aide the Arch Duke against the States. The <lb/>
            Foundation of this Combustion was laide vpo<ex>n</ex> <ex>th</ex>e sackinge of A <lb/>
            Protestant Towne in Brabant / Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> Grave Morris drew <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">out</fw>
            <pb n="11r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f011r/add_ms_22591_f011r.jpg"/>
            out ten thousand into <ex>th</ex>e Feilde, and some fewe blowes happened &amp; <lb/>
            suspected <ex>tha</ex>t it would haue gone further, and that there would haue <lb/>
            bine A generall opposition betweene <del rend="strikethrough">them </del>Protestants &amp; Papists, <lb/>
            but by meanes of the Pope and the kinge it was agreed, and went <lb/>
            noe further, but left A scarr to geive a newe occasion /
         </p>
         <p>
            The warr of Denmarke was allsoe brought vnto a happie end, <lb/>
            and the kinge retayned his right there: Not long after, <ex>th</ex>e yssue wher <lb/>
            of, Ambassadors were sent vnto Musco to renewe the league of <lb/>
            Freindshipp w<ex>i</ex>th the Emperor, whoe being nowe brought lowe by <lb/>
            continuall warrs, was glad to entertaine such A motion, traffique <lb/>
            is confirmed there w<ex>i</ex>th <ex>tha</ex>t Nation And fro<ex>m</ex> thence <ex>th</ex>e same Ambassa=<lb break="no"/>
            dors went to Swethia to conclude A league of Freindshippe, the <lb/>
            reason whereof was thought to be for the au<ex>n</ex>tient amitie that had <lb/>
            bine heretofore betweene the kinge and that nation. Fro<ex>m</ex> thence they <lb/>
            went to the Duke of Clove, w<ex>i</ex>th salutac<ex>i</ex>ons /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The suite of the <lb/>
                  cloath workers, my  <lb/>
                  Lo<ex>rd</ex> of Rochest<ex>e</ex>r sta<ex>n</ex>ds <lb/>
                  for them, <ex>th</ex>e co<ex>m</ex>plaint <lb/>
                  of the countesse, she <lb/>
                  shewes for a diuorce /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Nowe</hi> this yeere the Cloath workers (being couetuous of larg <lb/>
            ymploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>) petition to the king and Councell that there might go <lb/>
            noe more white Cloathes out of this kingdome, but that they might <lb/>
            be all dressed and dyed heere, before they went over, and the <lb/>
            reasons of their petition were three: first that the Hollander, <lb/>
            making vse of dressing and dying our Cloth, sould vs our owne <lb/>
            Clothe allmost double the vallewe <ex>tha</ex>t they bought it for, whereby <lb/>
            they were enriched, and wee impoverished / A second reason, that <lb/>
            whereas there are a multitude of Poore in this kingdome that <lb/>
            wanted ymployment, if they might have the dying &amp; dressing of <lb/>
            these Clothes, it would finde them worke, whereby they might be <lb/>
            releived, and there was noe reason, whye anye other should make <lb/>
            benefitt of that w<ex>hi</ex>ch wee might make good vse of our selves. Last <lb/>
            lye, whereas the trade of dressing of Cloath began to decaye, if <lb/>
            nowe they might but haue this, in p<ex>ro</ex>cesse of time it might be rest=<lb break="no"/>
            red, and they might haue as good Skill to dresse Clothe as <ex>th</ex>e Dutch <lb/>
            men. My Lord of Rochester, my Lord of Northa<ex>m</ex>pton, and my Lo<ex>rd</ex> <lb/>
            Treasuror that nowe is, were great agents in this busines, and <lb/>
            were thought to haue bine p<ex>ro</ex>mised great som<ex>m</ex>es of monye to <lb/>
            accomplish it  
         </p>
         <p>
            Nowe the Countesse begins newe Compl<ex>ain</ex>t<ex>es</ex> and findinge her <lb/>
            arte to continew Firme and that indeed there was such frigiditie <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">quoad hanc</hi> accomplished, that her husband the good Earle of Essex <lb/>
            could not execute the office of A husband, shee vp and tells her <lb/>
            Freindes that shee is still A mayde, and <ex>tha</ex>t shee had good cause <lb/>
            to complayne, since <ex>tha</ex>t shee had continued soe long his wiffe, she <lb/>
            in that space had never the fruition of that pleasure that ought <lb/>
            to be betweene man and wiffe, For w<ex>hi</ex>ch cause she p<ex>ro</ex>tested that <lb/>
            shee would never keepe him Companye anye longer &amp; desired <lb/>
            A divorcem<ex>en</ex>t because of his insufficiencie. This seemed Strange <lb/>
            vnto the world, whoe tooke notice of the Earle to be of an able <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">bodye</fw>
            <pb n="11v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f011v/add_ms_22591_f011v.jpg"/>
            bodye, and likelye to haue manye Children, and to vndertake anye <lb/>
            exploite for the good of the Como<ex>n</ex> wealthe, indeed valuing this to bee <lb/>
            but an idle and vaine reumor that was spread (as often happeneth) <lb/>
            to see howe such A thinge would be liked in the world, and therefore <lb/>
            lett it passe w<ex>i</ex>th litle notice / In the meanetyme there is A motion <lb/>
            betweene Rochester and her for A Marriage, and since it was soe <lb/>
            that the World had taken notice of her loosnes, nowe to make some <lb/>
            satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on, they would consum<ex>m</ex>ate A wedding betweene the<ex>m</ex>. This <lb/>
            motion was well liked on both p<ex>ar</ex>ties, but the obstacle remayned, her <lb/>
            husband was alive, and the lawe would not p<ex>er</ex>mitt her to haue two <lb/>
            husbands, Wherevpon shee growes soe much more the Eager of a  <lb/>
            divorce, that soe shee might haue A newe husband (for women of <lb/>
            her disposition delight in change) and therefore renewes her Co<ex>m</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            plainte. Advise is taken in the busines, whether such A thinge <lb/>
            maye be had, there being noe cause publique, as adulterye or <lb/>
            dislike of the husband. Againe it was A question, whether the <lb/>
            wiffe might sue A divorce or not, for that the Bill of divorcement <lb/>
            was given to the husband, and not to the wiffe / Manye suche like <lb/>
            obiections being disputed to and againe, at last it is concluded, <lb/>
            That in Case the Earle was soe vnable as shee reported to exe=<lb break="no"/>
            cute the office of A husband, and that if vpon searche by the <lb/>
            verdicte of 12: Matrones shee appeared to be Still A Mayde, it <lb/>
            was lawfull that there might be A divorce, and the reason was two  <lb/>
            fold, one that there might be A frigiditie <hi rend="italic">quoad hanc</hi> / another <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            marriage was appointed for p<ex>ro</ex>creation sake, for w<ex>hi</ex>ch cause it <lb/>
            was thought lawfull to sue A divorce /  
         </p>
         <p>
            Vpon this they proceeded to the searche, twelue Matrones <lb/>
            were impannelled, the daye appointed, the searche made, &amp; the verdict <lb/>
            retourned, that shee was A true mayde; Whoe should bring this to <lb/>
            the Eares of the kinge but my Lord of Northampto<ex>n</ex>, and soe to the <lb/>
            world whoe growes iealous of Fraude, doubting eith<ex>e</ex>r corruptio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            or deceipt (for it was vulgarlye reported <ex>tha</ex>t shee had had a child <lb/>
            long before in my Lord<ex>es</ex> absence) wherevpo<ex>n</ex> some saye this, some <lb/>
            saye that, and most that the Countesse was not searched, but <ex>tha</ex>t one <lb/>
            of S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Monsons daughters was brought in to be searched <lb/>
            in her place, and soe both Iurie and Iudges deceaved: But how <lb/>
            true this is, is not Credible. yet neverthelesse they grau<ex>n</ex>t a bill of <lb/>
            divorce; And nowe A sep<ex>ar</ex>ation being had betweene the<ex>m</ex>, the <lb/>
            Earle in A greate disconte<ex>n</ex>t leaves the Courte, and repairs  <lb/>
            to his house in Warwicke sheire neere  <hi rend="italic">
                    <ex>BLANK</ex>
                </hi> and there lives <lb/>
            A Private liffe /     
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The Motio<ex>n</ex> of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  marriage goes for=<lb break="no"/>
                  warde / Ouerburyes <lb/>
                  opinion co<ex>n</ex>cerning it <lb/>
                  he diswads Roch<ex>ester</ex> fro<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
                  it, <ex>th</ex>e breach betweene <lb/>
                  them. <ex>th</ex>e principall caus <lb/>
            		of it /
               </hi>
            </add>
            Nowe might there be A lawfull discourse of marriage, <lb/>
            since there was A lawfull divorce had, yet neverthelesse kept <lb/>
            private and onlye some p<ex>ar</ex>ticuler Freindes made privie / On <lb/>
            Rochesters side. Overburye whose advise he amongst others re=<lb break="no"/>
            quired in this busines, to what end it was vnknowne / Nev<ex>erth</ex>elesse <lb/>
            Overburye was vtterlye against it, and being in serious discou<ex>r</ex>se <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th him, concerning this subiect in the passage Gallerye at w<ex>hi</ex>t <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Hall</fw>
            <pb n="12r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f012r/add_ms_22591_f012r.jpg"/>
            Hall, entred into those or the like wordes as was reported. First how <lb/>
            Much he stood obliged to him for his Cou<ex>n</ex>tenance and Favour and <lb/>
            therefore would speake nothinge but the truthe. Then how dutyfull <lb/>
            and readye he was to p<ex>er</ex>forme all his Com<ex>m</ex>aundes, Fro<ex>m</ex> whence hee <lb/>
            might easelye p<ex>er</ex>ceave, that what he spake was out of affeccion. <lb/>
            And lastlye that he had often endeavoured to avert his mynde <lb/>
            from these thinges, that both tyme and the envye of men might turne <lb/>
            to his pr<ex>e</ex>iudice, taxing him that he had made all this to become <lb/>
            hatefull vnto him, and converting the meanes of good intenc<ex>i</ex>ons <lb/>
            towards him to his disp<ex>ar</ex>agem<ex>en</ex>t and losse: Notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge the <lb/>
            Viscount Still prest him on to passe his opinion, p<ex>ro</ex>testing greate <lb/>
            kindnes and to doe nothing w<ex>i</ex>thout his opinion / wherevpon hee <lb/>
            letts him vnderstand, that p<ex>er</ex>ceivinge the Como<ex>n</ex> reports of the <lb/>
            multitude, and waighing them w<ex>i</ex>th the greatnes of this p<ex>er</ex>sonage, <lb/>
            that he found it to be noe lesse hurtfull to his pr<ex>e</ex>ferrem<ex>en</ex>t, then <lb/>
            helpfull to subvert and overthrowe him. For whoe would (being <lb/>
            possest of soe great possibillities as he was, soe great honors and <lb/>
            large revenewes and daylye in expectac<ex>i</ex>on of others, cast all a=<lb break="no"/>
            waye vpo<ex>n</ex> A woman, that is noted both For her iniurye &amp; imodes=<lb break="no"/>
            tye, and pull vpo<ex>n</ex> him the hatred and contempt of great p<ex>er</ex>sonag<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            for soe small A Matter. Then he willed him to consider with <lb/>
            himselfe the Condic<ex>i</ex>on of the p<ex>er</ex>son whereof he spoke, the manner <lb/>
            of her carriadge fro<ex>m</ex> her youthe, her pr<ex>e</ex>sent Conversation, the <lb/>
            manye envyes dishonors and dislikes that were attendant vppon <lb/>
            her, and besides w<ex>hi</ex>ch is nowe the Com<ex>m</ex>on reporte of <ex>th</ex>e vulgar, <lb/>
            (and he should finde them to be soe) manye evills to attend his sub=<lb break="no"/>
            version and overth<del rend="strikethrough">o</del>rowe. It is not the nature of A wise ma<ex>n</ex> to <lb/>
            make her his wiffe whom he hath made his whore Lastly willed <lb/>
            him to expect noe better requitall at her handes then w<ex>hi</ex>ch she <lb/>
            had shewed her former husband, and withall to waighe the <lb/>
            pr<ex>e</ex>sent Condition that he was in, and to compare it w<ex>i</ex>th the fu=<lb break="no"/>
            ture. Nowe he had but as it were an inclination vnto such a <lb/>
            thinge, neither were those thinges made evident that after <lb/>
            ages would laie open / Neverthelesse <ex>tha</ex>t he was taxed w<ex>i</ex>th in=<lb break="no"/>
            civilitye, levitie, and indeed effeminatenes, that by the opynio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            of the wise he was iudged alltogither vnworthye of <ex>tha</ex>t honor <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            was bestowed vpon him; but when these surmises should come <lb/>
            by this his marriage to be made evident, what evills before were <lb/>
            but suspected, should then nowe be enlarged and laied to his <lb/>
            Charge. Honor is not attended w<ex>i</ex>th voluptuousnes, nor are the <lb/>
            ruyn of A Rotten branche, to be cherrished vpo<ex>n</ex> A newe planted  <lb/>
            tree, but if that he meant to be made famous, and to Continue <lb/>
            that w<ex>i</ex>th him, <ex>tha</ex>t now he freelye enioyed, his opinion was that he <lb/>
            should vtterlye leave and forsake her Companye, and hold her <lb/>
            both hurtfull and hatefull /
         </p>
         <p>
            These speeches drewe on others, and the Viscou<ex>n</ex>te beinge a <lb/>
            litle nettled in his affection, growes something harsh, and Sir
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Thomas</fw>
            <pb n="12v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f012v/add_ms_22591_f012v.jpg"/>
            Thomas having bine heretofore excepted at w<ex>i</ex>th these kinde of Co<ex>n</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            tenc<ex>i</ex>ons, growes soe much the more carelesse, answers word for  <lb/>
            worde, soe that fro<ex>m</ex> faire and Freindlye Speeces, they growe to word<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            of anger, and either to crosse other. In Conclusion, Overburye re=<lb break="no"/>
            quired his p<ex>or</ex>t<ex>i</ex>on dewe vnto him, and soe wills Rochester to leave <lb/>
            him to his owne Fortunes, for that he could not endure these in=<lb break="no"/>
            ordinate Iangles w<ex>hi</ex>ch he had accustomed towards him of late / <lb/>
            and that if there had bine anye thinge saide that was eith<ex>e</ex>r offe<ex>n</ex>sive <lb/>
            to him, to the disp<ex>ar</ex>agem<ex>en</ex>t of the Countesse, it was by his owne <lb/>
            p<ex>ro</ex>curem<ex>en</ex>t, and by reason of the good willand affection that hee <lb/>
            bore to him, w<ex>i</ex>th these and many such other wordes they p<ex>ar</ex>te
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Rochester &amp; the <lb/>
                  countesse meets, they <lb/>
                  conclude the deathe <lb/>
                  of Ouerburye / that <lb/>
                  North<ex>amp</ex>ton had a ha<ex>n</ex>d <lb/>
                  in it / <ex>th</ex>e Causes whye /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">The</hi> Countesse having ere this, borne A deadlye hate to=<lb break="no"/>
            wardes Overburye, because he had often tymes before diswaded <lb/>
            the Viscounte to abstaine fro<ex>m</ex> her Companye / yet nowe havinge <lb/>
            disclosed vnto her this speeche, shee becomes more revengfull, <lb/>
            especiallye because he had taxed her with the name of a Whore, <lb/>
            for truthe is hatefull to the evill, and what before she co<ex>n</ex>cealed, <lb/>
            nowe breaks forthe w<ex>i</ex>th furye, for concealed anger is muche <lb/>
            worse then open violence, perswading Rochester, that it was not <lb/>
            possible, that ever she should endure these iniuryes, or hope for <lb/>
            anye p<ex>ro</ex>speritie as long as he lived, he being the only man that <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thstood his p<ex>u</ex>rposes, w<ex>i</ex>th manye other p<ex>er</ex>swations, that he onlye <lb/>
            of all men begann to growe eminent, and whoe was soe likelye <lb/>
            to be the man to Stepp vpp next after him but Overburye. In=<lb break="no"/>
            soe much as these p<ex>er</ex>swasions, togither w<ex>i</ex>th his owne Conceaved <lb/>
            evill, p<ex>ro</ex>cures the Viscount to give A likeing to her determinatio<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            and to put his hand into the Fire where he needed not, makinge <lb/>
            himselfe accessarye to that w<ex>hi</ex>ch he had noe occasion to put in <lb/>
            practise at all 
         </p>
         <p>
            There were some that charged Northampto<ex>n</ex> to haue had a <lb/>
            hand in these businesses, and to haue vttered these and the like <lb/>
            wordes / That he wondred howe the Viscount could be soe muche <lb/>
            affected to his man Overburye, that w<ex>i</ex>thout him he could doe <lb/>
            nothing; as it were, making him his right hand, seeing he being  <lb/>
            newlye growne into the kings Favor, and whollye dependinge <lb/>
            vpon his greatnes, must expect to come to ruyne, when <ex>tha</ex>t man <lb/>
            rose to pr<ex>e</ex>ferrm<ex>en</ex>t. Allsoe he condemned Overburye for his bold <lb/>
            nes and p<ex>er</ex>emptorye sawcinesse that checkt and corrected the <lb/>
            Viscount for the love that past betwixt the Countisse and him, <lb/>
            and opposed manye of his designes and purposes, wherevpo<ex>n</ex> he <lb/>
            concluded, that vnlesse he did either curbe his greatnes, or abate <lb/>
            his Pride, he in tyme would be equall to him both in power and <lb/>
            Greatnes. Whether this p<ex>ro</ex>ceeded out of feare of himselfe, or <lb/>
            envye towards Overburye, or to colloqve w<ex>i</ex>th his Neece &amp; Roch<ex>ester</ex> <lb/>
            or to p<ex>re</ex>vent the plainenes of S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas whoe altogither dis=<lb break="no"/>
            tasted these iugling courses, it cannot be conceaved, but these  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">are</fw>
            <pb n="13r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f013r/add_ms_22591_f013r.jpg"/>
            are the last woordes that he spake of this subiect / that for his <lb/>
            owne p<ex>ar</ex>te he knewe himselfe to be cleere in all offenc<ex>es</ex> against <lb/>
            the State, and theire Familye was soe eminent in the Como<ex>n</ex>wealth <lb/>
            that he could not hurte him. But for Rochester, being made pr<ex>i</ex>vye <lb/>
            to all his dessignes, growing p<ex>er</ex>emptorye and noe whit tractable <lb/>
            to his disposition, besides, likelye to come to eminencie &amp; honor <lb/>
            in the Como<ex>n</ex> wealthe, he findes it both necessarye and fittinge for <lb/>
            his safetie, that he should be A meanes to dispatch him. Where=<lb break="no"/>
            vpon the Viscount being led by the nose as he thought for <ex>th</ex>e best, <lb/>
            gives consent and endeavors to put in practise <ex>tha</ex>t w<ex>hi</ex>ch hee had <lb/>
            determined. Now of all handes they cast about howe this mighte <lb/>
            be effected and passe vnregarded, soe that they might sustaine no <lb/>
            losse or disparagem<ex>en</ex>t by the attempte /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  S<ex>i</ex>r Willia<ex>m</ex> Wade <lb/>
                  remoued from the <lb/>
                  Liuetenancye of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  Tower, S<ex>i</ex>r Jeruis <lb/>
                  Yeluis præferred /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">For</hi> this purpose alone, it was thought that a quarrell was <lb/>
            picked w<ex>i</ex>th S<ex>i</ex>r Will<ex>i</ex>am Wade, whoe was nowe Leivtenant of the <lb/>
            Tower, and had continued it A greate while, but there were other <lb/>
            cause obiected / As First, he was thought too severe against the <lb/>
            Ladye Arbella, and gave some other Prisoners too much lib<ex>er</ex>tie / <lb/>
            Another was, that he being nowe growne ritche, becan to growe <lb/>
            carelesse, and neglected his office, but the verye truth of the  <lb/>
            businesse was thought to be this / S<ex>i</ex>r Iervis Yelvis beinge A <lb/>
            Lincolnesheire gent<ex>leman</ex>, haueing bene brought vpp a publique life <lb/>
            from his youthe, trayned in the Studie of the lawes in Lincolnes <lb/>
            Inne and ambitious of pr<ex>e</ex>ferrm<ex>en</ex>t, offered A some of monye for <lb/>
            that honor and Place, For howsoever S<ex>i</ex>r Will<ex>i</ex>am Wade might be <lb/>
            one waye taxed for his too much desire of wealthe, w<ex>hi</ex>ch thing might  <lb/>
            be tollerable in him being prest w<ex>i</ex>th A greate charge, yet he was <lb/>
            wise, honest, and discreete in his place, and discharged it w<ex>i</ex>th much <lb/>
            more sufficiencye, then he <ex>tha</ex>t succeeded him, but according to <ex>th</ex>e say=<lb break="no"/>
            inge of the Poett / 
         </p>
         <p>
            <foreign xml:lang="la"> 
            	<hi rend="italic">
            	   Euisquis habet numinos secura nauigat aura <lb/>
            	   Fortunamq<ex>ue</ex> Suo temporet arbitrio <lb/>
            	   Those men that store of monye haue <lb/>
            	   With prosperous wind shall Sayle <lb/>
            	   And Fortune plyes vnto their wishe <lb/>
            	   to speed they cannot faile. / <lb/>
            	</hi>
            </foreign>
         </p>
         <p>
            By this meanes he is gott in to the Leiutenancie, and for <lb/>
            this Cause S<ex>i</ex>r Will<ex>i</ex>am Wade is put <del rend="strikethrough">l</del>out / thinges ordered after <lb/>
            this sorte never p<ex>ro</ex>ceed w<ex>i</ex>thout entrye, vnlesse the p<ex>ar</ex>ties <ex>tha</ex>t inioye such <lb/>
            places be verye considerate, it is likelye they will haue a sudde<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            fall, but what care of men of power of such thinges / He being establi <lb/>
            shed in his office, must (to recollect his monye paid) vse some kind <lb/>
            of extortion, and to beare out this be observant to such as pr<ex>e</ex>ferred  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">him</fw>
            <pb n="13v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f013v/add_ms_22591_f013v.jpg"/>
            him, that soe by theire countenaunce he might vse the greater li=<lb break="no"/>
            bertie: for this Cause, he made the Earle of Northampto<ex>n</ex> &amp; Roch<ex>e</ex>st<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            the whole ende of his Actions, fearing more to displease them then <lb/>
            the kinge A fitt man for theire Purpose 
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">The countisse re=<lb break="no"/>
               payres to M<ex>ist</ex>ris Tur <lb/>
               ner to enquire out a <lb/>
               Man for her, makes <lb/>
               complainte of Ou<ex>er</ex>bury<add place="above">s</add> <lb/>
               insolencye, discloses <lb/>
               her determinations, <lb/>
               Weston is nominated /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">In</hi> the meane time, the Countisse thought it not enoughe to <lb/>
            heare, nor to frett and fume, nor to p<ex>er</ex>swade and intreate my Lord <lb/>
            to vndertake this daungerous enterprise, but to M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner <lb/>
            shee must goe, and there renewe her Complaint<ex>es</ex> with teares (hardly <lb/>
            found in A woman of her disposition) p<ex>ro</ex>testinge that shee never  <lb/>
            was soe defamed, neither did shee ever thinke, that anye mann, <lb/>
            durst haue bene soe sawcie as to call her whore and base woma<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            and that <add place="above">to</add> Rochester her onlye hopes, and w<ex>i</ex>th an impudent face, but <lb/>
            Overburye that Negro, that scum<ex>m</ex>e of men, that divill incarnate, <lb/>
            he might doe anye thinge, and passe ether vnregarded or vnpunishd. <hi rend="italic"> <lb/>
            </hi>This moves pittie in this pittifull woman M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner, whoe frett<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            as fast, to see her Frett, soe that there is such Storming betweene <lb/>
            them, as is incredible: At length, even as wee see two Clowdes aft<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            long Striffe in the Ayre w<ex>hi</ex>ch shall haue prioritie in place, ioyne <lb/>
            in one, Soe these two Women, after they had fullfilled their franticke  <lb/>
            humor, ioyne in this to be the deathe of him, that must be the ende  <lb/>
            (there is noe other mallice to the mallice of A Woman) noe submissio<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            noe intreatie, noe p<ex>er</ex>swation could pr<ex>e</ex>vayle, but he must dye M<ex>ist</ex>ris <lb/>
            Turner soothes her w<ex>i</ex>th (<hi rend="italic">I that she would</hi>) and it is pittye hee <lb/>
            should live to defame soe hono<ex>ra</ex>ble A Ladye, soe well descended, <lb/>
            to the vtter disp<ex>ar</ex>agm<ex>en</ex>t of her house, and that rather then he should <lb/>
            passe w<ex>i</ex>th liffe, shee would be his deathes man her selfe / wordes <lb/>
            of Course in such Cases where people are carryed awaye with <lb/>
            headye mallice, not with reason / yet for all this com<ex>m</ex>ing to theire <lb/>
            right sences, they begin to waighe the matter, and that it was <lb/>
            noe small thing to kill A man, both in respect of Conscience &amp; <lb/>
            lawe / Therefore they cast about w<ex>hi</ex>ch should be the best waye to <lb/>
            doe it, at last they conclude that to poyson him was the onlye way <lb/>
            and that w<ex>i</ex>th least suspect, but then the p<ex>ar</ex>tie that should doe it was <lb/>
            to seeke, for he must be noe ordinarye man, some Apothecarye or <lb/>
            Phisitian that might temper the poyson rightlye to take effecte <lb/>
            according to their mynde / After long Studye one Weston was <lb/>
            named, that had bine sometimes servant to Doc<ex>tor</ex> Turner, &amp; there <lb/>
            by learned such experience, that none was soe fitting to accom=<lb break="no"/>
            plish this exploit to him, This man nowe in the Cou<ex>n</ex>trye must be <lb/>
            sent for, M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner must worke vpo<ex>n</ex> him, to bringe him to this <lb/>
            exploit / For thinges of this nature must be carryed w<ex>i</ex>th wisedome <lb/>
            and discretion, for whoe will hazard his liffe for <hi rend="italic">Hadd I wist</hi>, <lb/>
            Two hundred poundes is p<ex>ro</ex>ferred him, lucre Constraines him, &amp; <lb/>
            he of all men vndertakes it / 
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Ouerburys great <lb/>
            		favor
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">These</hi> thinges notw<ex>i</ex>thstanding, Overburye Stills growes <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">into</fw>
            <pb n="14r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f014r/add_ms_22591_f014r.jpg"/>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  fauour, <ex>th</ex>e motio<ex>n</ex> of <lb/>
                  the Counsell to send <lb/>
                  him Ambassador to <lb/>
                  the Arch Duke, He <lb/>
                  conte<ex>m</ex>plats of it p<ex>er</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
                  swaded by my Lo<ex>rd</ex> <lb/>
                  viscount to refuse <lb/>
                  it / 
               </hi>
            </add>
            into favour, and the Cou<ex>n</ex>cell finding his diligencie &amp; sufficiencie <lb/>
            in his place, nominates him as A man fitt to be sent Ambassador in  <lb/>
            to the lowe Cou<ex>n</ex>tries to <ex>th</ex>e Arch Duke, making that A meanes to <lb/>
            drawe him vpp to greate p<ex>re</ex>ferrem<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>. This comes to Overburyes <lb/>
            Eare, whoe knowing my Lord of Northampto<ex>n</ex> to be his vtt<ex>e</ex>r enemie, <lb/>
            and growinge iealous of Rochester, begins to contemplate w<ex>ha</ex>t <lb/>
            the meaning of this might be; thus betweene hope and feare hee <lb/>
            Standes at A maze / to refuse would be to his greate disgrace, to <lb/>
            vndertake it would be to the losse of his pr<ex>e</ex>ferrem<ex>en</ex>t / Standing <lb/>
            in this doubt, the Viscount after thus manye iangles comes to  <lb/>
            him; and salutes him, and after manye discourses falls into speech <lb/>
            of the intenc<ex>i</ex>on of the Cou<ex>n</ex>cell concerning this Ambassage, not soe <lb/>
            much to assist him, or encourage him to it, as to see howe he Stood <lb/>
            affected. Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> finding him hammering vpo<ex>n</ex> his determin=<lb break="no"/>
            nac<ex>i</ex>ons, not being certainelye determined of anye thinge, ioynes  <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th him, and vtterlye diswades him fro<ex>m</ex> vndertaking it, for (q<ex>uo</ex>th <lb/>
            hee) yor pr<ex>e</ex>ferm<ex>en</ex>t and yor expectac<ex>i</ex>ons lies not amongst forrag<ex>n</ex>e <lb/>
            Nations / you are nowe in Creditt at home, and haue allreadye  <lb/>
            made triall of the dau<ex>n</ex>gers of Travell / whye then should you hazard <lb/>
            all vpon vncertaineties being in possession (as A man mighte <lb/>
            saye) of all that you maye expect, by this meanes allready. These <lb/>
            Speeches, w<ex>ha</ex>t with the trust that he put in the Viscount, what w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            the doubtfullnes of his mynde, doth in A manner confirme his <lb/>
            opinion rather to leave it then to take it, but neverthelesse <lb/>
            gives him to vnderstand, that it was noe small thinge to oppose <lb/>
            the determinac<ex>i</ex>ons of the Cou<ex>n</ex>cell and to contradicte the kings <lb/>
            imploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>: For in either of these, he must expect the displeasure <lb/>
            of both, and be in dau<ex>n</ex>ger to receive condigne punishm<ex>en</ex>t. But <lb/>
            Rochester to gett these doubts out of his mynde, w<ex>i</ex>th great pro=<lb break="no"/>
            stacons and long discourses, letts him vnderstand, that he had <lb/>
            soe much experience of his worthe, and found him soe faithfull <lb/>
            and diligent in his ymploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, <ex>tha</ex>t he could as well misse his <lb/>
            right hand as misse him, and that in case anye such daung<ex>e</ex>r should <lb/>
            happen to him, yet neverthelesse if either his word, his let<ex>ter</ex>, <lb/>
            Creditt or favor could either mitigate, release, or releive him, <lb/>
            it should not be wanting to doe him ease or pleasure: Being led <lb/>
            led on w<ex>i</ex>th these hopes, he is in a manner drawne vtterlye to <lb/>
            denie <ex>tha</ex>t w<ex>hi</ex>ch was intended for his profitt, and to give him a <lb/>
            fitt opp<ex>er</ex>tunitie to execute their mallice towards him as aft<ex>e</ex>r  <lb/>
            happened; thus according to the saying of the Poett <lb/>
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">ne quicqua<ex>m</ex> crede <unclear>hand</unclear> credere quisqua<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
               name fronte politi Astutam vapido seruent sub pectore vulpem</hi>
                </foreign> <lb/>
            <hi rend="bold">
               beleiue thou not scarce any ma<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
               for oft a Phrigian Face <lb/>
               Is smoothlye cou<ex>er</ex>ed w<ex>i</ex>th a smile <lb/>
               but w<ex>i</ex>thin seekes thy disgrace
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            The Viscount seeing him at this time in soe fitt a vaine to be <lb/>
            wrought vpon, and soe easilye to be p<ex>er</ex>swaded from his purpose, <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">doth</fw>
            <pb n="14v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f014v/add_ms_22591_f014v.jpg"/>
            doth shewe him much more Favor then heretofore he had done, <lb/>
            the better to confirme credence in him toward<ex>es</ex> his p<ex>er</ex>swations, <lb/>
            and to encourage him in his determinac<ex>i</ex>ons, that by this meanes <lb/>
            he is vtterlye deceaved, and growes confident to forsake it. In  <lb/>
            this mynde the Viscounte leaves him, &amp; betaks himselfe to his p<ex>u</ex>rpose /   
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The Countisse <lb/>
                  Earle and Viscou<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
                  meete / they deter=<lb break="no"/>
                  mine of the matter, <lb/>
                  the K<ex>ing</ex> is incensed <lb/>
                  against Ouerburye /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Sir</hi> Iervace being nowe growne old in his office, and acquain <lb/>
            ted with it, amongst other thinges is sounded, whether he Stand<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            faithfull toward<ex>es</ex> his two Patrons Northa<ex>m</ex>pto<ex>n</ex> and Rochester, <lb/>
            whereby it is found that he would be plyant to any thing they <lb/>
            desired, but not yet made acquainted with this determination, <lb/>
            Neverthelesse it feeds them with hope to execute theire p<ex>u</ex>rposes, <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th better p<ex>ro</ex>speritie: For the Leiuten<ex>an</ex>t being their Freind, and <lb/>
            Weston (A man <ex>tha</ex>t had gott the arte of poysoning) entertayned <lb/>
            for the purpose, and with A resolute mynde readie to effect <lb/>
            it, made them neither suspect nor doubt anye thinge, onlye how <lb/>
            they might get him to the Tower. For this purpose it was thought <lb/>
            fitt, that Rochester haueing the kings Eare, should be a means <lb/>
            to possesse the kinge w<ex>i</ex>th some misdemenors that he had comitted, <lb/>
            that there by the kinge being incenst against him, and the refusall <lb/>
            of the Ambassage making evident the truthe of these Co<ex>m</ex>plaints, <lb/>
            that they need not doubt of anye such matter. Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> my <lb/>
            Lord of Rochester amongst <add place="above">o</add>ther thinges (at a time convenient) <lb/>
            letts the kinge vnderstand howe insolent Overburye waas grow<ex>n</ex>e, <lb/>
            that he not onlye contemned him, but his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye allsoe, estima=<lb break="no"/>
            tinge this imploym<ex>en</ex>t to be sent Ambassador either too light A <lb/>
            pr<ex>e</ex>ferrm<ex>en</ex>t for his deserts, or els intended to p<ex>ro</ex>cure him some <lb/>
            further evill, and that he vtterlye dislike it, and determined <lb/>
            to refuse it. The king being possest of these thinges, and by him, <lb/>
            whoe to the Iudgm<ex>en</ex>t of the world was his greatest freind, tooke <lb/>
            displeasure at it, soe that by his Cou<ex>n</ex>tenance one might haue <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>ceived his anger. For the frowning of A kinge, is like <ex>th</ex>e roaring <lb/>
            of A Lyon, terrible to the Spectators and hearers, so <ex>tha</ex>t nowe <lb/>
            they doubted not of their expectac<ex>i</ex>ons to gett him into <ex>th</ex>e Tower, <lb/>
            where being as prisoner in the kings disgrace, vnd<ex>e</ex>r the p<ex>ro</ex>tectio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            of one whoe more esteeemed their favor then the kings displea=<lb break="no"/>
            sure, sequestred fro<ex>m</ex> his Freindes, noe intercourse suffered <lb/>
            to come vnto him, but what came fro<ex>m</ex> the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse, Northa<ex>m</ex>to<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            and Rochester, and Weston A fitt agent to execute all man<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            of evills, whie to the Iudgm<ex>en</ex>t of the world it is vnpossible, that <lb/>
            this evill should ever come to light, And thus being cockred vp <lb/>
            in their owne conceipts, they runn headlonge to their owne dist=<lb break="no"/>
            ruction. For when ther were but two p<ex>er</ex>sons pr<ex>i</ex>vye to the Acte <lb/>
            of Murther as in Cayne and Abell, it could not passe vn=<lb break="no"/>
            punished, but <ex>tha</ex>t Cayne must be marked w<ex>i</ex>th a p<ex>er</ex>petuall m<ex>ar</ex>ke <lb/>
            of ignominie; howe much more shall this goe vndiscovered whe<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            there are soe manye pr<ex>i</ex>vye to it. Thus maye wee see, that one 	 <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">sinne</fw>
            <pb n="15r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f015r/add_ms_22591_f015r.jpg"/>
            sinne another doth p<ex>ro</ex>voke, and that murther is as neere to lust <lb/>
            as flame to smoke
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  S<ex>i</ex>r Tho<ex>mas</ex> Refuses <lb/>
                  the Ambassage incu=<lb break="no"/>
                  rrs <ex>th</ex>e K<ex>ing’s</ex> displesure, <lb/>
                  he is sent to <ex>th</ex>e Tower, <lb/>
                  Weston is preferred <lb/>
                  to him, Gressa<ex>m</ex> dies, <lb/>
                  Franckline e<ex>n</ex>tertay=<lb break="no"/>
                  ned into the busines, <lb/>
                  a new Speech of Mar=<lb break="no"/>
                  riage betweene the  <lb/>
                  Countis &amp; Rochester
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Sir</hi> Thomas Overburye and Rochester having (for some <lb/>
            private occasion) fallen into A newe breache at New Markett <lb/>
            retournes verye pensivelye to london; And nowe the time being <lb/>
            come that he should give an answere what he would doe co<ex>n</ex>cerning <lb/>
            this Ambassage, he answered <ex>tha</ex>t he acknowledged himselfe much <lb/>
            bound vnto his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye for manye favors, <ex>tha</ex>t he had bestowed vpo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            him, and amongst the rest, most of all in that it pleased him, as <lb/>
            to pr<ex>e</ex>ferre him to soe greate honor, but yet neverthelesse, know=<lb break="no"/>
            ing himselfe vnworthie of such A Place, vnexperienced how <lb/>
            to execute it, and besides tied to manye domesticke busynesses, <lb/>
            desired to be excused. This seeming something strang and harsh, <lb/>
            that he should refuse his owne good, and by these meanes incurr <lb/>
            the displeasure of the kinge, and loose his expectac<ex>i</ex>ons, makes <lb/>
            some of his Freindes to wonder, others to Stand in a maze But <lb/>
            in Conclusion as he had iustlye deserved by reason of his co<ex>n</ex>te<ex>m</ex>pt <lb/>
            he is Comitted to the Tower, but not to be kept as a close Pri=<lb break="no"/>
            soner; but after my Lord of Northa<ex>m</ex>pto<ex>n</ex> and Rochester beinge <lb/>
            both of the privye Cou<ex>n</ex>cell and in great favor at Courte, sendes <lb/>
            vnto the Liveten<ex>a</ex>nt, that he should keepe him close pr<ex>i</ex>soner, and <lb/>
            afterwards received by word of mouthe fro<ex>m</ex> S<ex>i</ex>r Tho<ex>mas</ex> Mounson, <lb/>
            that he should not suffer any lett<ex>e</ex>rs, tokens, or other thinges <lb/>
            to be delivered vnto him 
         </p>
         <p>
            Theire expectac<ex>i</ex>on in this thinge being accomplished, M<ex>ist</ex>ris <lb/>
            Turner by the instigac<ex>i</ex>on of the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse, becomes A greate <lb/>
            Sutor to S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Mou<ex>n</ex>son, to haue his letter to pr<ex>e</ex>fer Westo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            vnto S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas, to waite on him in the Tower, whoe hearing <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            name of the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse, and withall vnderstanding of the greate <lb/>
            affection that was betweene her and Rochester, condiscended, wrote, <lb/>
            and sent him w<ex>i</ex>th this letter to S<ex>i</ex>r Iervis in the Tower, he shewed <lb/>
            it to S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas / S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas willing to deserue his pr<ex>e</ex>tious cheifs <lb/>
            favor with the more readines entertayned him, as when A man <lb/>
            ignorantlye treads vpo<ex>n</ex> A serpent, is stunge for his labor, soe <lb/>
            S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas harbors in his owne brest, <ex>th</ex>e author of his owne distruccio<ex>n</ex>   /
         </p>
         <p>
            Nowe Gresham growing into yeares haueing spent muche <lb/>
            time and manye fowle prayers to accomplish these things, at <lb/>
            this time gethers all his bables togither, vizt Pictures in lead, <lb/>
            in Waxe, in plats of Gold of naked men and women, w<ex>i</ex>th Crosses <lb/>
            Crucifixes, and other ymplem<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, wrapping them all vp togither <lb/>
            in A Starke crossed everye letter in the Sacred worde <hi rend="italic">Trinitie</hi> <lb/>
            crossed <unclear>ɑ.<del rend="strikethrough">u</del> ԝ.o:</unclear>  crossed, these beinge verye holilye delivered into <lb/>
            the handes of one Westo<ex>n</ex> to be hidd in the Earthe that noe man <lb/>
            might finde them / and soe in Thames Streete finished  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">his</fw>
            <pb n="15v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f015v/add_ms_22591_f015v.jpg"/>
            his evill times, he dyed leaving behinde him A man and A mayd, <lb/>
            one hanged for A witche the other for A Theefe / 
         </p>
         <p>
            After his death w<ex>i</ex>th much writtinge, manie entreaties and <lb/>
            rewardes, One Francklyn A Yorke sheire man was entertained <lb/>
            into these actions, A man of A reasonable Stature, crookshoul=<lb break="no"/>
            dred, of A swarthie Complection, and thought to be noe lesse A <lb/>
            Witche then the two former Gresham and forman / this man was <lb/>
            more ymployed to make poysons fitt to be administred by Westo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            then otherwise, for he was excellent in that Arte, to mitigate or <lb/>
            increase their Strength, soe that sometimes A Poyson should be <lb/>
            A Monthe ere it <del rend="strikethrough">sh</del>
                <add place="above">w</add>ould worke / verilye, evill actions shall nev<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            want evill actors, and in all Ages Phisitians, Apothecaries, drug <lb/>
            gests, Cashiered serving men that haue fallen into want, haue <lb/>
            still bine the Agents in such enterprises. Tyberius his Phisitia<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            Spade an Apothecarie, and Higdo Drusus servant, are made A=<lb break="no"/>
            gentes to be his poysoners. Nerowes bond men must kill him, <lb/>
            Pisees Captaine vnder Germanicus, must poyson him, and by <lb/>
            the helpe of A woman posoner of Coo a towne in Gretua whoe <lb/>
            was soe skillfull <ex>tha</ex>t shee hid poyson in his hayre to kill himselfe, <lb/>
            A Centurion to Maximus must poyson him. Alexand<ex>e</ex>rs phisitia<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            Anti Pater and Aristotle must be the author of his deathe / and  <lb/>
            heere Franklyn A kinde of Phisitian, Westo<ex>n</ex> A servant to Sir <lb/>
            Thomas, and S<ex>i</ex>r Iervis Yelvis, whoe is as you shall hereafter <lb/>
            heare, Privado to the Earle and Viscount and the Countesse, <lb/>
            and M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner are made instrum<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> to kill and dispatch S<ex>i</ex>r <lb/>
            Thomas Overburye / Soe that it hath bene allmost in all Ages, <lb/>
            and in all such outrages founde that ether such p<ex>er</ex>sons or wome<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            haue bene Actors in such attemptes / 
         </p>
         <p>
            Overburye being thus confyned into the Towre, &amp; acco<ex>m</ex>pted  <lb/>
            amongst them as A Fryer, A dead p<ex>er</ex>son in lawe, in whose brest <lb/>
            manye secretts were Contayned, being Still fedd on w<ex>i</ex>th hope <lb/>
            of pr<ex>e</ex>ferrem<ex>en</ex>t and libertie, least he should disclose w<ex>ha</ex>t he knew / <lb/>
            they at theire will and pleasure carrouse full healthes of  <lb/>
            sinne and abominac<ex>i</ex>on, and freelye discourse of A marriage to <lb/>
            be consumated betweene the<del rend="strikethrough">m</del> Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse and Rochester, that soe <lb/>
            being tyed in this bond of Matrimonye, and ioyned in affinitie <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th my Lord of Northa<ex>m</ex>pto<ex>n</ex>, more trust might be had in him, <lb/>
            and better vse be made of his honor and greatnes. Nowe there <lb/>
            is noe man to support him, noe man to diswade him, his loosnes <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse gaules his Conscience / and <ex>tha</ex>t it might be <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            more offensive to him, and make him willinger to co<ex>n</ex>sent <lb/>
            to this motion, he is Still prest with it, and <ex>tha</ex>t it is both vnfitt <lb/>
            and vnseemelye, whereas on the other syde if they marrie, it <lb/>
            will be both lawfull, honorable, and Comendable, &amp; the Eares <lb/>
            of the Vulgar will be then stopt, and none dares to be soe <lb/>
            bould as to touch him w<ex>i</ex>th it. This carries shewe of truthe, <lb/>
            soe that w<ex>ha</ex>t with his former affection, what w<ex>i</ex>th his present <lb/>
            offence <ex>tha</ex>t he conceives at theise courses, concludes <ex>th</ex>e marriag  / <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">tymes</fw>
            <pb n="16r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f016r/add_ms_22591_f016r.jpg"/>
            times are appointed to Conferr how impedim<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> mighte bee <lb/>
            avoyded, and what should be fitting for to be done in this behalfe  /     
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  How <ex>th</ex>e Lieutena<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
                  came acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
                  this busines, incou<ex>r</ex>aged <lb/>
                  to persist by Northto<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
                  rewards promised <lb/>
                  him, he examines S<ex>i</ex>r <lb/>
                  Thomas to finde out <lb/>
                  his affectio<ex>n</ex> most <lb/>
                  thinke of Religion, <lb/>
                  Some thinke towards <lb/>
                  the Countesse
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">It</hi> is nowe highe time to enter into this Action, and <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            tisse meanes to be the First, and for this purpose shee went &amp; gott <lb/>
            A Glasse of blewe water some two inches longe, this being wraped <lb/>
            in a pap<ex>er</ex>, shee deliversto Westons sonne w<ex>i</ex>th Instructions, <ex>tha</ex>t he <lb/>
            should goe to the Tower and deliver it to his Father. Hee doth soe, <lb/>
            whoe having his matter A forehand put in his head, at supp<ex>er</ex> time <lb/>
            takes the glasse in one hand, and whoe should he meete w<ex>i</ex>thall as he <lb/>
            was goinge, but S<ex>i</ex>r Gervis Yelvis the Leivten<ex>a</ex>nt, soe demaundes <lb/>
            he of him w<ex>i</ex>th a kinde of Caution whether he should give it him <lb/>
            nowe, the Leivten<ex>a</ex>nt Stopt and asked him what, to w<ex>hi</ex>ch Weston <lb/>
            answered, S<ex>i</ex>r knowe you not what is to be done, this made him <lb/>
            Stand in A Mase and doubt the worst, wherevpon he calls Westo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            into examinac<ex>i</ex>on, and makes him confesse all his intenc<ex>i</ex>on, fro<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            what Groundes, of whom he receaved it, and p<ex>ar</ex>tlye the cause of it, <lb/>
            He nowe being made A Slave vnto Greatenesse, and having laide <lb/>
            out much monye to p<ex>u</ex>rchase his place, for feare to loose the one, &amp; <lb/>
            to offend the other, letts Weston goe w<ex>i</ex>th this Caution to omitt it <lb/>
            for that time<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>, Whereas A wise man (rather then he would haue  <lb/>
            runne himselfe headlonge into p<ex>er</ex>dicion) would haue discovered <lb/>
            it, and haue made them A meanes to haue manifested his faith <lb/>
            fullnes and deligence in his office. But what shall we saye to <lb/>
            A man lost, the next daye he is sent for to the Lord of North<ex>amp</ex>ton, <lb/>
            there after manye longe and large discourses, at lengthe the <lb/>
            Earle discloses to him his intenc<ex>i</ex>on concerning Overburye, and <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th those thinges mingles manye of his insolencies. First of his <lb/>
            obstanacie against the Viscount, his insolencie against <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>t<ex>ess</ex> <lb/>
            his opposition against al<del rend="strikethrough">l</del> most all good men; and <ex>tha</ex>t for these <lb/>
            Causes if such A thinge happened, there being none to looke <lb/>
            after him, it would passe vnregarded or respected. But with <lb/>
            all giveds him manye Cautions howe he should manage himself <lb/>
            in this buisynes, letting him vnderstand, what manner of man <lb/>
            he was / A Scholler, and one that had an excellent tounge and  <lb/>
            witte / A travellor, experienced in the Course of the world / &amp; <lb/>
            besides that favoured of the Contrarye Faction, and as great a <lb/>
            politician as anye was this daye in England. Therefore in this <lb/>
            regarde, he ought to be soe much the more warye, both whoe came <lb/>
            to him and whoe went from him, and aboue all, that noe letters <lb/>
            past too and fro These and manye other cuch like speec<add place="above">ch</add>es having <lb/>
            past betweene them (for the Earle was two howres by his owne <lb/>
            Confession in prompting him w<ex>i</ex>th Cautions and Considerations, <lb/>
            that he might be the readyer to acte his parte in this adve<ex>n</ex>ture <lb/>
            he was to deale in) Lastlye he concludes <ex>tha</ex>t aboue all, hee  <lb/>
            should insinuate w<ex>i</ex>th him to see how he stood affected to theise <lb/>
            proceedings and what wordes he vttered, For a hart full
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">thrust</fw>
            <pb n="16v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f016v/add_ms_22591_f016v.jpg"/>
            thrust w<ex>i</ex>th greiffe and sorrowe must either speake or burste, <lb/>
            and his secrecie and deligence herein shall be rewarded w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            A thousand poundes / Whether it was <ex>th</ex>e greedines of <ex>th</ex>e reward, <lb/>
            or the foolish desire he had to give content vnto the Earle and <lb/>
            Viscounte, they being his onlye favorors, or some other hope tis <lb/>
            vnknowne, but he by this meanes is brought on to his owne dis=<lb break="no"/>
            truction, and soe gives consent to conceale that w<ex>hi</ex>ch was inte<ex>n</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            ded. At his Coming backe he repaires to S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Ou<ex>er</ex>bury <lb/>
            vnder pr<ex>e</ex>tence to comforte him in his sorrowe, and advises him <lb/>
            to be more lightsome, and not to consume himselfe in greiffe / <lb/>
            by this meanes entring into further discourse, secretly insynuats <lb/>
            into his intenc<ex>i</ex>ons S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas haueing A good opynion of him, <lb/>
            and supposing that all was done out of Faithe and honestie to=<lb break="no"/>
            wards him, having by this meanes learnt what he could out <lb/>
            of him, writes vnto my Lord of North<ex>amp</ex>ton a l<ex>ett</ex>re to this effect /
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="bold">
               My especiall good Lord, hauing vndertooke my prisoner accord=<lb break="no"/>
            	inge to yo<ex>u</ex>r Instructions after long silence as standinge betweene <lb/>
            	hope and feare, he takes his Bible, and p<del rend="strikethrough">rotests</del> after he had <lb/>
            	read vpon it, he takes it and by it p<ex>ro</ex>tested his in<ex>n</ex>ocencie. Aft<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            	vpon further conference concerning the Countesse he said, that <lb/>
            	(he had iustified her allreadye, and <ex>tha</ex>t he could doe noe more <lb/>
            	then he had done; but for himselfe, alas quoth he what will  <lb/>
            	they doe with mee; I answered, soe reason you, as you shall <lb/>
            	make noe question hereafter of your purenesse, and I lefte <lb/>
            	him in some sence to worke vpon him. As I was goinge he con=<lb break="no"/>
            	cluded, that in the generallitie she was soe worthie <ex>tha</ex>t she <lb/>
            	might be a wife for anye man, but not to saye that she was <lb/>
            	a wife in perticular for my Lord of Rochester, he woulde <lb/>
            	not saye it least my Lord should co<ex>n</ex>dempne him for waighinge <lb/>
            	his worthe. At my next coming to him, I found him not in <lb/>
            	sence but furie, he lett flye at you, but was respective of <lb/>
            	my Lord of Rochester, whose part he taketh altogither, I <lb/>
            	see the event, I desire it maye be safelye Covered. What <lb/>
            	my service maye doe you in this or anye thinge else, I will <lb/>
            	be faithfull to your Lordshipp, and soe I rest	Yo<ex>u</ex>rs
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="align-right">
            <hi rend="italic">Jeruice Yeluis  /</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            This and manye other thinges being inserted into this l<ex>ett</ex>re, <lb/>
            was sent vnto the Earle, w<ex>hi</ex>ch he read, and in reading laughes <lb/>
            and smiles, at the simplicitye of the one and ignorance of <ex>th</ex>e oth<ex>e</ex>r / <lb/>
            Neverthelesse in outward apparance he applauds all <ex>th</ex>e actio<ex>n</ex>s <lb/>
            of S<ex>i</ex>r Iervice, but espetiallye to my Lord of Rochester, holding <lb/>
            him both A discreet and A wise man, and that his service and <lb/>
            honest dealing in this imployment, deserves everlastinge <lb/>
            prayses w<ex>i</ex>th after ages /
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">
                    <hi rend="bold">Weston</hi>
                </fw>
         </p>
         <pb n="17r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f017r/add_ms_22591_f017r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  More Poysons are <lb/>
                  sent fro<ex>m</ex> the Cou<ex>n</ex>tes, <lb/>
                  S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Mounson <lb/>
                  is Suspected to haue  <lb/>
                  a hand in this bu=<lb break="no"/>
                  sinesse. Ouerburye  <lb/>
                  growes Sicklie, iea=<lb break="no"/>
                  lous of his dyet, noe <lb/>
                  accesse is suffered <lb/>
                  to him /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Weston</hi> having receaved foure score poundes of his allow=<lb break="no"/>
            ance, and yet neverthelesse nothing accomplished according to <lb/>
            the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesses expectac<ex>i</ex>on, is checkt by <unclear>M<ex>istre</ex>ss</unclear>
                <hi rend="italic"> </hi>Turner for delay=<lb break="no"/>
            inge it, Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> he getts into his handes certaine poysons, <lb/>
            vidzt Roscetre, white Arsinicke, Mercurye sublimate, Can=<lb break="no"/>
            tharides, red mercurye, w<ex>i</ex>th three or foure more severall poy=<lb break="no"/>
            sons, tempering them with his brothe, and his meates, according <lb/>
            as he sawe them affected increasing and deminishinge <ex>the</ex>ir Strength <lb/>
            as he was instructed by his auntient Freinde Mr Francklyn / Be=<lb break="no"/>
            sides these Tarts and Iellyes are sent by the Viscount &amp; Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse, <lb/>
            to S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Monsons and from thence by the handes of one Symo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            master servant vnto S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas, to be delivered to Weston, and soe <lb/>
            to overburye, Everye of w<ex>hi</ex>ch tarts and Iellyes were poysoned w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            A severall poyson. These course<del rend="strikethrough">th</del>
                <add place="above">s</add> causes S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Monson to be <lb/>
            suspected of this acte, and to haue a hande in it: First in respect <lb/>
            he pr<ex>e</ex>ferred Weston to this service / Secondlye because poysoned <lb/>
            Tartes and Iellyes went out of his house / And lastlye, for that <lb/>
            he did not discover these thinges, his men onlye having accesse vnto <lb/>
            the Tower and that to speake with Weston. Nowe his Salte, his <lb/>
            Sawce his meate, his drincke, and whatsoever he eates, is mi<ex>n</ex>gled <lb/>
            with poyson, and for the increase of the torment, is either incre=<lb break="no"/>
            ased or deminished, as he sawe S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Overburye affected  /
         </p>
         <p>
            By this meanes he begins to growe extreame sickelye hav=<lb break="no"/>
            ing bine heretofore accustomed to very good healthe, in soe <lb/>
            muche as he can scarce Stand or goe, what w<ex>i</ex>th the paine of his <lb/>
            bodye and the heate / yet neverthelesse being A Strong man he <lb/>
            Stood it out A longe time, till at length he began to growe <lb/>
            iealous of his man Weston, for his Maladye increased or di=<lb break="no"/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">
                    <unclear>miprise</unclear>
                </del> minished as he affected / but yet some Phicksicke he desired, <lb/>
            and at his speciall instance and request, and not w<ex>i</ex>thout some gr<ex>ea</ex>t <lb/>
            gratuitie as was thought, One Paule de-la-bell, an Apothecarie <lb/>
            by the advice of Docter Mervine, brought A Bathe to coole his <lb/>
            bodye, w<ex>i</ex>th advise to be spare of his Dyett for that he suspected <lb/>
            his meate was not wholesome / surelye this did him much good, &amp; <lb/>
            p<ex>re</ex>served his liffe longer then they expected, in soe muche as <lb/>
            they doubted some fallacie or fraude, and therefore sent newe <lb/>
            l<ex>ett</ex>res to the Leivten<ex>a</ex>nt to haue A spetiall Care that none might be <lb/>
            suffered to see him, or speake with him, for evill men are full of <lb/>
            needlesse Feares, and nowe there is such spetiall watch had over  <lb/>
            him, that none of his men might be p<ex>er</ex>mitted soe much libertie as <lb/>
            to speake with him out at A windowe, and the reason being asked, <lb/>
            answere was made that the Leuieten<ex>a</ex>nt had Comaundem<ex>en</ex>t fro<ex>m</ex> the <lb/>
            Cou<ex>n</ex>sell that it should bee soe /
         </p>
         <p>
            Thus this good Gent<ex>leman</ex> passeth awaye his tedious and sorrowfull <lb/>
            dayes, w<ex>i</ex>th manye discontents being filled w<ex>i</ex>th paines and greifs, <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout Freindes or Comfortors, readye to be vexed &amp; torme<ex>n</ex>ted <lb/>
            vpon everye newe occasion, and consuminge and languishing away <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">w<ex>i</ex>thout</fw>
            <pb n="17v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f017v/add_ms_22591_f017v.jpg"/>
            without anye como<ex>n</ex> societie, that was allowed to the meaneste <lb/>
            Prisoner in the house. In this man maye wee see <ex>th</ex>e miserye <lb/>
            of such as fall into the handes of popish Catholicks, for by <lb/>
            Northa<ex>m</ex>tons meanes, was this Strictnes shewed towardes him. <lb/>
            Heere will wee leave him languishing in sorrowe, &amp; lame<ex>n</ex>ting <lb/>
            his misfortune 
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The marriage be=<lb break="no"/>
                 tweene <ex>th</ex>e viscount  <lb/>
                 &amp; <ex>th</ex>e Count<ex>ess</ex> published <lb/>
                 questioned whether <lb/>
                 it maye be lawfull, <lb/>
                 a nullitie obtayned <lb/>
                 to the intent to make <lb/>
                 it lawfull, My Lord <lb/>
                 of Essex repayes her <lb/>
                 portion, the Viscou<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
                 made E<ex>arl</ex> of Somersett
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Tyme</hi> can noe longer conceale these secrett meetings, but <lb/>
            it must come to the light / the marriage betweene the Viscount &amp; <lb/>
            the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse is published / this is Strange to the world, &amp; so much <lb/>
            the more Strange, by how much three such great &amp; eminent p<ex>er</ex>sons <lb/>
            as the Earle of Essex, the Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse, and the Viscount, were in=<lb break="no"/>
            teressed in it; And nowe according to the Como<ex>n</ex> course, every one <lb/>
            speakes as they Stand affected, some boldlye, some sparingly, some <lb/>
            calls her A loose Woman and pitties the good Earle of Essex, &amp; <lb/>
            saye that he had sustayned soe much wronge, then eu<ex>er</ex> any English <lb/>
            Peere had done: First to suffer disgrace by the Prince, nowe by <lb/>
            his wiffe / others blame her, and give wordes harsh &amp; vnsee<ex>m</ex>lye / <lb/>
            A third sorte, Rochester, and that it is pittye but that she should <lb/>
            proue as badd A wiffe to him, as ever shee did to the Earle of <lb/>
            Essex / Then if Overburye had bine at libertie this had never <lb/>
            happened. Others that were more Staid and iuditious in <ex>the</ex>ir opinio<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            foresawe the ruyne and downefall of Rochester by this meanes <lb/>
            but noe durst <space/> for whoe will put his finger into <ex>th</ex>e fire <lb/>
            vnlesse he be compelled / Neverthelesse to stoppe the Mouthe  <lb/>
            of the Vulgar, this marriage is called into questio<ex>n</ex>, whether <lb/>
            it maye be lawfull or not, because her husband was livinge / <lb/>
            For this Cause the Bishopps of this Land were devided: by the <lb/>
            opynion of some shee might, by the opynio<ex>n</ex> of others she mighte <lb/>
            not. My Lord of Canterburye London  and manye others, were <lb/>
            vtterlye against it / But Winchester and Elye stood stiffelye it <lb/>
            might, p<ex>ro</ex>vided that A nullitie mighte be had, for by <ex>tha</ex>t meanes <lb/>
            the former marriage should be vtterlye determined. A nullity <lb/>
            was obtayned, and vpon the graunt of that it was ordered, <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            my Lord of Essex should repaye her portion, <ex>tha</ex>t he receaved <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th her at her Marriage, that soe to the shewe of the world, it  <lb/>
            might be said, there had bine noe marriage betweene the<ex>m</ex>; This <lb/>
            afterwards was called into question, and thought a meere tricke  <lb/>
            of North<ex>amp</ex>ton to disparage some of the greatest of o<ex>u</ex>r Clergie, <lb/>
            and to discou<ex>n</ex>tenance our religion, it left a fowle Scarre, and <lb/>
            gave occasion to the adversarye to speake broadlye, where they <lb/>
            had free libertie, &amp; of some even in our kingdome      
         </p>
         <p>
            This Order being sent to my Lord of Essex, he forthw<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            pr<ex>e</ex>pares for the paym<ex>en</ex>t of five thousand poundes (for soe much <lb/>
            he had receaved w<ex>i</ex>th her) and for this purpose he sold and feld  <lb/>
            divers woodes at Adderstone, and neere there abouts / His  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Grand</fw>
            <pb n="18r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f018r/add_ms_22591_f018r.jpg"/>
            Grand mother the Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse of Leicester helpt him much, or els <lb/>
            he should haue bine constrayned to sell much land to haue paide <lb/>
            it / Verelye A harde course having sustayned soe manye iniuries /
         </p>
         <p>
            The king neverthelesse continwes his Favor towardes Rochest<ex>e</ex>r, <lb/>
            and that he might be as eminent as the best / he is installed Earle <lb/>
            of Somersett, thus favors are heaped vpo<ex>n</ex> him though hee little <lb/>
            deserued them; And the Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse hath what shee desireth, that is <lb/>
            Still to be a Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse, but called after another name, <ex>tha</ex>t is Cou<ex>n</ex>t<ex>ess</ex> <lb/>
            of Somersett. Manye are the Changes that happen in this world, <lb/>
            some good, some badd, and those thinges we least suspect doth soonest <lb/>
            happen to subvert vs / At this tyme my Lord of Somersett little <lb/>
            thought to haue bine laide in the Tower, and made heire of Ou<ex>er</ex>bury <lb/>
            bedchamber, but by this wee maye see, that all thinges are in <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            handes of God /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The Marriage <lb/>
                  comes to S<ex>i</ex>r Tho<ex>mas</ex>Ou<ex>erbury’s</ex> <lb/>
                  eares, he prophiseth <lb/>
                  his owne death, he <lb/>
                  falleth to A Relapse, <lb/>
                  he writs to the Ear<ex>l</ex> <lb/>
                  to Remember his <lb/>
                  promise, Answere <lb/>
                  was Sent him with <lb/>
                  w<ex>ha</ex>t Mercurye insteed <lb/>
                  of a medicinable  <lb/>
                  Powder: his death, <lb/>
                  <ex>th</ex>e State of his body  <lb/>
                  after his death, <ex>th</ex>e  <lb/>
                  rumour <ex>tha</ex>t is Spred <lb/>
                  of him, the Authors <lb/>
                  lamentation. /
               </hi>
            </add>
            Nowe allthoughe S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Overburye was kept pr<ex>i</ex>vate, <lb/>
            and that noe man might haue accesse to him, yet the newes of this <lb/>
            marryage comes to his Eares, and pr<ex>e</ex>sentlye vpo<ex>n</ex> hearing of it he <lb/>
            tells the messinger, that he had allmost as good haue saide, to <lb/>
            morrowe he should dye, for he was sure nowe not to live long, and <lb/>
            therevpo<ex>n</ex> falls into greate Lamentations, aswell in respect of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Earle of Som<ex>er</ex>sett <ex>tha</ex>t he had soe cast awaye his Fortunes, as of <lb/>
            himselfe, for that nowe he more suspected his liffe then hereto=<lb break="no"/>
            fore, Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> he falls into A relapse, and his maladye en=<lb break="no"/>
            creaseth more and more vpo<ex>n</ex> him / whether weakned w<ex>i</ex>th greife <lb/>
            or for wante of libertie, or through abstinence it is not knowne, <lb/>
            but the Poyson hath nowe more power over him then eu<ex>er</ex> heretofore, <lb/>
            in soe much that he could Scarce contayne himselfe, by reaso<ex>n</ex> of <lb/>
            his extreame languishing awaye, as A man in A Co<ex>n</ex>sumption, <lb/>
            but w<ex>i</ex>th much more extremitye / Soe that nowe being in this extre=<lb break="no"/>
            mitie, he tthinkes it highe time to put Somersett in mynde of his <lb/>
            p<ex>ro</ex>mise, and for this p<ex>u</ex>rpose he writts A letter to this effecte
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Ouerburyes l<ex>ett</ex>re <lb/>
                  to the Earle /
               </hi>
            </add>   
            Right <del rend="strikethrough">ho</del> noble and worthie Sir, your former accoustomed <lb/>
            favours, and absolute promise concerning my present de=<lb break="no"/>
            liuerance, hath caused mee at this time by these lines to <lb/>
            sollicite your Lo<ex>rdshi</ex>pp and to put you in reme<ex>m</ex>brance of <ex>th</ex>e same <lb/>
            not doubting <ex>tha</ex>t yo<ex>u</ex>r honor is at all forgettfull of me, but only <lb/>
            (by reason of my imprisonem<ex>en</ex>t) being possest of a dau<ex>n</ex>gerous <lb/>
            desease, would for my bodyes safetye, p<ex>ar</ex>take of <ex>th</ex>e filicitie <lb/>
            of the opeen ayre; In which Case if yo<ex>u</ex>r Lordshippe please to <lb/>
            Comiserate my p<ex>re</ex>sent necessities, and procure mee my <lb/>
            speedye deliuerance, I shall not onlye stand soe muche <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            more obliged, but allsoe acknowledge you the defendor &amp; <lb/>
            preserver of my liffe
         </p>
         <p>
            These lines (being subscribed) were sent to Somersett, &amp; deliu<ex>er</ex>d <lb/>
            into his own handes, the messinger retournes answere, <ex>tha</ex>t pr<ex>e</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            sentlye he could not accomplish what he required, but willed <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">him</fw>
            <pb n="18v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f018v/add_ms_22591_f018v.jpg"/>
            him not to doubt, for shortlye he should heare of his deliverance <lb/>
            Thus being fedd w<ex>i</ex>th hope, he tooke newe comforte to him, in the <lb/>
            meane time Weston repaires to M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner for more of his <lb/>
            paie being nowe in want, answere was made that soe soone as he <lb/>
            hadd ended his imploym<ex>en</ex>t, he should not faile to receave it, but <lb/>
            before then he must not expecte anye thinge. Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> he retur<ex>n</ex>s  <lb/>
            and enters vpon newe designes, for in all this time, that is from  <lb/>
            the 21: of Aprill vntill the begin<ex>n</ex>ing of September following in  <lb/>
            the yeare 1613: S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas had held out. While he was thus pus=<lb break="no"/>
            ling himselfe to <unclear>
                    <del rend="strikethrough">l</del>
                </unclear> bringe this to perfectio<ex>n</ex> Somersett sent him A <lb/>
            letter to this Effect. That as yet the Courte was busye about ym <lb/>
            portant businesses, and the kings Eare was not at leasure to <lb/>
            entertaine anie motion, but as soone as he could find opp<ex>or</ex>tunitie, <lb/>
            he would not faile to speake in his behalfe. In the meane time <lb/>
            to ease the paine of his maladie, he had sent him A soveraigne <lb/>
            powder either to be eaten, or drunke, w<ex>hi</ex>ch powder was rancke <lb/>
            poyson / This feedes him Still w<ex>i</ex>th hopes, but brings him small <lb/>
            Comforte / Nowe Weston had found out an vnknowne Apothec<ex>ary</ex> <lb/>
            and w<ex>i</ex>th him concludes for twentie poundes to administer A <lb/>
            Glister, wherein should be put in Mercurye Sublimate, the <lb/>
            youthe was wone to doe it, Weston pr<ex>e</ex>pares it, p<ex>er</ex>swades Sir <lb/>
            Thomas that wilbe much for his healthe; Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> about the <lb/>
            14: daye of Sept<ex>ember</ex>, he bringes the said Apothecarye to execute <lb/>
            his office, assists him therein, and by the infusion thereof, hee <lb/>
            falls into A languishing disease with A paine in his Gutts, the <lb/>
            next daye after w<ex>i</ex>th extremitie of paine he gave vpp <ex>th</ex>e Ghost /
         </p>
         <p>
            After his death, Weston receives the rest of his paie, and <lb/>
            dispatches the vnknowne Apothec<ex>ary</ex> into France / After it was  <lb/>
            given out that S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas lived A loose liffe in the Towre, &amp; <lb/>
            not according to that Strictnes, that became A Prisoner but <lb/>
            being suffered to haue too much libertie, he runn into <ex>th</ex>e excesse <lb/>
            of laciviousnes, soe that there by hee gott the Poxe, and thereof <lb/>
            dyed. This went for Currant amongst some, amongst others <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            were ignorant, some litle respect had to it, but to others that <lb/>
            sought narrower into the matter, they found it farr oth<ex>e</ex>rwise, <lb/>
            For <hi rend="italic">De-la-Bell</hi> the Apothecarye before spoken of, havinge  <lb/>
            relation to him A little before his deathe, reported he was <lb/>
            changed in his Complection, his bodye Consumed awaye, and  <lb/>
            full of yellowe blisters vglye to looke vpo<ex>n</ex> And it appeared <lb/>
            by A letter that my Lord of North<ex>amp</ex>ton wrote to Rochester <lb/>
            to picke A thanke, that there was found in his Arme a blister, <lb/>
            an vop<ex>n</ex> his bellye 12 kernells raised, not like to breake, ech <lb/>
            as broade as three pence, as bigg as A small butto<ex>n</ex>, one yssue <lb/>
            vpo<ex>n</ex> his backe wherevpo<ex>n</ex> was A Plaster fro<ex>m</ex> his shoulders <lb/>
            downewards of A darke Tawnye collor, strang and Vglye <lb/>
            to behold, he stuncke soe intollerable <del rend="strikethrough">
                    <unclear/>
                </del> not to be borne with <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">and</fw>
            <pb n="19r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f019r/add_ms_22591_f019r.jpg"/>
            all, gladd to be throwne into A loose sheete into his Coffine, buryed <lb/>
            without knowledge or privitie of his Freindes vpo<ex>n</ex> the Tower hill / At <lb/>
            last he concludes <ex>tha</ex>t God is Gratious in cutting of ill Instrum<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> before <lb/>
            theire tyme. Some of the factious Crewe had A purpose, if he had <lb/>
            gott out, to haue made some vse of him, from whence maye be ga=<lb break="no"/>
            thered, howe that Northampto<ex>n</ex>, held Protestants factious, &amp; suspe=<lb break="no"/>
            cted S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas to haue further knowledge of his Secretts then he <lb/>
            would haue had him, w<ex>hi</ex>ch was the Cause as was thought, besides <ex>th</ex>e  <lb/>
            former evills, <ex>tha</ex>t hastned his ende, and caused him to be taxed w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            soe greate infamie as to dye of the Poxe. This passeth Currant &amp; <lb/>
            the mischeiffe lyes concealed, whoe dares to speake of it, two suche <lb/>
            greate men having theire handes in it /
         </p>
         <p>
            Thus maye wee see, that as well good as bad men come to misera=<lb break="no"/>
            ble endes, and oftentimes those that are vertuous doe soonest suffer <lb/>
            disgrace and Contempt. This man before he came to Courte was <lb/>
            brought vpp in all gent<ex>leman</ex> like quallities / In his youth at Cambridge <lb/>
            after in the mydle Temple there instructed in those quallities be=<lb break="no"/>
            came A Gent<ex>le</ex>man. by the intreatie of my Lord Treasuror S<ex>i</ex>r Rob<ex>er</ex>t <lb/>
            Civill pr<ex>e</ex>ferred to Courte, found Favor extraordynarie / yet hin=<lb break="no"/>
            dered in his expectac<ex>i</ex>ons by some of his Enemies, and to shifte <lb/>
            of discontents forced to <del rend="strikethrough">mur</del> Travell, therein spent not his tyme <lb/>
            as most doe to losse, but furnishing himselfe w<ex>i</ex>th thinges fittinge <lb/>
            A Statesman by experience in forrainge governm<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, knowledge <lb/>
            of the Language, passages of imploym<ex>en</ex>t, externall Cou<ex>r</ex>tshippe <lb/>
            and good behaviour, thinges not comon to everye man. Notw<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            standinge such as are the imp<ex>er</ex>fections of our tymes, he is broughte <lb/>
            into ignominie and Contempt / and all those good quallities obsc <lb/>
            cured by the disgracefull reproaches of A dissolute Woman; what <lb/>
            shall we then saye, since both vice and vertue doe both end w<ex>i</ex>th misery <lb/>
            he is most happie that liveth most private, for accordinge to the <lb/>
            saying of the <hi rend="italic">Poet</hi> /
         </p>
         <cb/>
         <p>
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
               <hi rend="bold">
                  Vitam animas operam Sumptus impedim<ex>us</ex> aula <lb/>
            		Præmia pro meritis quæ retributa putas <lb/>
            		Aula dedit nobis reseripta votata papyro <lb/>
            		Et sine mente Sonos et Sine corde manus <lb/>
            		Paucos beauit, aula plures perdidit <lb/>
                  Sed et hoc quoq<ex>ue</ex> ipso quos beauit perdidit <lb/>
               </hi>
            </foreign>
         </p>
         <cb/>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">
               Our Lusts, our Soules our wealth wee Spend <lb/>
            	In court to purchase praise <lb/>
               But what Reward is in the Ende <lb/>
            	For our desarts t’as repaide <lb/>
               There vowes and protestations deepe <lb/>
            	Not prest in pap<ex>er</ex> but in winde <lb/>
               <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">There</fw>
               <pb n="19v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f019v/add_ms_22591_f019v.jpg"/>
               There Sounds of wordes to lull’s a Sleepe <lb/>
               from bodye forct, not from the mynde <lb/>
               Hands there wee ioyne but not our harts <lb/>
               whereby it happineth fewe are blest <lb/>
               But manye thousand that resorts <lb/>
               vnto the Courte by it are lost <lb/>
               And of those fewe that blessed are <lb/>
               wee often see theire fall againe <lb/>
               Their blessed dayes are Speent in care, <lb/>
               And after end their lives in paine /
            </hi>
            To conclude amongst Courtiers, Enmitie is holden for p<ex>er</ex>fect <lb/>
            Amitie, and those Freindes whom most wee trust, doe soonest seke <lb/>
            to subvert and overthrowe vs, as appeareth even in this exa<ex>m</ex>ple <lb/>
            before our Eyes
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The co<ex>m</ex>plaint for <lb/>
                  want of Treasure, <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  K<ex>ing</ex> Setts many Lands <lb/>
                  to fee farme, <ex>th</ex>e death <lb/>
                  of my Lo<ex>rd</ex> Harrington, <lb/>
                  <ex>th</ex>e death of his Sonne /
               </hi> 
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">Greate </hi>som<ex>m</ex>es of monye being disbursed vppo<ex>n</ex> her graces <lb/>
            weddinge, and dayly ymploym<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> for others, some for Ireland / The <lb/>
            Treasuror wanting there to defraie ordinarye expences, some for <lb/>
            Complainte for want of Treasure;  Officers of Courte goe vnpaid, <lb/>
            and manye of the kings Servants rec<ex>eive</ex> not their wages at sett tymes, <lb/>
            soe that the kinge is forced to sett manye of his Lands to Fee Farme, <lb/>
            and the Fower deputed Treasurors w<ex>i</ex>th some fewe others haue <ex>th</ex>e pas=<lb break="no"/>
            singe of them. Nowe my Lord Harrington obtayned A Patent for <lb/>
            the making of brasse Farthings, A thinge that brought w<ex>i</ex>th it some <lb/>
            Contempt though lawfull, for all things lawfull are not expe=<lb break="no"/>
            dient, whoe being enioyned to goe into the lowe Cou<ex>n</ex>tryes w<ex>i</ex>th her <lb/>
            Grace, by the waye lost his liffe / His Sonne succeeded both in his <lb/>
            honor and Patent, but enioyed them not long, for hee dyed w<ex>i</ex>thin <lb/>
            A short time after, the hopefullest Gent<ex>le</ex>man of that name, more <lb/>
            fitt for ymploym<ex>en</ex>t then for A pr<ex>i</ex>vate liffe, and for A Statsma<ex>n</ex> the<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            for A Souldier / he had bine at Cambridge, there reputed for a <lb/>
            greate Scholler; he travelled into Italie, Venice and France / he <lb/>
            ymployed his time for the most p<ex>ar</ex>te in Studdie, whereby he made <lb/>
            himselfe apt for great matters. But yet it pleased God even  <lb/>
            then when he was in his greatest hope, to cutt of his dayes, he <lb/>
            gave all he had to the Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse of Bedfford his Sister, defeating <lb/>
            her neither of the Land nor the right of the Baronie, estima=<lb break="no"/>
            ting her to be worthie of much more then he had to leave / hee  <lb/>
            made A worthie and godlye end. These thinges com<ex>m</ex>ing soe thicke <lb/>
            one after another, left not time for <del rend="strikethrough">dr</del> men to dreame of Ou<ex>er</ex>bury<add place="above">s</add> death 
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">
                    <hi rend="bold">A</hi>
                </fw>
            <pb n="20r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f020r/add_ms_22591_f020r.jpg"/>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The E<ex>arl</ex> of Som<ex>er</ex>sett <lb/>
                  his conscience ac=<lb break="no"/>
                  cuseth him. North<ex>amp</ex>to<ex>n</ex>s <lb/>
                  Speech to him, hee <lb/>
                  becometh a Newter <lb/>
                  in Religion, the E<ex>arl</ex> <lb/>
                  of North<ex>amp</ex>tons course
               </hi>
            </add>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">A</hi> nullitie being thus purchased, he dignified as is saide, and <lb/>
            the Matche concluded about Candlemasse <hi rend="underline">1614</hi> they marrie w<ex>i</ex>th much <lb/>
            Ioye and solempnitie / A maske being p<ex>er</ex>formed at Som<ex>er</ex>setts charge, <lb/>
            and manye rumors passe w<ex>i</ex>thout anye respecte / all these things not <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thstandinge / A guiltie Conscience can never goe without accusac<ex>i</ex>on, <lb/>
            pensivenesse and Sullen<ex>n</ex>esse doe possesse the Earle, his wonted mirth <lb/>
            forsakes him, his Cou<ex>n</ex>tenance is cast downe, he takes not <ex>tha</ex>t feli=<lb break="no"/>
            citie in Companye as he was wonte to doe, but still something tro=<lb break="no"/>
            bles him. Verelye it is A daungerous thinge to fall with in the <lb/>
            Compasse of A guiltie Conscience, it eateth and consumeth the <lb/>
            Soule of A man as rust doth Iron, or as beating waves hollowes <lb/>
            the Rockes, and though those things are not made publique, yet neu<ex>er</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            thelesse North<ex>amp</ex>ton observed it in him / And having soe admirable <lb/>
            A Capacitye, he could make vse of all thinges, wherefore know=<lb break="no"/>
            ing his disease vizt, his mynde seared w<ex>i</ex>th murther, and knowinge <lb/>
            the Earle tractable as he desired, enters into more familiar <lb/>
            discourse w<ex>i</ex>th him, for when the mynde of A young man is Cor=<lb break="no"/>
            rupted w<ex>i</ex>th evill, he runns headlong into Sinne w<ex>i</ex>thout Staie or <lb/>
            Feare / wherefore amongst manye other discourses, this falls be=<lb break="no"/>
            tweene them / That in Case the deathe of S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Overburye <lb/>
            should come to light, they were then in A most dau<ex>n</ex>gerous State, &amp; <lb/>
            the next thinge they must expect is losse of liffe, Goods, Landes, <lb/>
            honors, their names to be made Scandalous to the world, and to <lb/>
            conclude to be branded w<ex>i</ex>th an ignominious deathe, neith<ex>e</ex>r that <lb/>
            there was anye waye left them for to escape this, but either by <lb/>
            making theire owne fortunes soe greate that they might oppose all <lb/>
            accusations, or els being Catholiques, to endeavor that in defen=<lb break="no"/>
            dinge them, they againe might assist their Cause, in case <ex>tha</ex>t anye <lb/>
            matter came against them / This carrying some shewe &amp; liky=<lb break="no"/>
            hood of truth, and <ex>tha</ex>t indeed his Case was desp<ex>er</ex>ate if it should <lb/>
            ever come to light, concludes to combine w<ex>i</ex>th North<ex>amp</ex>ton in w<ex>ha</ex>t <lb/>
            soever he should vndertake / And in Conclusion became A <lb/>
            Newter in Religion; wherevpo<ex>n</ex> to the intent that he might sett <lb/>
            further evills A Foote beside those before reme<ex>m</ex>bred, he begins <lb/>
            to rubb vpp the au<ex>n</ex>tient quarrell betweene the welche &amp; English <lb/>
            whoe nowe murmur at some discontents. And to the intent to <lb/>
            harten on the Irishe, sends letters thither, by the hands of one <lb/>
            Ham<ex>m</ex>on A poore man, vnto such whom he knowes to be faithfull, <lb/>
            in the Romish Religion, and thereby confirmes them in their opynio<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
            assuring them that God will Still p<ex>ro</ex>vide one or moe to p<ex>ro</ex>tect his  <lb/>
            Church, and that nowe the greatest favorite of England would <lb/>
            Stand for them / Vpo<ex>n</ex> w<ex>hi</ex>ch lett<ex>e</ex>r, the Irish growes obstinate as I <lb/>
            haue said, and alltogither neglect the Service of God, &amp; vtterlye <lb/>
            denye the Oathe of Supr<ex>e</ex>macie, p<ex>ro</ex>testing lose of liffe and Goodes, <lb/>
            rather then to be enforced to soe damnable A thinge. Now maye <lb/>
            wee see there the Churches vtterlye forsaken, none to heare
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">devine</fw>
            <pb n="20v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f020v/add_ms_22591_f020v.jpg"/>
            devine service, the discipline of their owne Church established, <lb/>
            and the Irish in generall, expecting a daye to haue their libertie <lb/>
            and freedome in religion. The same man retourning this newes, <lb/>
            is after sent in Yorkesheire w<ex>i</ex>th a black Staffe, and A knopp vpo<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            the ende, w<ex>i</ex>thin w<ex>hi</ex>ch knopp letters were conveyed fro<ex>m</ex> place to place, <lb/>
            aswell for appointing assemblies, as meetings for masse, &amp; enter=<lb break="no"/>
            tayning of Preists. Nowe might A man goe to masse in manye <lb/>
            plac<ex>es</ex> of the Cittie, and whoe were soe much publiquelye favoured <lb/>
            as Papists, their nu<ex>m</ex>ber increase, their Preists are entertayned, <lb/>
            Confession in manye parts publiquelye practised, and allthough <lb/>
            it were contrarye to the lawes, yet greatnesse overcou<ex>n</ex>tenau<ex>n</ex>cing <lb/>
            them it was little regarded. In the meane time quarrells wente <lb/>
            forward betweene the Scottish and English, Continuall Co<ex>m</ex>plaint<ex>es</ex>, <lb/>
            and the suite of the Cloath workers w<ex>i</ex>th hope of obtayning theire <lb/>
            request, not soe much because of the Profitt, as to raise vpp A <lb/>
            discontent betweene the Dutch and them / Theise Cou<ex>r</ex>ses caused <lb/>
            divers men to passe divers opinions, and manye men to passe <ex>the</ex>ir <lb/>
            opynion as they affected either p<ex>ar</ex>ties /
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The Rumor of the <lb/>
                  Spanish fleete. A Pro <lb/>
                  clamatio<ex>n</ex> ag<ex>ain</ex>st Spanish <lb/>
                  monye / A Leaguer in <lb/>
                  the Lowe Countryes, <lb/>
                  <ex>th</ex>e publique rumour <lb/>
                  against my Lord of <lb/>
                  Northa<ex>m</ex>pton, he ex=<lb break="no"/>
                  hibits A bill in the <lb/>
                  Starr chamber ag<ex>ains</ex>t <lb/>
                  the publishers, they <lb/>
                  iustifie mt Lo<ex>rd</ex> of Cant<ex>erbury’s</ex> <lb/>
                  speech / the death of <lb/>
                  my Lord of Northa<ex>m</ex>p<ex>ton</ex> <lb/>
                  his funerall, his will <lb/>
                  the names of those <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
                  Succeeded him in his offices /
               </hi>
            </add>
            Not long after it was rumored abroade, <ex>tha</ex>t the Spaniard had <lb/>
            drawne out A Navye of Shipps of an hundred Sayle, but to <lb/>
            w<ex>ha</ex>t purpose noe man knewe, manye suspected for Eng<ex>land</ex>, because <lb/>
            they were come soe farr vpo<ex>n</ex> these Coasts / others said for <ex>th</ex>e vse <lb/>
            of their Marriners to accustome them to the Sea / but most of all <lb/>
            were of opynion that these were but shaddowes, and <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e full <lb/>
            intenc<ex>i</ex>on of <ex>th</ex>e Spaniard was to haue taken advantage of <ex>th</ex>e tyme, <lb/>
            Howsoever vpo<ex>n</ex> this there followed A Proclamatio<ex>n</ex> agst Spanishe <lb/>
            monye, that their monye should not goe currant in England, w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            Caused manye to suspect worse then the worst; and some saide one <lb/>
            thinge, some another. Vpo<ex>n</ex> <ex>th</ex>e necke of <ex>thi</ex>s comes newes of warrs, <lb/>
            in the lowe cou<ex>n</ex>tryes, some said against <ex>th</ex>e Palsgrave, some against  <lb/>
            the States; the Scotts begine to flye out into rebellion, &amp; are sup=<lb break="no"/>
            prest: <ex>th</ex>e wildernesse in Ireland begins to Stirr, sometimes 30: <lb/>
            sometimes 40:, sometimes three hundred flye out and Stand vpon <lb/>
            theire Guard. These things administer occasions of wonder to <ex>th</ex>e ig=<lb break="no"/>
            norant, and manye of them whoe knewe <ex>th</ex>e truthe of things, knewe <lb/>
            not what to saye to it. Presists come into the kingdome by Tenns <lb/>
            fifteenes and twenties at A tyme, and haue free accesse, soe <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            my Lord of North<ex>amp</ex>ton (being warden of the Cinque Port<ex>es</ex>) begins <lb/>
            to be called into question. Some saye he hath A hand in these bu=<lb break="no"/>
            synesses, others saye he letts Preists haue his free accesse, &amp; that <lb/>
            in Blomesburye amongst his owne buildings they haue free harbor, <lb/>
            Others saye that through his Cou<ex>n</ex>tenance thither any man might <lb/>
            goe to his p<del rend="strikethrough">r<ex>i</ex>vate</del>
                <add place="above">ublicke</add> masse, besides manye other Intelligences <lb/>
            being brought fro<ex>m</ex> beyond seas, drawes him further into suspition, <lb/>
            and the kinge begins to w<ex>i</ex>thdrawe his favor fro<ex>m</ex> him. wherefore <lb/>
            he exhibits his bill against such as defamed him into <ex>th</ex>e Starr
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Cha<ex>m</ex>ber</fw>
            <pb n="21r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f021r/add_ms_22591_f021r.jpg"/>
            chamber, some are for this cause com<ex>m</ex>itted to the Tower, others to <lb/>
            Newgate, others to the Fleete, till they come to their Answere / And <lb/>
            in the end openlye in the Starr chamber, he is accused for sufferinge <lb/>
            Preists to haue free accesse into Yorkesheire vnder pr<ex>e</ex>tence of his <lb/>
            office, for cou<ex>n</ex>tenau<ex>n</ex>cing them, for sending letters too and againe to en=<lb break="no"/>
            courage men in theire opinions, and manye other such like things And <lb/>
            when the Lordes should come to passe theire voyces, my Lord of <lb/>
            Canterburye amongst the rest made A speeche to this effect. That <lb/>
            allthough manye had bine the rumors &amp; reports <ex>tha</ex>t had passed in these <lb/>
            tymes, some of them husht vpp for vncertaine truthes and flyinge <lb/>
            Fables, then entertyaned for approved truthes, yet neverthelesse <lb/>
            such thinges as are grownded vpo<ex>n</ex> reason, and for w<ex>hi</ex>ch men of vpright <lb/>
            Conscience haue some occasion to speake, to have such either lightly <lb/>
            valued or punished, was rather iniustice then anye way beseeminge <lb/>
            the Equitie of that Courte / But in truthe these whereof wee nowe <lb/>
            speake are grounded vpo<ex>n</ex> some Cause, and my Lords owne Letters <lb/>
            make evident, <ex>tha</ex>t he hath done some thinges both against his owne con=<lb break="no"/>
            science and meaninge, meerelye to attaine vnto honor &amp; Sou<ex>er</ex>aignetie, <lb/>
            and to please the kinge. And w<ex>i</ex>th <ex>tha</ex>t he pulls out A letter written <lb/>
            fro<ex>m</ex> my Lord to Cardynall Bellarmine to this effecte / That howsoe=<lb break="no"/>
            ever the Conditions of the tymes Compelled him, and his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty vrged <lb/>
            him to turne Protestant / yet neverthelesse his harte Stood w<ex>i</ex>th the <lb/>
            Papists, and that he would be readye to further them in any atte<ex>m</ex>pte <lb/>
            This and much more being read to some such purpose, he p<ex>ro</ex>ceeded <lb/>
            and shewed, howe that these thinges were not meerelye vncertaine, <lb/>
            but even the accions that followed did iustifie them to be true / for <lb/>
            there were never knowne to be soe many Preists to come ov<ex>e</ex>r into <lb/>
            this kingdome in soe short a time, as of late there had done / neither <lb/>
            could he assu<add place="above">r</add>e himselfe, that my Lord was true harted vnto the <lb/>
            State, since allsoe he harboured such about him as would vnd<ex>e</ex>rtake <lb/>
            to write in defence of the Gunpowder Treason  This and much more <lb/>
            being saide about the latter end of Easter terme 1614 my Lord being <lb/>
            hereat much dis<del rend="strikethrough">pleased</del>couraged after the Courte brake, tooke his <lb/>
            Barge, went to Greenewitch there made his will, wherein hee <lb/>
            published himselfe to dye in the same Faithe he was baptised, made <lb/>
            some of his Freindes executors, others he bestowed guiftes vpon, <lb/>
            his fayre house he bestowed to my Lord Chamberlayne, his Lands <lb/>
            to my Lord Theophilus Howard, retired backe to his house at <lb/>
            London, and before Mydsomer  Tear<ex>m</ex>e following was dead  Manye <lb/>
            were the rumors <ex>tha</ex>t were raised of this man after his deathe, <lb/>
            that he was A Traytor to the State, and <ex>tha</ex>t he was not dead but <lb/>
            carryed beyond Sea to blinde the world; and the reason was, because <lb/>
            he would be buryed at Dover and not at London. Others saye, <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            if he had lived he would haue bene the Author of much Stirre, <lb/>
            manye disliked him, and as was reported, even the kinge him=<lb break="no"/>
            selfe nowe toward<ex>es</ex> his latter end, w<ex>hi</ex>ch made him fall into these <lb/>
            Courses; but truelye he was A Notable Polititian, and carryed
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">things</fw>
            <pb n="21r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f021r/add_ms_22591_f021r.jpg"/>
            thinges more comodiouslye for the Papists then ever any before  <lb/>
            him. His Funerall was kept privatelye at Rochester where hee <lb/>
            desired to be buryed, because it was the Cheiffe Porte Towne of his <lb/>
            Office, w<ex>i</ex>thout anye State to outward appearance. My Lord Treasuror <lb/>
            that nowe is succeeded in the Treasurorshippe, my Lord of Somersett <lb/>
            made Lord Chamberlaine and Chancellor of Cambridge. my Lorde <lb/>
            Zouche Warden of the Cinque-Ports, My Lord of Wocester some <lb/>
            shorte time after, privye Seale / Theise succeeded him in his offices
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  The cloathwork<ex>e</ex>rs <lb/>
                  obtayne their Petitio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
                  the old Charter of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  Marchants aduentu=<lb break="no"/>
                  rers is Seized into <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  kings hand; <ex>th</ex>e Dutche <lb/>
                  growe discontented <lb/>
                  at it, <ex>th</ex>e doubtfullnes <lb/>
                  of Somersetts mynde / <lb/>
                  he Sues for his pardo<ex>n</ex>, <lb/>
                  obtaine it, My Lo<ex>rd</ex> Canc<ex>ellor</ex> <lb/>
                  refuse to Seale it fals <lb/>
                  into Suspition, begins <lb/>
                  to be neglected /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">The</hi> Clothworkers Still p<ex>er</ex>sisting in their Suite, and having two <lb/>
            such Strong Freindes to Stand for them, and Alderman Cocken a rich <lb/>
            Marchant to backe them, they at length obtaine what they desire, &amp; <lb/>
            Proclamatio<ex>n</ex> goes forthe that noe whit Cloathes shalbe carryed ou<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            vndyed or <add place="above">vn</add>drest / And for this purpose the old Charter of <ex>th</ex>e M<ex>er</ex>cha<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
            Adventurers is seized into the kinges hands, soe that <ex>tha</ex>t co<ex>m</ex>pany falls <lb/>
            to decaye. Nowe the Dutche men, they begine to murmur against <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            English, and make Proclamation there, that noe man shall buye anye <lb/>
            such Cloathes aas come soe over drest and dyed; Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> <ex>th</ex>e English <lb/>
            make A newe Proclamatio<ex>n</ex>, that noe man shall transporte Wooll <lb/>
            out of the kingdome: these thinges feed some with hope of some fu<ex>r</ex>th<ex>e</ex>r  <lb/>
            troubles; yet neverthelesse it is soe ordered by the Cou<ex>n</ex>cell, that <lb/>
            all these thinges are pacifyed, and some qua<ex>n</ex>titie amou<ex>n</ex>ting to a c<ex>er</ex>taine <lb/>
            number of white Cloathes are suffered to be transported aswell <lb/>
            to giue content to the Hollander, as satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on and imploym<ex>en</ex>t to some <lb/>
            yonge Marchants <ex>tha</ex>t had entred to this trade, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes these <lb/>
            Clamors are A litle Staid; yet neverthelesse great impressio<ex>n</ex> of <lb/>
            envye is betweene these two Companies /   
         </p>
         <p>
            Nowe one of the greatest Freindes that Som<ex>er</ex>sett had being dead, <lb/>
            and himselfe Still iealous of his safetie, he begins to cast aboute <lb/>
            howe he might avoyde the dau<ex>n</ex>ger of the lawe, for his Intelligencers <lb/>
            gave him notice of manye desp<ex>er</ex>ate wordes that were vttered con=<lb break="no"/>
            cerning Overburyes deathe / wherevpo<ex>n</ex> finding the kinge in A good <lb/>
            humor, hee moves him to this effect: That whereas it had pleased <lb/>
            his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tye, to Comitt manye things into his Charge, and some of them <lb/>
            provinge somethinge too waightie for him to vndergoe, it was soe <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            ignorantlye he runn himselfe into A premanire, whereby he had <lb/>
            forfeited to him both his Lands, his Goods and his libertie, and that <lb/>
            nowe he came to surrender them all vpp into his ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ies</ex> hand, vnles <lb/>
            it pleased him of his wonted favor towards him, to graunt him p<ex>ar</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            don for that and manye other offences that he had ignorantlye co<ex>m</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            mitted; the kinge Still bearing A good affection towards him, bad him <lb/>
            drawe his p<ex>ar</ex>don, and he would signe it: Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> he makes his re=<lb break="no"/>
            paire to S<ex>i</ex>r Rob<ex>er</ex>t Cotten, and intreats him to looke him A Pardon <lb/>
            the largest he could finde in Former pr<ex>e</ex>sidents, soe hee brings him <lb/>
            One that was made by the Pope to Cardynall Woolsey, Theffect <lb/>
            of w<ex>hi</ex>ch was, That the kinge of his meere motion &amp; speciall favor <lb/>
            did p<ex>ar</ex>don all and all mannor of Treasons, misprisions of treasons, <lb/>
            murders fellonies and outrages whatsoever by the Said S<ex>i</ex>r Rob<ex>er</ex>t
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Carr</fw>
            <pb n="22r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f022r/add_ms_22591_f022r.jpg"/>
            Carr E<ex>arl</ex> of Somersett comitted or hereafter to be comitted, w<ex>i</ex>th <del rend="strikethrough">ma <lb/>
            </del>manye other words to make it more ample &amp; large, according to forme, <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch he caused to be drawne and ingrossed &amp; brought it to the King; The <lb/>
            king he signed it: At length it comes to my Lord Cha<ex>n</ex>cellors hand, hee <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>vses it and refuses to lett it passe the Seale / My Lord asks <ex>th</ex>e reason <lb/>
            answere was made, <ex>tha</ex>t he could not iustifie <ex>th</ex>e doing of it, but <ex>tha</ex>t he should <lb/>
            incure A pr<ex>e</ex>munire as well as himselfe. This Stroke Som<ex>er</ex>sett to the hart <lb/>
            &amp; nowe he was in greater doubt, then ever he was before, for Still he is <lb/>
            Stunge with Feare to be touched w<ex>i</ex>th Overburyes deathe, and soe verye <lb/>
            pensivelye retires to w<ex>hi</ex>thall, and there remaines /
         </p>
         <p>
            The kinge coming to Londo<ex>n</ex>, My Lord Chau<ex>n</ex>cellor acquainted him w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            <ex>th</ex>e Pardon, and shewed his ma<ex>jes</ex>ty what dau<ex>n</ex>ger he had incurred, in case he <lb/>
            had sealed it. The King p<ex>er</ex>ceiving the truthe of the busines, suspected some <lb/>
            greater matter then he knewe of, withdrawes his Cou<ex>n</ex>tenance fro<ex>m</ex> Som<ex>erset</ex> <lb/>
            whoe nowe wanting vertue to support his greatnes w<ex>i</ex>thout <ex>th</ex>e Kings favor, <lb/>
            falls into <ex>th</ex>e co<ex>n</ex>tempt of manye, &amp; those <ex>tha</ex>t are his Enemies neglect him, <lb/>
            and doe as it were deride his manner of Carriage, by w<ex>hi</ex>ch meanes he <lb/>
            runnes headlong into his owne p<ex>er</ex>ditio<ex>n</ex> as shalbe hereafter shewed
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  My Lo<ex>rd</ex> Canc<ex>ellor</ex> Sued <lb/>
                  in <ex>th</ex>e Starr-cha<ex>m</ex>ber <lb/>
                  for being within <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
                  Compasse of a præ=<lb break="no"/>
                  munire, <ex>th</ex>e K<ex>ing</ex> goes to <lb/>
                  cambridge, a breach  <lb/>
                  about ignoramus, my  <lb/>
                  Lord Coke Stand ag<ex>ains</ex>t <lb/>
                  my Lo<ex>rd</ex> Canc<ex>ellor</ex>. The K<ex>ing</ex> <lb/>
                  graces S<ex>i</ex>r G: Villars <lb/>
                  bestowes gr<ex>ea</ex>t honors <lb/>
                  on him, Som<ex>er</ex>sett<ex>es</ex> cou<ex>r</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
                  ses to co<ex>n</ex>ceale Ou<ex>er</ex>b<ex>ury’s</ex> <lb/>
                  death, his Couetuous <lb/>
                  nes, his insolencie, <lb/>
                  he is crost by Villers <lb/>
                  the report of the <lb/>
                  Vulgar / 
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">In</hi> <ex>th</ex>e yeere 1614 <ex>th</ex>e Kinge by <ex>th</ex>e intreatie of Som<ex>er</ex>sett determines to <lb/>
            goe to Cambridge, &amp; there was entertayned w<ex>i</ex>th great Solemnitie; But <lb/>
            amongst the rest there was A Plaie called by <ex>th</ex>e name of Ignoramus, <lb/>
            <ex>tha</ex>t Stirred vp A great co<ex>n</ex>tentio<ex>n</ex> betweene <ex>th</ex>e como<ex>n</ex> Lawyers &amp; <ex>th</ex>e Schollers, <lb/>
            in soe much as their flowtes grewe vnsufferable, but at last it was Staid <lb/>
            by my Lord Cha<ex>n</ex>cellor and the explayning of the meaninge /
         </p>
         <p>
            About this time it happened, <ex>tha</ex>t divers Citizens having recovered cer=<lb break="no"/>
            taine som<ex>m</ex>es of monye in the Kings benche, &amp; thereof having had iudgm<ex>en</ex>t, the <lb/>
            p<ex>ar</ex>tie def<ex>endan</ex>t neu<ex>er</ex>
                <ex>th</ex>elesse exhibitts his bill in Chancerye to haue releiffe , <ex>th</ex>e  <lb/>
            pl<ex>ain</ex>t<ex>iff</ex> <lb/>
            at <ex>th</ex>e Como<ex>n</ex> lawe having alreadie had Iudgm<ex>en</ex>t for <ex>th</ex>e same matter, there  <lb/>
            Sta<ex>n</ex>ds <lb/>
            out and disobaies the kings p<ex>ro</ex>ces, Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> A write of conte<ex>m</ex>pt issues <lb/>
            against him; they are taken comitted to <ex>th</ex>e Fleete, and there continewe in  <lb/>
            their obstinacye / Neverthelesse not long after, vpo<ex>n</ex> some advise they ex=<lb break="no"/>
            hibite their bill into the Starrcha<ex>m</ex>ber against my Lord, intending <ex>tha</ex>t he <lb/>
            ought not to <add place="above">inter</add>feddle w<ex>i</ex>th any matter <ex>tha</ex>t was allreadye determined at <lb/>
            the Como<ex>n</ex> lawe, and whereof A Iudgment had bine passed, and this was <lb/>
            ordeyned by the Statute in <ex>th</ex>e 4; H<ex>enry</ex> 4: Cap: 23: Whereby it was ena=<lb break="no"/>
            acted, that Iudgm<ex>en</ex>t given in the Kings Courte shall not be examined <lb/>
            in the Chancerye Parlyam<ex>en</ex>t or elswhere, vntill it be done by attaint <lb/>
            or error &amp;c. Nowe my Lord hauing laied them fast vpo<ex>n</ex> A Bill <lb/>
            exhibited before him, &amp; Iudgm<ex>en</ex>t allreadye being given, <ex>tha</ex>t therefore <lb/>
            my Lord had incurred A pr<ex>e</ex>munire, and humblie prayed releiffe in  <lb/>
            this Casse. Manye were the Opynions of Lawyers concerninge this <lb/>
            matter, some Stood on my Lord Chau<ex>n</ex>cellors syde, some said that <ex>th</ex>e poore <lb/>
            men had iniurye, &amp; <ex>tha</ex>t they might iustifie w<ex>ha</ex>t they had done, &amp; amongst  <lb/>
            manye my Lord Cooke Stood out Stifelye , <ex>tha</ex>t my Lord Chau<ex>n</ex>cellour <lb/>
            could not iustifie that Action; And thus it stands Still in question, <lb/>
            whether my lord be in A Premunire, yea or noe /
         </p>
         <p>
            My Lord of Somersett Still continuing his loose cou<ex>r</ex>ses, &amp; vtterlye <lb/>
            neglecting that Severitie that ought to be in A man in his Place, be=<lb break="no"/>
            sides the former suspitions and Iealousies, gives occasion of others <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">allsoe</fw>
            <pb n="22v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f022v/add_ms_22591_f022v.jpg"/>
            allsoe, whereby <ex>th</ex>e kinge doth more &amp; more fall into dislike. There being <lb/>
            at this time A young Gent<ex>le</ex>man about the Courte, <ex>tha</ex>t not long before had <lb/>
            arrived fro<ex>m</ex> travells out of Fraunce, his name was Villiers a Lec<ex>e</ex>ster <lb/>
            sheire Gent<ex>le</ex>man, &amp; of an au<ex>n</ex>tient house, whoe as well in respect of his <lb/>
            Carriage as of his Cou<ex>n</ex>tenance was more remarkable the<ex>n</ex> many <lb/>
            others / On this man the kinge casts a p<ex>ar</ex>ticuler affection, holding him to <lb/>
            be the onlye p<ex>ro</ex>perist and best deserving Gent<ex>le</ex>man of England / where  <lb/>
            vpon he entertaines him into favor, bestowes 1000 li vpo<ex>n</ex> him, after <lb/>
            adornes him w<ex>i</ex>th the Title of Knighthood, and nowe he begins to grow <lb/>
            everye daye more eminent then other, greater honors are bestowed <lb/>
            vpon him, as <ex>th</ex>e dignities to be knight of the Garter, and M<ex>aste</ex>r of <ex>th</ex>e horse, <lb/>
            places not como<ex>n</ex> to everye p<ex>er</ex>son, &amp; soe much the more remarkable  <lb/>
            because they are bestowed vpo<ex>n</ex> him being soe yonge in yeares / his <lb/>
            wisedome is comended of the wisest, and his expectac<ex>i</ex>ons greater then <lb/>
            manye that went before him.   
         </p>
         <p>
            This Stings Som<ex>er</ex>sett to the harte, to see another Stepp to his place, <lb/>
            and the more feares his subverc<ex>i</ex>on and downefall. Wherefore hee <lb/>
            goes about to circu<ex>m</ex>vent dau<ex>n</ex>gers, and for this purpose send<ex>es</ex> into Fr<ex>ance</ex> <lb/>
            to make awaye <ex>th</ex>e Apothecarye <ex>tha</ex>t administred <ex>th</ex>e Phisicke <ex>tha</ex>t killed <lb/>
            S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas; Endeavored to gett in all letters and writtings <ex>tha</ex>t had past <lb/>
            concerning that busynes, and disgracing and discou<ex>n</ex>tenau<ex>n</ex>cing all such <lb/>
            as at anie time once Spake of the death of Overburye, to the intent <lb/>
            it might be concealed &amp; kept close: but w<ex>ha</ex>t God will haue discosed, <lb/>
            shall never be concealed. Messingers are sent fro<ex>m</ex> place to place, <lb/>
            he being A Privye Cou<ex>n</ex>cellor and in Favor, his warrant passes <lb/>
            currant, soe <ex>tha</ex>t in all plac<ex>es</ex>, Truncks, Chests, Boxes, Studies, dores <lb/>
            and such houses wherein he suspected anye letters or other matters, <lb/>
            <ex>tha</ex>t app<ex>er</ex>tayned vnto that mischeiffe laie hidd, were brooken ope<ex>n</ex> &amp; searched, <lb/>
            to the intent <ex>tha</ex>t they might bring such writtings to my Lord: yet neu<ex>er</ex>
                <ex>th</ex>elesse <lb/>
            manye (and more then we dreampt of) of those letters came to my Lord <lb/>
            of Canterburyes hand and my Lord Cookes, soe <ex>tha</ex>t these courses maks <lb/>
            him more rather suspected, then any whitt at all eases his greife. /
         </p>
         <p>
            At home in his office vsing extraordinarye Covetuousnes and <lb/>
            parsimonie he thereby heap’d vpp to himselfe greate Store of mony, <lb/>
            and would not vndertake anye enterprise w<ex>i</ex>thout he was well rewar=<lb break="no"/>
            ded for his paine; everye newe occasion and occurrence that came <lb/>
            to his hands brought him in allsoe a Fleece of monye. Offices in Cou<ex>r</ex>t <lb/>
            that laye in his guifte, not bestowed w<ex>i</ex>thout monye, <ex>th</ex>e Kings letters <lb/>
            not purchased w<ex>i</ex>thout monye, noe p<ex>ar</ex>don obtayned w<ex>i</ex>thout monye, soe <lb/>
            that he was as great A bribe taker, as his Mother the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse <lb/>
            of Suffolke, and as many rumors and hard reports were sprad <lb/>
            on him for the same. yet neverthelesse he Still continued his <lb/>
             favor <lb/>
            in dispighte, (as a man might saye) of his opposites, even vnto the <lb/>
            greatest dignitie, w<ex>hi</ex>ch caused him to be as proude as Covetuous, and <lb/>
            to comitt as manye open insolencies as he had received secrett bribs, <lb/>
            thought it noe matter to leane on the Kings Cushio<ex>n</ex> in publique, to check <lb/>
            some of the nobillitie, and Amongst the rest to make a flatt breach <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th my Lord of Canterburye, A grave and reverend gent<ex>le</ex>man one <lb/>
            of the Pillars of this kingdome, and that could descerne the follies <lb/>
            of this yonge man. Thus admiring of his owne worthe, he works <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">his</fw>
            <pb n="23r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f023r/add_ms_22591_f023r.jpg"/>
            his owne subvertion, and by these insolencies plucking more evills <lb/>
            vpon his head, and dailye adding more Enemies to those that before <lb/>
            he had deserved
         </p>
         <p>
            These thinges laying him open to the envye of <ex>th</ex>e greatest, and <lb/>
            S<ex>i</ex>r Georg Villars seeing his exceeding Covetuousnes, having now <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Eares of the kinge, would oftentimes crosse his expectac<ex>i</ex>ons as it is cre=<lb break="no"/>
            dible reported, and deceive him of manye A Bribe w<ex>hi</ex>ch he hoped <lb/>
            for, doing those things voluntarilye and for A thanke w<ex>hi</ex>ch my Lord <lb/>
            would not haue spoken of w<ex>i</ex>thout much monye. these Courses laide <lb/>
            him open to the Contempt of the Vulgar allsoe / and nowe all men  <lb/>
            according to their Custome began to exclaime of his greate ex=<lb break="no"/>
            tortion: Thus maye wee see him following /   
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="RM">
               <hi rend="italic">
                  Ouerburyes death <lb/>
                  called into question <lb/>
                  Westo<ex>n</ex> sent for &amp; by <lb/>
                  my Lo<ex>rd</ex> Cooke  Examined <lb/>
                  Stands out, vpon my  <lb/>
                  Lo<ex>rd</ex> of Lond<ex>on’s</ex>p<ex>er</ex>swasion <lb/>
                  confesseth all, <ex>th</ex>e Earl <lb/>
                  and cou<ex>n</ex>tese attached, <lb/>
                  they deny the deede, <lb/>
                  S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Mounson <lb/>
                  comitted to <ex>th</ex>e Tower, <lb/>
                  S<ex>i</ex>r Walter Raleighe <lb/>
                  and the countiss of  <lb/>
                  Shrewsburye set at <lb/>
                  libertie, <ex>th</ex>e deathe <lb/>
                  of <ex>th</ex>e Ladye Arbella <lb/>
                  <ex>th</ex>e convictio<ex>n</ex> of <ex>th</ex>e E<ex>arl</ex> <lb/>
                  and Cou<ex>n</ex>tis. <ex>Th</ex>e man<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
                  of their Arraignem<ex>en</ex>t, <lb/>
                  and <ex>th</ex>e many rumors <lb/>
                  that were Spread  <lb/>
                  vpo<ex>n</ex> these thinges /
               </hi>
            </add>
            <hi rend="bold">The</hi> deathe of Overburye hauing now lyen concealed aboute <lb/>
            two yeares, and the Earles insolencie growing everye day great<ex>e</ex>r <lb/>
            then other, p<ex>ro</ex>cured him manye more Enemies as is said, yet there <lb/>
            was noe man that was soe hardie for feare of the Kings displeasure, <lb/>
            (he carrying A verye good affecc<ex>i</ex>on Still towards him) to make him <lb/>
            acquainted w<ex>i</ex>th it, or bringe it to the triall of the lawe. At last (for <lb/>
            divers are the Rumors howe it was discovered) one was that S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas <lb/>
            Overburyes man petic<ex>i</ex>ons to my Lord Coke, and the Substance of the <lb/>
            Petition was, to lett his Lordship vnderstand, that whereas his m<ex>aste</ex>r <lb/>
            had bine Comitted to the Tower by the consent of North<ex>amp</ex>ton &amp; Som<ex>er</ex>s<ex>et</ex> <lb/>
            and there languishing to deathe vnnaturallie, that if it pleased his <lb/>
            Lordshipp to Call One Weston before him, he might gather <ex>tha</ex>t out <lb/>
            of him, that would disclose <ex>th</ex>e whole practise. Others saie, that my <lb/>
            Lord of Canterburye, having conceived (as is said) some dislike <lb/>
            against Som<ex>er</ex>sett, and willing to make himselfe gratious w<ex>i</ex>th the <lb/>
            Kinge, possesses S<ex>i</ex>r Raphe Winwood w<ex>i</ex>th the busines (one that was <lb/>
            pr<ex>e</ex>ferred to bee Secretarye vnder my Lord of Som<ex>er</ex>sett, &amp; to assist <lb/>
            him) and letts him vnderstand the whole matter as hath bine re=<lb break="no"/>
            lated, and that manye letters came vnto his handes &amp; pr<ex>e</ex>su<ex>m</ex>pc<ex>i</ex>ons  <lb/>
            therein, that it should be true.  And there remayned A Truncke  <lb/>
            in such A Place wherein manye writtings were Contayned <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            would make evident the truthe. S<ex>i</ex>r Raphe being willing likewise <lb/>
            to become more eminent w<ex>i</ex>th the kinge, possest him w<ex>i</ex>th the busines, <lb/>
            and p<ex>ro</ex>ceeding vpo<ex>n</ex> A Confident Ground, warrant was sent to my <lb/>
            Lord Cooke, to p<ex>ro</ex>secute the matter. Others saie that by the losse <lb/>
            of A letter it was disclosed. And divers opinions there were <lb/>
            howe it should come to light, it having bine kept soe close soe long, <lb/>
            for thinges of this nature, when they are soe longe concealed bring <lb/>
            more wonder. But howsoever it was made knowne, my Lo<ex>rd</ex> Cooke <lb/>
            by vertue of his warrant, sent for Weston to come before him, <lb/>
            &amp; examined him vpo<ex>n</ex> divers Articles concerning this subiecte, <lb/>
            &amp; p<ex>er</ex>swaded him, intreated him, &amp; threatned him to tell the truthe / <lb/>
            Weston Stood out and would not, thus he p<ex>er</ex>sisted some weeke or a <lb/>
            Fortnight / manye men vrged him to it, accusors were brought <lb/>
            before him and deposed vpo<ex>n</ex> their oathes, <ex>tha</ex>t whatsoever was <lb/>
            obiected to him was true / This little pr<ex>e</ex>vayled; At last my Lo<ex>rd</ex> <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">of</fw>
            <pb n="23v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f023v/add_ms_22591_f023v.jpg"/>
            of London went to him, &amp; by his p<ex>er</ex>swasions he tells all: How M<ex>ist</ex>ris Tur=<lb break="no"/>
            ner &amp; <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse came acquainted, w<ex>ha</ex>t Relatio<ex>n</ex> shee had to witches, <lb/>
            Sorcerors, &amp; Coniurors, <ex>tha</ex>t North<ex>amp</ex>ton, Som<ex>er</ex>sett, Francklyn, the Monsons, &amp; <lb/>
            Yelvis, had all their hands in these busynesses; Wherevpo<ex>n</ex> they were all <lb/>
            appr<ex>e</ex>hended, Some sent to <ex>th</ex>e Tower, Oth<ex>e</ex>rs to Newgate. Having thus co<ex>n</ex>fest <lb/>
            this evill and being Convicted according to the Course of Lawe, hee was <lb/>
            had to Tyborne to be hanged, and there S<ex>i</ex>r Iohn Lydlis &amp; others yma=<lb break="no"/>
            gining this to be but A Fable, and <ex>tha</ex>t he was hired to accuse those <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>sons (for whoe allmost would haue beleived it) examines him of it <lb/>
            at the Gallowes, &amp; vpo<ex>n</ex> his examinac<ex>i</ex>on, he iustifyed what he had done, <lb/>
            to the great wonder of all those <ex>tha</ex>t Stood by and harde him. After him <lb/>
            M<ex>ist</ex>ris Turner; After her Francklyne, then S<ex>i</ex>r Iervice Yelvis vpo<ex>n</ex> their <lb/>
            severall Arraignem<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, &amp; co<ex>n</ex>fessions of <ex>th</ex>e facte, were found guiltie <lb/>
            and hanged, all verye penitent and sorrowefull for w<ex>ha</ex>t was done. To <lb/>
            write <ex>th</ex>e p<ex>ar</ex>ticulers of <ex>the</ex>ir Arraignem<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>, Confessions, and the manner <lb/>
            of their deathes, is needlesse, being Como<ex>n</ex>. Nowe the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse and the  <lb/>
            Earle were attached, and comitted to <ex>th</ex>e p<ex>ro</ex>tecc<ex>i</ex>on, one to the deane of <lb/>
            Westminster, the other to the Shreiffe of London, &amp; according to <lb/>
            the Courses of such Cases there are great reports raysed, Watche  <lb/>
            and ward kept, more then ordinarye, and the Guard more observant <lb/>
            This makes the Kinge Stand at A Maze, aand to ymagine <ex>tha</ex>t there is <lb/>
            noe truthe in men, growes more iealous of himselfe then hereto=<lb break="no"/>
            fore, because Carr his onlye Favorite, and <ex>tha</ex>t laie (as it were) <lb/>
            in his bosome, should be intrapt in such an evill. And <ex>th</ex>e tongues <lb/>
            of the vulgar beginne to walke: some saie <ex>tha</ex>t North<ex>amp</ex>ton &amp; Som<ex>er</ex>sett, <lb/>
            had combyned w<ex>i</ex>th the Spaniard for A some of Monye to deliver <lb/>
            them vpp <ex>th</ex>e Navye, and <ex>tha</ex>t S<ex>i</ex>r Will<ex>i</ex>am Monson Viceadmirall shold <lb/>
            haue done it <ex>th</ex>e next Springe  That the kinge &amp; whole State should haue <lb/>
            bene poysoned at the Christning of the Cou<ex>n</ex>tesses Child (for she was <lb/>
            then w<ex>i</ex>th Child)  And manye more the like rumors were Spread not <lb/>
            worth the speaking, to the intent to incense the people <ex>th</ex>e more ag<ex>ain</ex>st <lb/>
            them, and to make the matter the more heynous &amp; greivous to the <lb/>
            world. At this tyme the Lady Arbella dyed, A matter more <lb/>
            remarkable then was observed, and gave some occasio<ex>n</ex> of speeche <lb/>
            to manye, but yet neverthelesse past over in silence /
         </p>
         <p>
            These hurlye burlies being growne something calme, and the <lb/>
            myndes of men A litle setled, <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse and Somersett were called <lb/>
            before my Lord Chancellor and others authorised for that purpose, <lb/>
            to be examined, and my Lord Cooke was the man that prest the <lb/>
            Evidence ag<ex>ain</ex>st them w<ex>hi</ex>ch (as it was thought) p<ex>ro</ex>cured him some gr<ex>ea</ex>t <lb/>
            enemies: Two &amp; twentie Articles were obiected against them, <lb/>
            to all w<ex>hi</ex>ch or to most p<ex>ar</ex>te of them, Somersett pleaded ignorace, <lb/>
            and <ex>tha</ex>t these obiections were meere trickes to intrapp him, and <lb/>
            incense the kinge against him / The same answere was in <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tis, <lb/>
            and <ex>tha</ex>t it might rather proceed out of envye, then for anye iust cause <lb/>
            They cause it to be given out, <ex>tha</ex>t theire accusation was wro<ex>n</ex>gfull, <lb/>
            and none were accused, but such as were greatest favorits to <lb/>
            the Kinge, soe <ex>tha</ex>t there was muche a doe to litle purpose. At last <lb/>
            when they hard, <ex>tha</ex>t Weston, Turner, Franklyn and Yelvis were all <lb/>
            hanged, and that they had co<ex>n</ex>fest the matter, <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse beinge <lb/>
            brought before <ex>th</ex>e Councell, confest the whole truth, but Som<ex>er</ex>sett <lb/>
            Stood to it Still <ex>tha</ex>t he was not Agent in it, &amp; <ex>tha</ex>t these accusations <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">did</fw>
            <pb n="24r" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f024r/add_ms_22591_f024r.jpg"/>
            did nothing touch him, and therefore ought to be excused. Never<ex>th</ex>eles <lb/>
            his Landes and goods were com<ex>m</ex>itted to Custodie, p<ex>ar</ex>te to my Lo<ex>rd</ex> Treasuror, <lb/>
            &amp; p<ex>ar</ex>te to others to the kings vse The monye, plate &amp; Iewells w<ex>hi</ex>ch he <lb/>
            had heaped vp togither, amounted by reporte vnto 280000: poundes: <lb/>
            his Landes to 19000 li p<ex>er</ex> Ann<ex>um</ex>, and the kinge bestowed manye of the<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
            vpo<ex>n</ex> the Prince. There was litle Speeche of this, in respect <ex>tha</ex>t both the <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>son &amp; matter wherein he was Agent were both envied &amp; facinoro<add place="above">u</add>s <lb/>
            neither was there anye <ex>tha</ex>t pittyed him, but most said, <ex>tha</ex>t he had but his <lb/>
            iust deserts, for the Iniuries &amp; wrongs <ex>tha</ex>t he had offered to Essexe /
         </p>
         <p>
            The arraignem<ex>en</ex>t was put of, and in <ex>th</ex>e meane time, S<ex>i</ex>r Walter <lb/>
            Raleige was sett at libertie. This man had Continued in <ex>th</ex>e Tower <lb/>
            nowe allmost ten yeares A condemned p<ex>er</ex>son, for a Plott inte<ex>n</ex>ded <lb/>
            against his ma<ex>jes</ex>tye at his first coming in, he bore a great envie ag<ex>ain</ex>st <lb/>
            Somersett because he had begged his Landes of the kinge, &amp; gott it <lb/>
            into his possession givinge him many quipps &amp; taunts during <ex>th</ex>e time <lb/>
            <ex>tha</ex>t he was in the Tower / these two accidents happening beyond expec=<lb break="no"/>
            tac<ex>i</ex>on: <ex>tha</ex>t the one being <ex>th</ex>e espetiall favorite of <ex>th</ex>e kinge, <ex>th</ex>e other A con=<lb break="no"/>
            demned man; the one ymprisoned, the oth<ex>e</ex>r sett at libertie, gave great <lb/>
            occasion of Speech &amp; rumor, and soe much <ex>th</ex>e more wonder &amp; admirac<ex>i</ex>on, <lb/>
            because of Raleighes witt &amp; pollicie. And this yeere allsoe, <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            tesse of Shrewsburye, whoe was comitted for being pr<ex>i</ex>vie to the <lb/>
            escape of <ex>th</ex>e Ladye Arbella, was sett at libertie, &amp; <ex>th</ex>e Earle her husba<ex>n</ex>d <lb/>
            dyed, leaving the greatest p<ex>ar</ex>te of his Lande vnto his daughters /
         </p>
         <p>
            During all this this time, <ex>tha</ex>t is fro<ex>m</ex> Michaellmasse terme, vnto <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            shorte Vacac<ex>i</ex>on betweene Easter &amp; Trynitie termes, the Arraignem<ex>en</ex>t <lb/>
            was put of, some attributed <ex>th</ex>e Cause to be, for because <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse <lb/>
            was w<ex>i</ex>th Child, and in the meane time was delivered of A daughter / <lb/>
            some, <ex>tha</ex>t further proofes of incertainties might be brought in / oth<ex>e</ex>rs <lb/>
            to give them longer time to consider vpo<ex>n</ex> the matter, &amp; <ex>tha</ex>t it was A <lb/>
            greate favor / I saye, these rumors being published amongst <ex>th</ex>e people, <lb/>
            At length the kinge authorised my Lord Chau<ex>n</ex>cellor to be high Ste=<lb break="no"/>
            ward of England for the time beinge, and ioyned 8: of <ex>th</ex>e Iudges w<ex>i</ex>th  <lb/>
            him, for his assistant<ex>es</ex> / Vizt. the fower Iudgs of <ex>th</ex>e Kings Benche, My <lb/>
            Lord cheiffe Iustice of <ex>th</ex>e Como<ex>n</ex> Plees, Iustice Nicholes, my Lo<ex>rd</ex> cheiffe <lb/>
            Baro<ex>n</ex> &amp; oth<ex>e</ex>rs of <ex>th</ex>e Barons, w<ex>i</ex>th power to call Som<ex>er</ex>sett &amp; <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tisse <lb/>
            before them, to shew cause wherefore they should not haue <ex>th</ex>e sentence <lb/>
            of death passed vpo<ex>n</ex> them, for this offence comitted, both against <ex>th</ex>e law <lb/>
            of the Land, &amp; ag<ex>ain</ex>st <ex>th</ex>e Kinge, his Crowne &amp; Dignitie. Soe vpo<ex>n</ex> <ex>th</ex>e 24th of <lb/>
            Maye in <ex>th</ex>e yeere 1616: there being a seate royall placed at <ex>th</ex>e vpp<ex>er</ex> end <lb/>
            of Westminster hall, A litle short of <ex>th</ex>e kings benche, and seats made <lb/>
            round about it, for <ex>th</ex>e rest of <ex>th</ex>e Iudges and Peeres to sitt on, <del rend="strikethrough">a</del> A little ca=<lb break="no"/>
            bine built close by <ex>th</ex>e como<ex>n</ex> pleas for <ex>th</ex>e Prisoners, when they came from <lb/>
            <ex>th</ex>e Tower to be put to rest them in, they p<ex>ro</ex>ceed to <ex>th</ex>e tryall after this man<ex>er</ex>, <lb/>
            As soone as my Lord Highe Steward w<ex>i</ex>th greate State came into West <lb/>
            minster Hall w<ex>i</ex>th his assistants <ex>th</ex>e Iudges, divers Lord<ex>es</ex> and Gent<ex>le</ex>men <lb/>
            attending, and 4: Serieants at Armes before him, ascending A little <lb/>
            Gallerye made of purpose to keepe of <ex>th</ex>e Crowde, he takes his Seate, &amp; <lb/>
            <ex>th</ex>e rest of his assistants &amp; Peeres according to their places. This being <lb/>
            done, after silence p<ex>ro</ex>clamed, one of <ex>th</ex>e Herrald<ex>es</ex> at Armes reaches <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            highe Steward his patent, &amp; he delivers it to <ex>th</ex>e Clarke of <ex>th</ex>e Crowne <lb/>
            to read it / After S<ex>i</ex>r Raphe Conysby reaches him his Staffe, and is <lb/>
            there pr<ex>e</ex>sent accordinge to his place to give attendance. Aft<ex>e</ex>r <ex>th</ex>e Patent <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">read</fw>
            <pb n="24v" facs="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f024v/add_ms_22591_f024v.jpg"/>
            read, and p<ex>ro</ex>clamation for silence, &amp; <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e accusors should come in, <ex>th</ex>e Prisoners <lb/>
            were sent for by <ex>th</ex>e Clarke of <ex>th</ex>e Checke, whose office it was to attend <ex>th</ex>e Pri=<lb break="no"/>
            soners. This being done, and <ex>th</ex>e Prisoners placed at <ex>th</ex>e Barr, S<ex>i</ex>r <hi rend="italic">
                    <ex>BLANK</ex>
                </hi> Fanshaw <lb/>
            reades the Indictm<ex>en</ex>t, to w<ex>hi</ex>ch <ex>th</ex>e Cou<ex>n</ex>tesse pleaded guiltie, and confessed <ex>th</ex>e fact, <lb/>
            but Som<ex>er</ex>sett pleaded not guiltie, and had time fro<ex>m</ex> tenn of <ex>th</ex>e Clocke in <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Morning till ten of <ex>th</ex>e Clocke at night to cleere himselfe / much was said <lb/>
            but to litle purpose. At last the Peeres hauing conferred of <ex>th</ex>e matter, re=<lb break="no"/>
            turne their verdict, laying their handes vpo<ex>n</ex> their Brests, &amp; swearing by <lb/>
            their honors (for they doe not take an oathe as ordinarye Iurors doe) that he <lb/>
            was guiltie of <ex>th</ex>e murder and poysoning of S<ex>i</ex>r Thomas Overbury. Where <lb/>
            vpo<ex>n</ex> my Lord high Steward p<ex>ro</ex>nou<ex>n</ex>ced sentence of Death against him, and <lb/>
             soe he was had backe to the Tower, where he remayneth at the mercie of <lb/>
            the kinge. This man maye iustlye saie, as sometimes Pope Barbarossa <lb/>
            saide, when he was put fro<ex>m</ex> the Popedome /
         </p>
         <cb/>
         <p>
            <foreign xml:lang="la">
               <hi rend="bold">
                  Qui modo sum<ex>m</ex>us era<ex>m</ex> lætatus nomine præsul <lb/>
                  Tristis et abiectus nunc mea fata gemo <lb/>
                  Excatsus Solio nuper versabar in alto <lb/>
                  Cunctaq<ex>ue</ex> gens pedibus, oscula prona daba<ex>n</ex>t <lb/>
                  Nunc ego pænaru<ex>m</ex> fundo de <unclear>nuluor in imo</unclear> <lb/>
                  Vultu<ex>m</ex> deformen pallidaq<ex>ue</ex> ore gero <lb/>
                  Omnibus è terris auru<ex>m</ex> mihi Sponte ferebant <lb/>
                  Sed nec gaza <unclear>niuet</unclear> necquis amicis adest <lb/>
                  Sic varians fortuna vices adu<ex>er</ex>sa secu<ex>n</ex>dis <lb/>
                  Subdit et ambiguis nomine ludit atrox <lb/>
                  Cedit in exe<ex>m</ex>plu<ex>m</ex> <unclear>cu<ex>n</ex>etis</unclear> quos gloria tollit <lb/>
                  Vortice de summo, moxego Papa cado.
               </hi>
            </foreign>
         </p>
         <cb/>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">
               Loe here I am, that sometyme tooke delight <lb/>
               in name of Pope <lb/>
               Nowe being sadd &amp; abiect doe bewaile <lb/>
               my fate and hope <lb/>
               Of late pretend, I did converse with state=<lb break="no"/>
               lye Pompe and grace <lb/>
               And eu<ex>er</ex>y Nation to my feete theire rea=<lb break="no"/>
               die kisses place, <lb/>
               But now in dungion deepe and throwne, of <lb/>
               paines in mortall feare <lb/>
               A Cou<ex>n</ex>t’nance pale, a bodye leane, deform’d <lb/>
               with greife I beare, <lb/>
               #Fro<ex>m</ex> <lb/>
               #From all parts of <ex>th</ex>e Earth, they brought mee <lb/>
               gold, w<ex>i</ex>thout co<ex>n</ex>straint <lb/>
               But now nor gold, nor pretious Stones, nor freind<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
               can ease my playnt <lb/>
               Soe variable fortune is, toe nice to great <lb/>
               attempts <lb/>
               Soe subiect &amp; soe doubtfull toe, soe aduerse <lb/>
               in Events <lb/>
               That Atis with our name doth playe, as with <lb/>
               A tenis Ball <lb/>
               For being lifted vp with fame, the greater <lb/>
               is our fall, <lb/>
               Let this example be to such, whom fortune <lb/>
               doth aduance <lb/>
               That they as I from Popedome fell, m<add place="above">a</add>y fall <lb/>
               by like mischance /
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            For we cannot read of anye <ex>tha</ex>t eu<ex>er</ex> was soe g<ex>rea</ex>t A Favorite as Som<ex>er</ex>sett, <lb/>
            neither <ex>th</ex>e Spence<add place="above">r</add>s w<ex>i</ex>th Ed<ex>ward</ex> 2:, nor <ex>th</ex>e E<ex>arl</ex> of Warwicke w<ex>i</ex>th <hi rend="italic">H<ex>enry</ex> 6:</hi>, <lb/>
            nor <ex>th</ex>e Duke <lb/>
            of Suffolke w<ex>i</ex>th <hi rend="italic">H<ex>enry</ex> 8:</hi> as this man was w<ex>i</ex>th the kinge, neither was there anye <lb/>
            <ex>tha</ex>t eu<ex>er</ex> came to soe suddaine, &amp; vnexpected A Fall / They therefore <ex>tha</ex>t doe but <lb/>
            rightlie consider this discou<ex>r</ex>se, shall find it in three things worthie observac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            First <ex>tha</ex>t neither honor, nor Wealthe, are anie certaine Inheritanc<ex>es</ex>, but <lb/>
            occasions (vnles God be mercifull vnto vs) for the Devill to picke a quar=<lb break="no"/>
            rell <del rend="strikethrough">w<ex>i</ex>th</del> against vs, to bringe vs into Infamie / Sec<ex>ond</ex> <ex>tha</ex>t God neever leaves <lb/>
            Murther (though never soe closelye Carryed) vnpunished / Lastlye, <ex>tha</ex>t there <lb/>
            was never knowne in soe shorte A time, soe manye great men dye, w<ex>i</ex>th sus=<lb break="no"/>
            pition of poyson and witchcrafte. There was first my Lord Treasuror, <lb/>
            the Prince, my Lord Harrington, his Sonne, Overburye, North<ex>amp</ex>ton, besid<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            these, w<ex>hi</ex>ch are noe lesse then Sixe others, w<ex>i</ex>thin these three yeares and <lb/>
            A halfe, and the two Mounsons w<ex>hi</ex>ch yet remayne vntryed.
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">FINIS</hi>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f002r/add_ms_22591_f002r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f002v/add_ms_22591_f002v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="3" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f003r/add_ms_22591_f003r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="4" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f003v/add_ms_22591_f003v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="5" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f004r/add_ms_22591_f004r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="6" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f004v/add_ms_22591_f004v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="7" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f005r/add_ms_22591_f005r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="8" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f005v/add_ms_22591_f005v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="9" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f006r/add_ms_22591_f006r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="10" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f006v/add_ms_22591_f006v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="11" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f007r/add_ms_22591_f007r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="12" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f007v/add_ms_22591_f007v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="13" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f008r/add_ms_22591_f008r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="14" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f008v/add_ms_22591_f008v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="15" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f009r/add_ms_22591_f009r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="16" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f009v/add_ms_22591_f009v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="17" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f010r/add_ms_22591_f010r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="18" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f010v/add_ms_22591_f010v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="19" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f011r/add_ms_22591_f011r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="20" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f011v/add_ms_22591_f011v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="21" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f012r/add_ms_22591_f012r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="22" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f012v/add_ms_22591_f012v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="23" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f013r/add_ms_22591_f013r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="24" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f013v/add_ms_22591_f013v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="25" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f014r/add_ms_22591_f014r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="26" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f014v/add_ms_22591_f014v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="27" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f015r/add_ms_22591_f015r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="28" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f015v/add_ms_22591_f015v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="29" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f016r/add_ms_22591_f016r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="30" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f016v/add_ms_22591_f016v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="31" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f017r/add_ms_22591_f017r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="32" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f017v/add_ms_22591_f017v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="33" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f018r/add_ms_22591_f018r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="34" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f018v/add_ms_22591_f018v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="35" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f019r/add_ms_22591_f019r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="36" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f019v/add_ms_22591_f019v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="37" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f020r/add_ms_22591_f020r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="38" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f020v/add_ms_22591_f020v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="39" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f021r/add_ms_22591_f021r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="40" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f021v/add_ms_22591_f021v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="41" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f022r/add_ms_22591_f022r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="42" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f022v/add_ms_22591_f022v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="43" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f023r/add_ms_22591_f023r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="44" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f023v/add_ms_22591_f023v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="45" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f024r/add_ms_22591_f024r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="46" url="/bl/add_ms_22591/add_ms_22591_f024v/add_ms_22591_f024v.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>