<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Form of Government in the Kirk of Scotland</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="VA">
               <name>Victoria Anker</name>
               <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLHarleyMS4931.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Harley_MS_4931">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Harley</collection>
                <idno>MS 4931</idno>
                <msName/>
             </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Harley MS 4931</p>
            </msDesc>
            
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1639">c.1639?</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term>Bishops' Wars</term>
               <term>Scotland</term>
               <term>Scottish Church</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2017-07-28" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2017-07-17" who="#VA" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="70r" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f070r/harley_ms_4931_f070r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            The forme of Government in the Kirke of Scotland./.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">1.</add> 
            The Confession of faith, &amp; reformation of the Kirk of Scotland in Doctrine, Wor<ex>shi</ex>p, &amp; <lb/>
            Discipline, were regulated by the word of god, &amp; grounded upon scripture, as is acknow- <lb/>
            ledged by the Harmony of Confessions of the reformed Kirke, &amp; by the testimony of <lb/>
            the best Divines in the Kirk of England, &amp; other reformed Kirks.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">2.</add>
            At <ex>tha</ex>t time, &amp; to this day amidst the greatest dissentions, <unclear>
                    <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del>
                </unclear> &amp; not w<ex>i</ex>thstanding the ambiti- <lb/>
            on, &amp; usurpation of Prelates, noe other Ministers, &amp; officers haue beene acknowled- <lb/>
            ged, or received by the authority of the reformed Kirk of Scotland, but Pastours, Do- <lb/>
            ctors, Elders, &amp; Deacons, these being warranted by Scripture, &amp; being sufficient for  <lb/>
            all <ex>th</ex>e necessary uses of this Kirke; yet so, <ex>tha</ex>t <ex>th</ex>e civill Maigstrate had his owne emi- <lb/>
            nent place, &amp; civill power for <ex>th</ex>e conservation, &amp; purgation of Religion. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">3.</add> 
            Noe man here, w<ex>e</ex>r he never so wise, &amp; pious aboue others, or doth he never so <lb/>
            much arrogate authority to himselfe, hath <ex>th</ex>e reines of Kirk government in his hands, <lb/>
            to dispose, or doe what seemeth good in his owne eyes, but all matters are devised, &amp; <lb/>
            determined by co<ex>m</ex>mon consent, in the conventions, &amp; assemblies of <ex>th</ex>e Kirk: The <lb/>
            kirk Assemblies were of 4 sorts, &amp; degrees, commonly designed by <ex>th</ex>e names of Kirk <lb/>
            sessions, or consistories; Presbyteries, or Classes; Provinciall Synods; &amp; Generall, or na- <lb/>
            tionall assemblies.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">4.</add>
            The Kirk session, or consistory doth consist of one Minister at least, approved for <lb/>
            his learning, life, &amp; skill in government; And of Elders, men of best knowledge, &amp; <lb/>
            holiest life in the parish, so many in number as <ex>th</ex>e proportion <del rend="strikethrough">in</del>
                <add place="above">of</add> the Congregati- <lb/>
            on doth require, who are chosen with the consent of the people, &amp; in the presence <lb/>
            of <ex>th</ex>e people solemnly admitted to their charge. These convene weekly for orde- <lb/>
            ring such matters of <ex>th</ex>e word of god, as are proper to <ex>tha</ex>t parish, as, What daies of  <lb/>
            the weeke are meetest for assembling to the publique wor<ex>shi</ex>p, or Catechising; and What <lb/>
            houres of the Lords day before, &amp; after noone are fittest for the exercises of <ex>tha</ex>t day; At <lb/>
            what times the communion shalbe given; For censuring of Delinquents, by swearing, <lb/>
            cursing, prophaning of the Lords day, drinking, fornication, adultery; &amp; for delating of  <lb/>
            greate offences, such as Heresy, Superstition &amp;c. If any be suspected, or if there be any <lb/>
            scandall in their bounds, proceeding also w<ex>i</ex>th the<unclear>-</unclear> censures of the kirk against them. <lb/>
            That all transgressours may be brought to repentance, or separated from the people of <lb/>
            god, according to the ordinances of <ex>Chris</ex>t, &amp; order of the Kirk. Heere also the Deacons (who <lb/>
            haue the charge of the poore) are present to receiue direction in their duty.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">5.</add>
            The Presbytery, or Classical meeting, doth consist of particular Kirks in such a cir- <lb/>
            cuit, 12. 16. 20. or <add place="above">so</add> many as by convenience of the place can weekely assemble. Here <lb/>
            some one Elder of each parish (appointed by the particular kirk sessions) &amp; the <lb/>
            whole Ministers of these kirks do meete, where the Ministers, &amp; others to be admitted <lb/>
            into <ex>th</ex>e ministry (whom we call Expectants,) exercise their guifts by course, in inter- <lb/>
            preting some places of scripture appointed <ex>the</ex>m by the Presbytery; the exercise, or pro- <lb/>
            phecying being ended, the Ministers, &amp; Elders sitt downe w<ex>i</ex>th their moderatour, &amp; af- <lb/>
            ter prayer, &amp; censure of the Doctrine, they use the power of Iurisdiction, Ordination, <lb/>
            Suspension, Deprivation, Visitation of the Kirks, Tryall of the processes of Exco<ex>m</ex>uni- <lb/>
            cation diduced by the particular Eldershipp, And of Direction to the Minister of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            parish to Exco<ex>m</ex>municate, if need be. Heere the Scandalous faults of Ministers in do- <lb/>
            ctrine, or life, are delated; And all p<ex>er</ex>sons of whatsoever quality disobedient to their <lb/>
            owne ministers, &amp; Elders, are <ex>wi</ex>th greate Authority censured..
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">6.</add> 
            Provinciall synods; these consists of the whole Presbyteries in a shire, or province; <lb/>
            so <ex>th</ex>at the whole kingdome is divided into shires, or provinces, in relation to these Synods. <lb/>
            Here all the Ministers, &amp; one Elder in every parish, doe meete twice in the <lb/>
            Yeare, &amp; after Preaching, &amp; Calling upon the name of God, by the Moderatour of the  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">preceeding</fw>
            <pb n="70v" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f070v/harley_ms_4931_f070v.jpg"/>
            <space unit="page" extent="1"/>
            <pb n="71r" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f071r/harley_ms_4931_f071r.jpg"/>
            preceeding Moderatour, a new Moderatour being chosen, they try the Presbyteries by <ex>the</ex>r <lb/>
            Records, presented by the Clarke of every Presbytery. What was obscure, or difficult <lb/>
            for the Presbytery, or might concerne <ex>the</ex>m all in Common, is determined, &amp; ordered; &amp; <lb/>
            if any difficulty arise, which doth not fall under some Kirke Constitution, its referred <lb/>
            to the Nationall Assembly. All matters are with such diligence expedited, <ex>tha</ex>t each <lb/>
            Minister may returne to his charge on the Lords day. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">7.</add> 
            In the Generall, or Nationall Assembly, the Kings Ma<ex>jes</ex>ty in p<ex>er</ex>son; or his Co<ex>m</ex>missioner <lb/>
            in his place, useth to be present, who conveene once in the yeare, or oftner pro <lb/>
            re nata. It doth consist of Ministers, &amp; Elders from each Presbytery, &amp; Regall bourgh. <lb/>
            After solemne humiliation the first day of <ex>tha</ex>t Assembly one of the ministers is chosen by <lb/>
            the voices of the whole Assembly, to Moderate, &amp; Preside in that Assembly; The records <lb/>
            of the Synods are perused, &amp; tried; Acts, &amp; constitutions for all the Churches are agreed upon <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th common consent, &amp; all mens doubts, &amp; scruples concerning <ex>the</ex>m are satisfied to the full, <lb/>
            if they be propounded <unclear>Ammo <unclear>-</unclear>difitandi, non tentandi</unclear>. Appellations, Petitions, Grievan- <lb/>
            ces, &amp; Complaints are examined, &amp; determined by this supreme, &amp; highest Kirk Iudicatory. <lb/>
            And some Co<ex>m</ex>missioners chosen to p<ex>re</ex>sent grievances, or petitions agree upon in the Assem- <lb/>
            bly, to the Parliament, the King, <ex>th</ex>e Councell of the Kingdome, or Convention of Estates. <lb/>
            In this authority, &amp; subordination of Sessions, Presbyteries, Provinciall Synods, &amp; Nationall <lb/>
            Assemblies, doth consist <ex>th</ex>e Orders, <ex>th</ex>e Beauty, the Strength of <ex>th</ex>e Kirk of Scotland, <lb/>
            comfortable to the godly both Pastours, &amp; Professors, &amp; terrible (as an army w<ex>i</ex>th ban- <lb/>
            ners) to papists (be their places never so high), to all Hereticks, Schismaticks, Hirelings, <lb/>
            &amp; all ungodly men; no scandalous fault of any p<ex>er</ex>son escapeth censure; no heresy, or  <lb/>
            errour can sooner be hatched, but its presently crushed by some of these inferior <lb/>
            assemblies, or if it be kept on foot, or take strength, its quite suppressed by the natio- <lb/>
            nall Assembly, convening once in the yeare; w<ex>hi</ex>ch hath beene a maine cause why so <lb/>
            few sects, or errours in doctrine, or wor<ex>shi</ex>p haue appeared in the Kirke of Scotland for <lb/>
            many years. And wheresoever those Assemblies haue place, power, &amp; liberty, the <lb/>
            names of Heresies, &amp; Sects haue not almost beene heard. In these Assemblies the <lb/>
            particular kirkes are not governed by the extrinsecall power of any one, or many sett <lb/>
            over <ex>the</ex>m, as in the Monarchicall government of Prelates, but they are ruled, and <lb/>
            iudged by <ex>the</ex>mselues, &amp; <ex>the</ex>r owne intrinsecall power, each member by <ex>th</ex>e whole body, in an <lb/>
            orderly way, none of the whole co<ex>m</ex>munion of the faithfull being barred from the <lb/>
            ioynt, &amp; co<ex>m</ex>mon government. By these Assemblies the Gift, the Knowledge, &amp; Zeale <lb/>
            of all the members (especially of the Ministers) are stirred up, quickned, encreased, &amp; <lb/>
            strengthned; an holy emulation is excited by acquaintance, conference, &amp; by perceiving <lb/>
            the gifts one of another; &amp; the best gifts are knowne for planning of Kirks, &amp; Colled- <lb/>
            ges. Whence it is <ex>tha</ex>t ministers returne from these Assemblies ashamed, &amp; humbled <lb/>
            in themselues, &amp; furnished w<ex>i</ex>th fresh resolutions for every pastorall duty, for the <lb/>
            co<ex>m</ex>mon benefitt, &amp; edification of all the Kirks./.
         </p>
         <pb n="71v" facs="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f071v/harley_ms_4931_f071v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               The Scottish <lb/>
               Kirke Go-<lb break="no"/>
               vernment.
            </add>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f070r/harley_ms_4931_f070r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f070v/harley_ms_4931_f070v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="3" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f071r/harley_ms_4931_f071r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="4" url="/bl/harley_ms_4931_part/harley_ms_4931_f071v/harley_ms_4931_f071v.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>