<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from York when the King was There</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="VA">
               <name>Victoria Anker</name>
               <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TW">
               <name>Tim Wales</name>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLAddMS21935.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_21935">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Additional</collection>
                <idno>MS 21935</idno>
                <msName>Nehemiah Wallington book</msName>
             </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Additional MS 21935</p>
            </msDesc>
            
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl/>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1640-09-13">13 September 1640</date>
            <placeName corresp="../places/places.xml#PL0015">York</placeName>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term>letter</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term>Bishop's Wars</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-08-08" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2018-05-24" who="#TW" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="91v" facs="/bl/add_ms_21935_part/add_ms_21935_f091v/add_ms_21935_f091v.jpg"/>
         <head>
            <add place="header" rend="align-centre">
               1640
            </add>
            <add place="header" rend="indent">
               OF the bitternes of warre
            </add>
            But by the way. I will giue you a littel tast of the bitternesse of warr <lb/>
            and that done by our owne Souldiers in this our owne Land: I will <lb/>
            impart vnto you. Some Part of a Letter (that Came from Yoarke <lb/>
            when our King was theire)
         </head>
         <p>
            My deare frendes. I am soe bound to you that I Cannot but wright <lb/>
            a few words to Sertisfie you how it faires with vs at Yoarke <lb/>
            and their abouts  Wee haue no lesse then two &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">twenty</del> <add place="above">thirty</add> thousand <lb/>
            horse and foote at Yoarke and within sixe miles such Spoyle made <lb/>
            of Corne &amp; Hay &amp; Grasse &amp; Fruite and Trees as is Lamentabel <lb/>
            to behold, Sure these are those days foretold <ex>tha</ex>t Tyrants shall <lb/>
            abound, <del rend="strikethrough">For God seuere Curse hath euer most fearefull <unclear>     </unclear> </del> <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">and Ravishings</del>  For Most fearefull Blasphemies: horrable <lb/>
            Thefts, and most Barbaros and vnhedious Adultries &amp; Rauishings <lb/>
            Shure these are a People distinated to destroction. for Gods <lb/>
            seuere Curse hath euer attended such men And yet for all our <lb/>
            misery this is not the Least that wee haue not one to tell vs <lb/>
            how long, nor Yett that Pittys vs in our sad Condition: bvt <lb/>
            diuers Punished for not ioyning with them &amp; not Lending a <lb/>
            hand to Curse &amp; Sware, I the wrighter sertisfie you of this <lb/>
            that you may be more thankfull for your Peace &amp; Liberty. and <lb/>
            more petyfull to vs in this great misery, The King stay still <lb/>
            at Yoarke and the Lord Leftenant keeps with him very Closse <lb/>
            Yester day he had a grate parly with the knites &amp; Gentry <lb/>
            of the North to supply the King with mony, but was withstood <lb/>
            that vext him very Sore. The Country grones vnder <ex>th</ex>e heauie <lb/>
            burdens of Ship mony: Bilitting of Solgers and now setting forth <lb/>
            their traine bands with a months pay in euery mans purse<ex>s</ex> <lb/>
            besides many partickelare greuiances that many Suffer vnder <lb/>
            And our Ministers are Commanded now to Posses their people <lb/>
            after Sermon of the ell Carrage of the Rebelles	
         </p>
         <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">And</fw>
         <pb n="92r" facs="/bl/add_ms_21935_part/add_ms_21935_f092r/add_ms_21935_f092r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <add place="header" rend="align-centre">
               1640
            </add>
            <add place="header" rend="italic align-centre">
               Of the bitternesse of warr
            </add>
            And how grasiously his Maigsty hath dealt with them from time to time <lb/>
            and to exhort their people to dutifull Obeydience. and to beware of <lb/>
            haueing any thing to doe with those Rebels: And one Docter Marsh <lb/>
            Minister of Hullefax Preached before the King yesterday such a Ser <lb/>
            mon against false prophets, and sayd their ware many of them gone <lb/>
            to new England and he doubted they were all such. and would also in <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            end Proue various like the other. We exspect the Lords from <ex>th</ex>e South <lb/>
            very Shortly, the Lorde keepe vs from a mutany, for all Sorts Complaine <lb/>
            and wee are fare out of the good old way of bareing one anothers <lb/>
            burdens, I might say more, but this I doe to giue you a smit of our <lb/>
            Condistion. not doubting but you will Ply the throne of grace where <lb/>
            we hartily desier to meete you. and all that wayt for the day of our <lb/>
            deliuerance: not onely our present mesery but especially from the <lb/>
            body of death and the wayt that presseth downe  Now to God wee <lb/>
            desier to Leaue you and yours and rest
         </p>
         <p rend="align-right">
            Your unsained
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            From Yoarke <ex>th</ex>e XIII of Septem<ex>ber</ex> 1640
         </p>
         <p>
            This Letter did Come Where I was at a priuat Fast at that time <add place="above">G<del rend="strikethrough">iu</del> Him</add>
         </p>
         <p>
            Also the Scots are Pitched betwene Durham and New Cassell <lb/>
            and we here they intend to be at Yoarke the twenty forth of this month <lb/>
            if not before they send as farr as Northollerton &amp; Bedell for prouison <lb/>
            of Corne and Cattell. but pay wee haue very honestly
         </p>
         <p>
            Now What doe I wright out this Letter for  But to shew forth Gods <lb/>
            grate mercy &amp; Patience in this also  but to giue you a littel taste of itt
         </p>
         <p>
            First see their dishonour vnto God in their Blasphemies, Swearing <lb/>
            and Cursing and if any did not so then they should be called Puritens <lb/>
            or Rebels and so their fellows would be ready to Punish them. and <lb/>
            wrong them in what they Could  Oh see Gods grate Patience in forbaring <lb/>
            and <del rend="strikethrough">his</del> the Lords grate marcy in <del rend="strikethrough">Spr</del> Sparing vs
         </p>
         <p>
            Secondly Oh see &amp; Behold the bitter <del rend="strikethrough">fruite </del>fruite of warre in penery <lb/>
            and want for it makes a losse and a spoyel of all both <del rend="strikethrough">both</del> fruites <lb/>
            trees &amp; grounds  I did heare that there ware those that ware worth <lb/>
            fiue hundred pound <del rend="strikethrough">a year</del> <add place="above">a yeere</add> would gladly haue sould it all <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">forr</fw>
            <pb n="92v" facs="/bl/add_ms_21935_part/add_ms_21935_f092v/add_ms_21935_f092v.jpg"/>
            <add place="header" rend="align-centre">
               1640
            </add>
            <add place="header" rend="italic align-centre">
               Of the bitternesse of warr
            </add>
            all for a hungdred pound and haue giuen vp the right tittle of it <lb/>
            and their is such Spoyle of ground <del rend="strikethrough">thought</del> that it is thought <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            some will not recouer it againe this many yeeres
         </p>
         <p>
            Thirdly none Could scarse inioy his owne house for loging of Solgers <lb/>
            and grate wronge done to many weomen &amp; mayds, most horrable <lb/>
            thefts, I did heere Creditably that our Soulgers would get blwe <lb/>
            iakets and apparel themselues Like Scots and so a Company of them <lb/>
            goe together to our houses or viliages &amp; robe &amp; Pilleg them
         </p>
         <p>
            Forthly this ads to misery when as wee know no end nor how <lb/>
            Long it will Last
         </p>
         <p>
            Fiftly Oh then Considier how the enemies. &amp; flatterers &amp; des <lb/>
            semeller to be about our King stiring him to goe against thes <lb/>
            deare Children of God &amp; the Kings faithfull Subiects and <lb/>
            his true Subiects that are gone to New England
         </p>
         <p>
            Sixtly Consider the Country groning vnder <ex>th</ex>e heauy burden <lb/>
            of Shipmony. billiting of Solgers &amp; setting forth traine bands <lb/>
            with a months Pay in euery mans Purse
         </p>
         <p>
            Seuenthly See againe how they Command the Ministers to <lb/>
            Possesse the <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> People with Wronges and Slanders against <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Kings best Subiects and Cales them Rebels
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">8</add>
            Lastly Behold the Slanders that are Layd One the Scots <lb/>
            how they robe &amp; take things from them without Pay when <lb/>
            as they Pay very honestly
         </p>
         <p>
            Oh now behold and Consider of this grate marcy of God <lb/>
            in deliuering vs out of this grate misery and Causing Warr <lb/>
            to Cease
         </p> 
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/add_ms_21935_part/add_ms_21935_f091v/add_ms_21935_f091v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/add_ms_21935_part/add_ms_21935_f092r/add_ms_21935_f092r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="3" url="/bl/add_ms_21935_part/add_ms_21935_f092v/add_ms_21935_f092v.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>