<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Offer Made by the Archdukes and Accepted by the States in April 1607</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="VA">
               <name>Victoria Anker</name>
               <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TW">
               <name>Tim Wales</name>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLAddMS11600.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_11600">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <repository>British Library</repository>
               <collection>Additional</collection>
               <idno>MS 11600</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Additional MS 11600</p>
            </msDesc>
            
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1607">1607</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
            <language ident="LA">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term>foreign policy</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-08-16" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2018-04" who="#TW" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="106v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f106v/add_ms_11600_f106v.jpg"/>
         <head rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">
               An offer made by the Archdukes and accepted by <lb/>
               the States in Aprill i607.
            </hi>
         </head>
         <p>
            The <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> affectinge nothinge more then to see the low <lb/>
            Countreis and theire good inhabitants deliuered from theire <lb/>
            Wars, doe heereby declare w<ex>i</ex>th good deliberac<ex>i</ex>on that they ar <lb/>
            contented to treate w<ex>i</ex>th the States gen<ex>er</ex>all of the vnited provinces <lb/>
            in quallitie, and as holdinge them for Countries Provinces <lb/>
            and <hi rend="italic">States</hi> free, ouer the w<ex>hi</ex>ch theire highnesses doe pretende <lb/>
            nothinge, be it by waie of a perpetuall peace or of a Truce <lb/>
            or suspention of Armes for twelue, fyfteene or twenty yeares <lb/>
            at the choise of the said <hi rend="italic">States</hi> and all vpon reasonable condic<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            Amonge w<ex>hi</ex>ch Condic<ex>i</ex>ons alsoe shalbe agreed aswell by the conclusion <lb/>
            of perpetuall peace as the said Truice or suspention of Armes <lb/>
            that either shall abide w<ex>i</ex>th that w<ex>hi</ex>ch hee nowe holdeth and <lb/>
            possesseth vnles by a Comon consent it can<ex>n</ex> bee otherwise <lb/>
            Concluded, to accomodate theire <hi rend="italic">highnesses</hi> and the said <hi rend="italic">States</hi> <lb/>
            togeather w<ex>i</ex>th the Countries respectiuely, by exchange of some <lb/>
            Townes or places: he likewise vpon the order and Assurance <lb/>
            of the Traffique and frequentac<ex>i</ex>on, w<ex>i</ex>th the dependances and <lb/>
            likewise of the intervention agreem<ex>en</ex>t and maintenance of that <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch shalbe concluded, And theire highnesses, havinge ripelie <lb/>
            considered the Constituc<ex>i</ex>on and state of the vnited provinces <lb/>
            and purposinge to deale w<ex>i</ex>th them sincerely and w<ex>i</ex>thout <lb/>
            deceit, and to admitt the said <hi rend="italic">States</hi>. tyme to resolue of <lb/>
            what is most convenient for the Comon good) are contented <lb/>
            that the personnes whome they shall depute for the said Treatie <lb/>
            (borne in the lowe Countreis) shall assemble w<ex>i</ex>th those of <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">States</hi> in equall nomber at such tyme and place as <lb/>
            the said <hi rend="italic">States</hi> shall make choise of. And to thend that the <lb/>
            premisses may the better proceede, be it to a perpetuall peace <lb/>
            or the said Truice theire <hi rend="italic">highnesses</hi> are Contented that for <lb/>
            the eight next monethes there be a Cessation of all sieges <lb/>
            Surprises of Townes and fortresses, Invations and lodgings <lb/>
            in the provinces and quarters and the buildinge of anie <lb/>
            fortes. Provided that the said <hi rend="italic">States</hi> shall graunte and 
            <pb n="107r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f107r/add_ms_11600_f107r.jpg"/>
            accord (also) of theire side the said provitionall cessation and that w<ex>i</ex>thin eight <lb/>
            daies after the presentac<ex>i</ex>on of these and that before the first daie of <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> next cominge they shall make their declarac<ex>i</ex>on vnto theire <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">highnesses </hi>vpon the said principall treatie offered them, either of <lb/>
            peace or suspenc<ex>i</ex>on of Armes w<ex>i</ex>th the tyme and place to be chosen <lb/>
            to that ende. / .  Theise Condic<ex>i</ex>ons and all other hostile actions <lb/>
            by <add place="above">sea</add> and lande in all the Lowe Countries, and by Sea in <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> and <lb/>
            else where aswell for the regard of the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> as theire <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">highnesses </hi>from the daie of <ex>Blank</ex> And w<ex>i</ex>th Condic<ex>i</ex>on that yf <lb/>
            from that daie and Moneth the one p<ex>ar</ex>te (havinge not beene adu<ex>er</ex>tised <lb/>
            thereof) taketh anie thinge vpon the other it shalbe restored againe <lb/>
            were accordinge to the <hi rend="italic">Archdukes</hi> first proposic<ex>i</ex>on inserted in the <lb/>
            originall of that before written accepted offer where this mark ◌ is <lb/>
            impressed but nowe by the <hi rend="italic">States</hi> accepted and theire <unclear>exc</unclear>eption by <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">Archduke </hi>accorded. Jointly w<ex>i</ex>th the <hi rend="italic">States</hi> acception of the <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Archdukes</hi> offer, they demaunded, and he consented promise, that <lb/>
            the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines</hi> Aggreation and declarac<ex>i</ex>on to that of his <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">highnesses</hi>, shall w<ex>i</ex>thin the first three monethes next followinge <lb/>
            the first daie of the Cessac<ex>i</ex>on bee deliu<ex>er</ex>ed vnto the <hi rend="italic">States</hi>. / .
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">
               The Negotiation of the Archdukes Comissioners w<ex>i</ex>th those of <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
               States hath since <ex>tha</ex>t ouerture among other, produced <lb/>
               especiallie these effectes. / . <lb/>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            That it shalbe lawfull for the <hi rend="italic">States</hi> havinge nowe graunted a <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">Comission</del> Cessac<ex>i</ex>on at the Sea vpon theese Coastes as farr as the <lb/>
            Gorlings) to continewe theire accustomed guardes notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge <lb/>
            the Cessation) vpon the Coastes of Flaunders to hinder the ingresse <lb/>
            and egresse in to and out of the <hi rend="italic">Archdukes</hi> havens. That no <lb/>
            Souldier w<ex>i</ex>thout theire lymitted Garrisons nor other inhabitants <lb/>
            that shalbe found in theire contrarie <hi rend="italic">Prouinces</hi> shall enioye <lb/>
            the freedome of Cessac<ex>i</ex>on but remaine subieect to the rigour of <lb/>
            Warre, vnlesse they haue license expresselie to that ende <lb/>
            That w<ex>i</ex>thin sixe weekes after the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines</hi> declarac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            and aggreation to what the <hi rend="italic">Archdukes</hi> hath done and shall <lb/>
            doe touchinge the peace soe delyuered vnto the <hi rend="italic">States</hi> they <lb/>
            Will recall theire fleete of Warre from <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>. That
            <pb n="107v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f107v/add_ms_11600_f107v.jpg"/>
            duringe the tyme limitted for the deliu<ex>er</ex>ie of the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic"/>
                </hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Aggreation </hi>the <hi rend="italic">States</hi> will not reenforce there present Fleete <lb/>
            and Strength of warre at Sea. vpon the Coasts of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> That <lb/>
            duringe the cessation of the States will suffer the small fisherie <lb/>
            of the <hi rend="italic">Archdukes </hi>havens peaceable to labour in and out <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout molestac<ex>i</ex>on. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Essaies of Coniecture</hi> <lb/>
            vpon the foresaid propositions and Negotiac<ex>i</ex>ons touchinge <lb/>
            Cessac<ex>i</ex>on of Armes, and peace betweene the <hi rend="italic">Archduke</hi> <lb/>
            and the <hi rend="italic">States. by Ge<add place="above">r</add>llill Tauerner, veritate et <lb/>
            reuerentia, more, eet amore</hi>. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            The Scope of my coniecture diuides it selfe into three <lb/>
            discourses. / . 
         </p>
         <p>
            1	Vppon some perticulares for the most p<ex>ar</ex>t proper to the	 <lb/>
            Cessation, provided, excepted and graunted by the <hi rend="italic">States</hi>. /
         </p>
         <p>
            2	What reasons there are, that either doe or ought move his <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">highnes </hi>the <hi rend="italic">Archdukes</hi> inclinac<ex>i</ex>on to a peace, and what <lb/>
            to bringe the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines</hi> accorde. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Whether the <hi rend="italic">States </hi>should affecte a peace vpon this offer <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">his highnesses </hi>w<ex>i</ex>th the amplificac<ex>i</ex>on of discourse <lb/>
            vppon some particulars concerninge the conclusion and <lb/>
            state of peace /
         </p>
         <p>
            Touchinge particulars provided excepted and graunted by <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">States</hi>. 		<hi rend="italic">Prouided / .	</hi>That w<ex>i</ex>thin three <lb/>
            monethes after the first daie of the Cessac<ex>i</ex>on the kinge <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">Spaines </hi>Aggreac<ex>i</ex>on to what the <hi rend="italic">Archduke </hi>hath <lb/>
            done and shaall doe touchinge the peace shalbe deliu<ex>er</ex>ed <lb/>
            to the <hi rend="italic">States</hi>. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            This is the <hi rend="italic">Base </hi>whereon the frame and <hi rend="italic">Architecture </hi>of <lb/>
            the Negotiac<ex>i</ex>on ought to be erected, for the sufficient <lb/>
            authoritie of the offer (because the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> is the <lb/>
            principall pretender ou<ex>er</ex> them) must consist either vpon <lb/>
            the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines </hi> publique disclamac<ex>i</ex>on of his <lb/>
            p<ex>re</ex>tended right and claime to the principallitie of theise
            <pb n="108r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f108r/add_ms_11600_f108r.jpg"/>
            Countries by hauinge gyven his interest wholy to the Archduke and his <lb/>
            next bloude  and soe successivelie to all psoteritie descendinge theire or in <lb/>
            his authenticall authorism<ex>en</ex>t and ratificac<ex>i</ex>on of what the Archduke shall <lb/>
            treate and conclude and boeth in respect aswell of the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines</hi> <lb/>
            posteritie as his Maiestie: w<ex>i</ex>thout th<unclear>e</unclear>se full subscriptions and <lb/>
            aknowledgm<ex>en</ex>
                <unclear>t</unclear> the graunts wilbe vnfirme / Provided that the <lb/>
            deputies of his highnes shall assemble w<ex>i</ex>th those of the <hi rend="italic">States</hi> in <lb/>
            equall nomber at such tyme and place as the States shall make <lb/>
            choise of and that the tyme and place of Covention vpon conclusion <lb/>
            shalbe appointed likewise by the choise of the States. /
         </p>
         <p>
            This caution is very requisite and conformable consideringe howe <lb/>
            vnfaithfullie som<ex>m</ex>e p<ex>ar</ex>ties haue heeretofore beene dealt w<ex>i</ex>thall in <lb/>
            thier conventions for pacificac<ex>i</ex>ons w<ex>i</ex>th that syde/ . And for theire <lb/>
            further hopes the badd successes that soe manie plotts of bloud in <lb/>
            this o<ex>u</ex>r Adge haue suffered to the Conspirators ruine and the wonder <lb/>
            full deliu<ex>er</ex>ie of those that were conspired against (a manifest <lb/>
            expression of th’almighties wrath and iustice bent against the hands <lb/>
            and harts, and heades of suche inhumaine practizes) shalbe w<ex>i</ex>th the <lb/>
            front terror, foorce <ex>th</ex>e vniu<ex>er</ex>sall world desiste to vndertake the subverc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of State by such vnnaturall deluges, and immoderac<ex>i</ex>ons of bloud. <lb/>
            This for theire further hope, but not securetie, soe longe as loue of <lb/>
            earthlie principallitie preceades the hope of heavenly kingdome <lb/>
            in the Sowle of Man, And yf anie malignant Stratagem be carried <lb/>
            vnder his pretence of peace yf this solide face of goodnes beares <lb/>
            a hollowe harte and badnes of the Myne: I am p<ex>er</ex>swaded is dangerous <lb/>
            not bent vpon anie weake p<ex>ar</ex>ticular. but carried w<ex>i</ex>th a purpose <lb/>
            full of hoepe and probabillitie to worke the ruine and subverc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of the States, soe vnexpected free and almost boundlesse are <lb/>
            his offers and soe deepely in his faith ingaged. Provided That <lb/>
            it shalbe lawfull for the States havinge nowe graunted a <lb/>
            Cessation at Sea as farre as the Gorlings) to holde and to continewe <lb/>
            theire accustomed guardes vpon the Coasts of <hi rend="italic">Flaunders</hi> to <lb/>
            hinder the ingress and egress in to and owt of the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> <lb/>
            Havens. / .
         </p>
         <pb n="108v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f108v/add_ms_11600_f108v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            Howsoeu<ex>er</ex> the States are moued to intertaine the treatie as a worke <lb/>
            pretendinge the reciprocall and mutuall benefitt respectiuelie <lb/>
            of all the <hi rend="italic">Netherland<unclear>es</unclear>sh </hi>provinces on either side yet since it cannot <lb/>
            be denied that Treaties and Cessations may somtimes be rather bent <lb/>
            to a misterious and offensiue and then w<ex>i</ex>th sinceritie to the <lb/>
            pretence, And that a iealousie of such a meaninge maie <lb/>
            produce a multitude of <del rend="strikethrough">ag</del> arguments ro render it excusable <lb/>
            in this particular where theire opposer (in respect of them <lb/>
            is by religion pollicie and nature to bee suspected for an <lb/>
            Enemy rather then loeked for as a freind. It may be therfore <lb/>
            well admitted them to stand vppon their guard how gratious <lb/>
            and conformable soeu<ex>er</ex> his pretences seeme to bee and of the <lb/>
            gen<ex>er</ex>allitie and bodie of theire guarde, this Cawtion is a <lb/>
            limbe, For Treaties that are bent to A misterious end <lb/>
            maie amonge other Aymes tend to the supplies assistances and <lb/>
            intervenc<ex>i</ex>ons of those forraine freeinds and instruments they <lb/>
            want by the way of Free passage granted by cessac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            and prohibited by warre And though the end of Treatie bee <lb/>
            not lymitted in that, For to express my thought the benefitt <lb/>
            of such particular  vnlasting helpes beares noe proporc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th the nature of ouerture) yet since his highnes havinge <lb/>
            noe assurance that the Treatie shall produce a worke to <lb/>
            satisfie the expectac<ex>i</ex>on of his purpose for a peace, and finding <lb/>
            waies layd open to bringe in spplies for warre hee coulde <lb/>
            not haue neglected to make vse of such an opportuntie <lb/>
            as (in the vncertentie of suche a Case) advanceth him <lb/>
            appointment for his better State against the worser yf <lb/>
            the better failes. / . The future danger and preiudice <lb/>
            whereof the better to prevent this caution holdes a guarde <lb/>
            nor could his highnes make a difficultie in accordinge it <lb/>
            provided only for defence, since it should be a kinde of inequallitie <lb/>
            in the cessac<ex>i</ex>on partiallie against the <hi rend="italic">States</hi> to reduce theire <lb/>
            Navie wholie from theire Guards at Sea where they com<ex>m</ex>aunde <lb/>
            in cheife when for the equallitinge of that reducc<ex>i</ex>on on the States <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">behalfe</fw>
            <pb n="109r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f109r/add_ms_11600_f109r.jpg"/>
            behalfe his Highnes havinge no thinge at the Sea of equall force to theires <lb/>
            had not the meanes to make a Conterpoies. / .  <hi rend="italic">Excepted</hi>. /
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">
               The Cessation touchinge Spaine propounded by the Archduke <lb/>
               in his firste offer. /
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            There were noe sence the States should haue subscribed to a cessation <lb/>
            touchinge <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> till <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> had bound it selfe vnto the like for <lb/>
            them and ratefied the <hi rend="italic">Archdukes </hi>declarac<ex>i</ex>on in theire cause a matter <lb/>
            yet in promise onelie, not p<ex>er</ex>formed w<ex>i</ex>thout p<ex>er</ex>formance of the w<ex>hi</ex>ch the p<ex>ro</ex>gress <lb/>
            of the rest goes on in vayne. Besides the States offence vpon the kinge of <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> soe much imports the vnited provinces that nothinge shoulde <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>swade a retracc<ex>i</ex>on of the same but knowledge of some vtilitie that it <lb/>
            would bringe theire State in gen<ex>er</ex>all much lesse to see an acte or twoe of <lb/>
            treatie in a plaie of peace: wherevnto w<ex>i</ex>thout the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines</hi> <lb/>
            accorde to what his <hi rend="italic">highnes </hi>doeth and shall negotiate (an Aggreac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            then dowbted of)  this whole affaier concerninge must <del rend="strikethrough">
                    <unclear/>
                </del>  of necessitie <lb/>
            haue turned / All soildiors w<ex>i</ex>thout theire limitted garrisons and other <lb/>
            inhabitants that shalbe founde in theire contrarie provinces from inioyinge <lb/>
            the freedome of Cessation and shall remayne subiect to the rigor of warre <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout licence expresselie to that ende/. From this exception <lb/>
            Spring<ex>es</ex> a twoe fould vse first. It prevents the danger that the libertie <lb/>
            of intervention betweene twoe states in an affaier of this kingdome <lb/>
            may bringe vnto the syde that hath the greater cause to suspecte the <lb/>
            secrett practices and meaninge of this opposite, For yf offence be meant <lb/>
            and that the Stratagem bee carried by a traitors hand the libertie of <lb/>
            intervenc<ex>i</ex>on shaddowes his passages and gyves him more facilitie <lb/>
            for smoothe convaiances, whereby hee may dispatch his practices <lb/>
            iuste as a <hi rend="italic">Cutt purse</hi> carriers his <hi rend="italic">leger de Main</hi> for the p<ex>er</ex>formance <lb/>
            of the theft more cleanely and securely from detection in a Crowde <lb/>
            then whereby the people are distinguished in their places and <lb/>
            expressed in sight. / . Whereas the prohibition of that libertie <lb/>
            renders the waie more readie to declare the tract of conspirators <lb/>
            proceedings because his stopps are not soe easelie defaced and <lb/>
            hidden  from the Eye in an vnbeaten pathe, asin a trodden waie <lb/>
            frequented by the Concourse of a multitude. / . 
         </p>
         <pb n="109v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f109v/add_ms_11600_f109v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            And nowe his highnes and the States are so deuided and aparte <lb/>
            there cannot pass a noate or signe of Correspondence vnsuspected <lb/>
            even by comon sence/ . Secondly it holdes there guardes <lb/>
            and frontiers more conteyned and vigelant, whereas the <lb/>
            libertie of intervention would haue bredd secureties dissoluc<ex>i</ex>on/. <lb/>
            And though the Surface of this exception seem<unclear>s</unclear> to regarde <lb/>
            respectiuely aswell his <hi rend="italic">highnes</hi> as the <hi rend="italic">States</hi>. Yet it in the <lb/>
            vse it gyues the more peculier inclinac<ex>i</ex>on to the States not <lb/>
            that the instituc<ex>i</ex>on is guiltie of partiallitie but in a due and <lb/>
            iust regard particularlie to the safetie of theire State, by <lb/>
            reason they haue more cause then his <hi rend="italic">highnes</hi> to make <lb/>
            vse of suche preventions and preservatiues/ .
         </p>
         <p>
            That w<ex>i</ex>thin sixe weeks after the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines </hi>aggreac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            aforesaid bee deliuered vnto the States they will recall <lb/>
            theire Fleete of Warre from <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> and that duringe <lb/>
            the tyme limitted for that deliu<ex>er</ex>ie they will not reenforce <lb/>
            theire present Fleete vppon the Coasts of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            In these graunts togeather w<ex>i</ex>th the excepted propositions <lb/>
            made by his <hi rend="italic">highnes </hi>in his first offer tendinge to this ende <lb/>
            it may be noted howe affectiuelie his highnes prosecutes <lb/>
            the retraction of the States offence from <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> and w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            such earnestnes as yf it seemed to pointe at somthinge movinge <lb/>
            at that Warre w<ex>hi</ex>ch ioyned w<ex>i</ex>th other motives) hath aduised <lb/>
            this ouerture. / . True it is the States proiected Warre <lb/>
            nowe readie to be sett on foete against the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine <lb/>
            </hi>imports his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie to labour the prevention of the same because <lb/>
            it is bent against his <hi rend="italic">Indians </hi>and other parts of the <lb/>
            principall supporters of his State, And even to the <lb/>
            nature and extent of his <hi rend="italic">highnes</hi> offer, for sodainenes <lb/>
            and amplitude agrees soe well in tyme and measure <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th the birth and dimentions of that the States designe; as it <lb/>
            deserves a voice in the Coniecturable  reasons that <lb/>
            haue moued this treatie for a peace. /
         </p>
         <pb n="110r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f110r/add_ms_11600_f110r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            But now this noted affection that his <hi rend="italic">highnes </hi>seemes to beare the retraction <lb/>
            of that warre, maie minister occasion of twoe questions. first, whether <lb/>
            when the <hi rend="italic">States </hi>haue drawen theire warre from thence and duringe <lb/>
            the suspence of theire hostilitie his Ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s defecte of present strength <lb/>
            in Coll<unclear>or</unclear>es Guarrisons fortiffications shipping and other necessaries <lb/>
            pertinent to the resistance of the States proiected warre against him <lb/>
            in his Coast<ex>es</ex> and Seas of <hi rend="italic">America</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Africa</hi> (yf that be anie <lb/>
            motiue in this ouerture) maie be supplied. the second wheather <lb/>
            duringe this Cessation theie his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie securelie bringinge home <lb/>
            his Treasure maie not furnishe the lowe Countrie warre w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            a supplie of monie (yf want thereof be likewise anie motiue in <lb/>
            this ouerture) and soe when theise effectuall points are fortefied <lb/>
            make an Evasion from the peace vnto the disadvantage of the States <lb/>
            And that the rather since the libertie and lawfullnes to make excepc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            to some pointe propounded in the Treatie maie when the cessac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            is extended to the fullnes of tyme to satisfie that purpose shaddowe <lb/>
            a misterious evation w<ex>i</ex>thout discreaditinge the protestac<ex>i</ex>on of <lb/>
            sinceritie / To these I answeare theise. .i  the offer of the peace <lb/>
            pretendinge suche a large conformitie and seeminge in the sup<ex>er</ex>ficies <lb/>
            soe reasonable. The States could not well haue refused to <lb/>
            treate w<ex>i</ex>thout incurringe an vniu<ex>er</ex>sall imputac<ex>i</ex>on of pervesnes <lb/>
            and pride: To treate weare vaine ww<ex>i</ex>thout the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines <lb/>
            </hi>accorde because he is the principall pretender ou<ex>er</ex> them The kinge <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">Spaynes </hi>accord would questionles haue beene denied w<ex>i</ex>thout <lb/>
            Cessation graunted by the States, aswell for him in Spaine as <lb/>
            for his highnes in the <hi rend="italic">Netherlands.</hi> Soe that it followeth almost <lb/>
            of necessitie, the States must graunte vpon some Condic<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            the revocation of theire warre from <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>. 2 The verie <lb/>
            name of an attempt of sound found acc<ex>i</ex>on and a well compacted <lb/>
            frame suche as is this designe of the States as will appeare <lb/>
            where I approche more pertinentlie to the pointe, directed <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th an ayme against the <hi rend="italic">Indians </hi>and such partes whereon the
            <pb n="110v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f110v/add_ms_11600_f110v.jpg"/>
            mightines of <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>consist<ex>es</ex>, and w<ex>hi</ex>ch hee cannot be depriued of <lb/>
            but his State muste of necessitie growe weake and humble <lb/>
            beares such a terror on the fronte, that beinge alreadie apprehended <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th feare. noe reinforcement or supplie that such a litle tyme <lb/>
            canne furnishe him w<ex>i</ex>thall wilbe soe full and compleate, as to <lb/>
            make him confident in his abillitie to master it by force, but <lb/>
            still there will remayne, in suche a waightie and important <lb/>
            cause some diffedence and dowbt of an assured habillitie <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch will p<ex>er</ex>swade him rather to divert then stand the hazard of the <lb/>
            Checke, the rather since the interprise is in the subiect vnex=<lb break="no"/>
            ampled and nothinge of experience drawen from action doeth <lb/>
            present itselfe to Councell or instruct the managinge of the <lb/>
            defence  3. Suche supplie as this Cessac<ex>i</ex>on maie advaunce <lb/>
            the Archdukes warre, can bee but temporarie, farr from a <lb/>
            sufficiencie to wage the tyme required for conquest of soe <lb/>
            stronge a scituac<ex>i</ex>on as the vnited provinces w<ex>hi</ex>ch are by nature <lb/>
            soe defensible that Com<ex>m</ex>on industrie maie easelie prevent <lb/>
            theire sudden subuertion and muste by woen  by peeces <lb/>
            when soeu<ex>er</ex> warre attempt<ex>es</ex> w<ex>i</ex>th meanes to conquer them, and <lb/>
            then consideringe the refuges as well contingent as domestique <lb/>
            of the vnited provinces., I am p<ex>er</ex>swaded that the Archedukes warre <lb/>
            howsoeu<ex>er</ex> such a tyme maie furnish him w<ex>i</ex>th p<ex>re</ex>sent reinforcem<ex>en</ex>t <lb/>
            or supplie shall notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge fall into the form<ex>er</ex> state of <lb/>
            want, when warre block<ex>es</ex> vpp theire passages againe, Soe <lb/>
            that this ou<ex>er</ex>ture extends itselfe (in my opinion) to a farther <lb/>
            ende thatt that, and is to large to limitt her purposed <lb/>
            expectac<ex>i</ex>on in soe smale an vse./  4. Since <ex>th</ex>e revocation <lb/>
            shall not be made vntill the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>hath ratefied <lb/>
            the Archdukes declarac<ex>i</ex>on, w<ex>hi</ex>ch extends even to the freenes <lb/>
            of theire State. the damage of the States will not be verie <lb/>
            greate in that exchange conceyvinge that for the credditt
            <pb n="111r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f111r/add_ms_11600_f111r.jpg"/>
            and assistance of theire cause that declarac<ex>i</ex>on will advance more benefitt <lb/>
            then anie suche p<ex>ar</ex>ticular supplie as either that of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>  w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            tendes more properlie and but vncertainlie and weakelie to defend <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> <lb/>
            then hurte the States or that belonginge to his highnes for the waginge <lb/>
            of the war<del rend="strikethrough">
                    <unclear/> </del>in the lowe countries w<ex>hi</ex>ch cannot take awaie the cause of <lb/>
            his defects but onlie sett a little temporarie florish on his sworde <lb/>
            can disadvantage them, And to provid the better against the <lb/>
            vncertaine yssues of this temporisinge busines The States haue <lb/>
            the wisdome to containe the constituc<ex>i</ex>on and the ba<unclear>n</unclear>ke of that <lb/>
            theire worthie proiect bent against the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>whole <lb/>
            and entire, and not onlie vndissolued but growinge (also and <lb/>
            increasinge in appointm<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> and habillities to the ende that yf the treatie <lb/>
            bringe noe resoluc<ex>i</ex>on  forthe for peace they may bee readie and <lb/>
            prepared to vse the first occasion season and oportunitie for warre
         </p>
         <p>
            That the States duringe the cessac<ex>i</ex>on will suffer the smale <lb/>
            fisherie of the Archedukes havens to labour in and w<ex>i</ex>thout <lb/>
            molestac<ex>i</ex>on  /
         </p>
         <p>
            This graunte maie serue to gyve the world to vnderstande that <lb/>
            whatsoeu<ex>er</ex> they refuse to graunt imports some danger to theire <lb/>
            State and that theire affections are conformable and readie to <lb/>
            admitt the mutuall benefitt of all the <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes</hi> aswell <lb/>
            of those subiected to his highnes as of theese subsistinge w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            them selues soe farre as maie be yealded not endangeringe <lb/>
            the publique saftie of thire owne: /
         </p>
         <p>
            My coniectures <lb/>
            What reasons there are that either doe or ought to moue the Archeduk <lb/>
            inclinac<ex>i</ex>on to a peace and what to bringe the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaynes <lb/>
            </hi>accorde. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            To moue his highnes the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> intent to peace these reasons <lb/>
            maye in my coniecture bee conceiued. / .
         </p>
         <pb n="111v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f111v/add_ms_11600_f111v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            1	hee hath litle or noe probabillitie to reduce the States into the Armes <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> by force 
         </p>
         <p>
            2	hee hath some cause of <del rend="strikethrough">force</del> feare to loose by the continewance <lb/>
            of warre not onelie his hoepe of winninge all but even this <lb/>
            present interest alsoe in anie of the <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi>.	
         </p>
         <p>
            3	hee hath greate reason to continewe his present estate in <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes</hi>. yf not by warre by peace. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            And to bringe the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaines </hi>accorde ther may be coniec <lb/>
            tured the considerac<ex>i</ex>on of the Archedukes twoe first motyues
         </p>
         <p>
            The continewance of the warres threatens the deprivac<ex>i</ex>on of <lb/>
            his Ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ies</ex> best p<ex>ar</ex>ticulers where on the pride and greatnes of <lb/>
            his power consists and further the hasars of his principallitie
         </p>
         <p>
            Of all these heades I will discourse in order as they followe. <lb/>
            Touchinge the Archedukes first motiue. That hee hath <lb/>
            litlr or no<del rend="strikethrough">thinge</del> probabillitie to reduce the States into <lb/>
            the Armes of Spaine by foorce will appeare by comparing <lb/>
            theire seu<ex>er</ex>all estates aswell in the domestique constituc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of the <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi> as alsoe in the apect<ex>es</ex> of theire contingents <lb/>
            and assistancs. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            In the domestique constituc<ex>i</ex>on of the Netherlands are to be <lb/>
            compared as necessarie materialls. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            1	The habillities of theire com<ex>m</ex>on wealthes to sustaine Warre.
         </p>
         <p>
            2	The affections of theire Subiect<ex>es</ex> to contribute vnto the Warre.
         </p>
         <p>
            3	Theire power to impose taxes on theire Subiects.
         </p>
         <p>
            4.	The naturall strength of theire Scituations
         </p>
         <p>
            5	The fortifficac<ex>i</ex>ons and other warlike appointm<ex>en</ex>ts out of <lb/>
            power and industrie to hold the naturall advantages <lb/>
            of Seate. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            And in the Aspects of theire contingents and assistancs. <lb/>
            The p<ex>ar</ex>ticular addic<ex>i</ex>ons or supplies that the defects or powers <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thin the proper and domestique constituc<ex>i</ex>on of theire <lb/>
            states shall receyue. / .
         </p>
         <pb n="112r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f112r/add_ms_11600_f112r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            First touchinge the abillities of theire com<ex>m</ex>on wealthes. His Highnes pro=<lb break="no"/>
            vinces are not soe able as those of the States to contribute vnto the Warre <lb/>
            howsoeu<ex>er</ex> the Archedukes Army may beare a while the more florished <lb/>
            Ensigne, the States com<ex>m</ex>on wealth, (notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge) though but the <lb/>
            defendant partie shall carrie the more easie burthen of the greifes <lb/>
            and miseries of warre, because theire traffique the life blood of theire <lb/>
            boedie pollitique. Whereon theire people for the most p<ex>ar</ex>te consiste <lb/>
            hath verie free and open entercourse and passage beeinge but a litle <lb/>
            subiect to obstruction and impeachem<ex>en</ex>t, still increasinge the <lb/>
            measure of theire Stocks. / .  Whereas the Archedukes provinces <lb/>
            depriued of theire libertie at Sea by the Strength of the States Navie <lb/>
            produce but litle other profits of them selues then what the lande <lb/>
            bring<ex>es</ex> forth. And blessings of the land, are by a land warre <lb/>
            continewallie suppressed and trodden <del rend="strikethrough">downe</del> on <del rend="strikethrough">disorders of this</del> <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">warres</del> and in his prouinc<ex>es</ex> the more because the loese disorders of <lb/>
            his warre are curbd but w<ex>i</ex>th a loese an easie reyne where <lb/>
            miserie is more, habillitie is lesse. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Conserninge the willingnes of the Subiect<ex>es</ex>. /
         </p>
         <p>
            The Subiects of his highnes are not soe willinge as those of the <lb/>
            States to contribute vnto the Warre. /
         </p>
         <p>
            The Marchants of the Vnited provin<ex>es</ex> incorporated in there Townes <lb/>
            whose traffique is increased by blockinge vpp the convenient <lb/>
            hauens and portes of marte in his <hi rend="italic">highnes</hi> side, will in affecc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            to theire Townes vfould theire ssubstanc<ex>es</ex> assistantlie and <lb/>
            amplie for the Warre because the Warre augments the <lb/>
            benefitt of theire p<ex>ar</ex>ticular. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Whereas his <hi rend="italic">highnes </hi>provinces beinge w<ex>i</ex>thin the Freedome of com<ex>m</ex>erce <lb/>
            for the inlargem<ex>en</ex>t whereof they haue hetherto the more willingly <lb/>
            imp<ex>ar</ex>ted to the warre, Nowe since theire hopes to recou<ex>er</ex> it, <lb/>
            by warre, are become discouraged theire willingnes growes <lb/>
            (likewise wearie to sustaine the warre, w<ex>hi</ex>ch ia a heauie <lb/>
            burthen of a light importance in respecte of theire <lb/>
            desires. / .
         </p>
         <pb n="112v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f112v/add_ms_11600_f112v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            Theire hopes to recou<ex>er</ex> theire com<ex>m</ex>erce by force and practizes of enmitie <lb/>
            are discouraged by the interception of twoe passages of hostillitie<del rend="strikethrough">s <lb/>
            </del>vpon the ends whereof theire warlike hoopes to prosper were <lb/>
            erected. /
         </p>
         <p>
            1	In that theire ou<ex>er</ex>ture of <hi rend="italic">Ostend</hi>, (whereon there hoepes were highlie <lb/>
            raised as on a worke promisinge them much libertie) is frustrate <lb/>
            in effect of theire losse of <hi rend="italic">Sluice</hi> and the dependancs. And <lb/>
            then to add vnto that sence of theire debillitie theire purchase <lb/>
            of experience bought vpon <hi rend="italic">Ostend</hi> maie w<ex>i</ex>th good reason <lb/>
            discourage the consception of such an other enterprise <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch after it hath spent them much tymes bloud and treasure <lb/>
            for an vncertaine successe besides the hinderancs and wants <lb/>
            that will begett in other actions and defencs maie accidentallie <lb/>
            be frustrated of the propounded vse by either opposers <lb/>
            footinge and confrontm<ex>en</ex>t in some other place of like importance /
         </p>
         <p>
            2	Whereas his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> and his highnes the Archedukes <lb/>
            had about the tyme of Queene Elizabeths death published <lb/>
            an edict conteininge certeine pollitique incitem<ex>en</ex>ts and <lb/>
            inductions to invite and drawe awaie the M<ex>er</ex>chants and <lb/>
            other substanciall inha<ex>b</ex>itants of the vnited prouincs from thence <lb/>
            to theire dominions w<ex>hi</ex>ch was a practize threateninge <lb/>
            dissoluc<ex>i</ex>on to the State pollitique of the vnited provincs <lb/>
            because, besides inductions of encouragem<ex>en</ex>t it seem’d to <lb/>
            importe some matter of necessitie as an express p<ex>ro</ex>hibic<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            against all of the vnited provincs to make anie traffique <lb/>
            into theire dominions directlie or indirectlie vnder paine <lb/>
            to be whollie made prize of besides the waight of <lb/>
            manie other greevious penalties, vnless they first w<ex>i</ex>thdrewe <lb/>
            theire contribuc<ex>i</ex>on customes and obedience from the States <lb/>
            and the execution of this edict must necessarilie haue <lb/>
            turn’d to the damage of the States Marchants soe longe <lb/>
            as they weare to trade diuided, and a partie: And con=<lb break="no"/>
            sequentlie had not a publique remedie b<add place="above">en</add>e provided) haue <lb/>
            <pb n="113r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f113r/add_ms_11600_f113r.jpg"/>
            moved and stirred vp dangerous contractions provatelie for change, the hope <lb/>
            of this practise is likewise disanimated by a Counter act of the States <lb/>
            providinge for theire Marchants defence in driuinge theire commerce w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            confirmed theire continewance to the States side w<ex>i</ex>th bonds of benefitt that <lb/>
            weaued and knitt the comon cause of the vnited prouincs togeather w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            the Marchants p<ex>ar</ex>ticuler into one peece and worke. ./.
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               The new com <lb/>
               pany of Mer <lb/>
               chants erected <lb/>
               by the States to <lb/>
               open <ex>th</ex>e traffique <lb/>
               into <ex>th</ex>e West <lb/>
               Indeas
            </add>
            The Subiects (therefore) of the Archeduks maritine territories seeinge <lb/>
            themselues continewallie locked vpp when to theire memories and eies <lb/>
            the wealthes and blessings of theire form<ex>er</ex> libertie togeather w<ex>i</ex>th a p<ex>re</ex>sentac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of the free and prosperous traffique of the vnited provincs, appeare	 <lb/>
            and findinge that peace and nothinge but peace is likelie to repaier <lb/>
            theire ruines and dilapidac<ex>i</ex>ons wherew<ex>i</ex>th the buildings of the Vnited <lb/>
            provincs are raisde the pleasinge and attractiue obiect of a florishing <lb/>
            and wealthie State conferrs theire respects vnto the causes that effect <lb/>
            the same, and theire desires in a thinge soe plentifull of benefitt <lb/>
            and good importance to the State and com<ex>m</ex>on wealth whereon they <lb/>
            lyue cannot but mooue the Archeduks harte in theire behalfe.
         </p>
         <p>
            3	Of theire powers to impose on the Subiect. / .	 <lb/>
            His highnes cannot impose of a Taxe soe safelie as the States.
         </p>
         <p>
               1	Because the States are naturall people of the Countries they <lb/>
            gou<ex>er</ex>ne, his highnes to his a stranger. /.
         </p>
         <p>
               2	The States people will rather beare and endure anie other tollerable <lb/>
            gou<ex>er</ex>m<ex>en</ex>t then be retorned into the Armes of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> because the <lb/>
            insolence and cruelties of <hi rend="italic">Spaynes </hi>Vice gerents haue impressed <lb/>
            in them (almoste) an irreconcilliable hate towards the <hi rend="italic">Spanishe <lb/>
            </hi>predominance. / .   
         </p>
         <p>
               3	The opinion of a people is better p<ex>er</ex>swaded of a taxe imposed by <lb/>
            an <hi rend="italic">Aristocrate</hi> whose correspondent quallitie doeth make it seeme <lb/>
            more interressed ingaged and affected for the com<ex>m</ex>on benefitt, then by <lb/>
            a prince, the highnes and transcendance of whose place more <lb/>
            distant from familliar popularitie begetts construcc<ex>i</ex>on, That a <lb/>
            Taxe imposed by him exhausts and exacts theire tribute rather <lb/>
            to maintaine the formall pride of Courtlines and State, then anie <lb/>
            necessarie seruice tendinge to the com<ex>m</ex>on good. /.
            <pb n="113v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f113v/add_ms_11600_f113v.jpg"/>
            The best and cheefest of the vnited provincs are of soe broken a <lb/>
            Cituac<ex>i</ex>on and interceptable passages that yf theire people in <lb/>
            theire discontentm<ex>en</ex>ts should commove, theire Comotion maie <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th litle difficultie be prevented rowted and suppressed <lb/>
            before the increase of nomber growe to anie dangerous <lb/>
            head and w<ex>i</ex>th the more facillitie and assurance, since <lb/>
            the greater p<ex>ar</ex>te of theire people consistinge vpon trade <lb/>
            Contented, because theire libertie to driue the husbandmen <lb/>
            Courses they professe gyves them increase of meanes to <lb/>
            liue mixte w<ex>i</ex>th the discontented and strongly seated on the <lb/>
            passag<ex>es</ex>, doe serve for guardes vpon the States advantages <lb/>
            of Seate to hold the discontented Subiect in deuotion to <lb/>
            the State. . /.
         </p>
         <p>
            Whereas the Archedukes provincs are for the moste p<ex>ar</ex>te <lb/>
            Champion w<ex>hi</ex>ch admitts much more ease to gather heade <lb/>
            and w<ex>i</ex>th temptac<ex>i</ex>on, since the cheefest Subiect<ex>es</ex> by reason <lb/>
            theire Subiection to his warre continewes the inlargem<ex>en</ex>t <lb/>
            of theire Comon benefitt (Comerce) imprisoned (as it were) <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thin the States offenciue circumventinge power at sea <lb/>
            are possessed w<ex>i</ex>th motiues vrginge them to discontent. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            And lastlie to confirme the constituc<ex>i</ex>on of the States <lb/>
            power to impose vpon the Subiect, and to dishable his <lb/>
            highnesses w<ex>i</ex>th dangerous infirmitie, The generall <lb/>
            obedience of the States Armie is intire and sounde, whereas <lb/>
            his highnesses is very seldome vndeuided but possessed <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th mutinies. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            			Of the nature of theire Scituations <lb/>
            4	His <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi>  proving are in the nature of theire scituac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            lesse defensible then those of the States first because the <lb/>
            best of the vnited provincs are floudes his highnesses <lb/>
            Champion. Floud<ex>es</ex> and broken water Lands are in theire <lb/>
            natures lesse accessable and passable then champion groundes
            <pb n="114r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f114r/add_ms_11600_f114r.jpg"/>
            and being guarded by an apt industrious inhabitant provided of such aunswerable <lb/>
            appointm<ex>en</ex>ts as the States (aswell by Sea as land) are furnished w<ex>i</ex>th an <lb/>
            opposite lande warre shall haue litle proceedinge admitted vpon them <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout greate daunger to be interupted and circumvented. / .
         </p>
         <p>
               2	The Stat<ex>es</ex> possesse convenient seates of Strength vpon the best of the <lb/>
            Archeduk<ex>es</ex> provinc<ex>es</ex>, w<ex>hi</ex>ch serue not onlie as a rampier of defence to <lb/>
            holde the vnited provinces in good securetie  w<ex>i</ex>thin them selues but alsoe <lb/>
            as a doer to gyve the States an open easie waie of entrance and <lb/>
            accesse vpon his <hi rend="italic">Highness</hi> yf occasion gyves them purpose to invade. /
         </p>
         <p>
               3	To add facillitie to all the <hi rend="italic">States</hi>. Proceedinges in theire acc<ex>i</ex>ons <lb/>
            of theire warres and to his <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi> impediment there scituac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            gyves them more dexteritie an actiue quallitie of verie mother <lb/>
            vse in warre. To leade an expedic<ex>i</ex>on of defence or enterprice <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th readines and speede from place to place, then cann his <hi rend="italic">Highnesses <lb/>
            </hi> afforde and w<ex>i</ex>th a lesser chardge: For land wherein his highnes is <lb/>
            almost confinde admitts not transportac<ex>i</ex>on w<ex>i</ex>th soe easie chardge <lb/>
            and motion as the water w<ex>hi</ex>ch the States comaunde. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Lastlie in the proper and domestique constituc<ex>i</ex>on of the <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi> <lb/>
            and concerninge theire appointm<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>  for theire holdinge of theire <lb/>
            growndes appointm<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> besides the habillities alreadie spoken of <lb/>
            deuide them selues accordinge to the different nature of the scituac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            into the fortifficac<ex>i</ex>onss w<ex>i</ex>th the dependices vpon the lande Shippinge <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th provition at Sea, and men to gouerne and mannage boethe. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            Touchinge Fortifficac<ex>i</ex>on w<ex>i</ex>th the peculiar requisite appointm<ex>en</ex>ts on <lb/>
            the lande neither side discou<ex>er</ex>s wwant, but on the Sea the Navie of <lb/>
            the States is cheefelie Stronge a power aboue his <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi>, <lb/>
            aswell invasiue as defensiue as the quallitie of theire warre <lb/>
            shall leade. /.  Thus farre it seemes to me that the domestique <lb/>
            Constituc<ex>i</ex>on of the vnited provinc<ex>es</ex> is more defensible, able, <lb/>
            willinge Subiect and confident to sustaine the warre then his <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Highnesses </hi>only exceptinge that there yet remaines one necessarie <lb/>
            vndiscourste<hi rend="italic"> </hi>wherein his highenesse exceades the States <lb/>
            proprietie in Strength. . . <lb/>
            					<hi rend="italic">Namelie Menn.</hi>
            <pb n="114v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f114v/add_ms_11600_f114v.jpg"/>
            It cannot be denied (indeed) that his <hi rend="italic">Highnesses </hi>meanes to raise supplies <lb/>
            of mercenary menn consistinge cheefelie of <hi rend="italic">Wallones</hi>. A <lb/>
            nation warlike populous and borne in his Territories <lb/>
            are properlie more seruiceable plentifull and readie <lb/>
            then the States abillities. for that respect in theire domestique <lb/>
            State whose <hi rend="italic">Ilanders</hi> whereof theire cheefest populac<ex>i</ex>ons <lb/>
            doe consiste though a populous ciuillitie affordes not <lb/>
            suche a multiplicitie of mercinarie nombers not a people <lb/>
            soe disposed and actiue in the ordinarie seruice of the lande <lb/>
            warre. Howe eu<ex>er</ex> pregnant, provident industrious prudent <lb/>
            Councellors But for the seruice of the Sea the States are <lb/>
            well provided in them selues because the Ilanders of the <lb/>
            vnited provinc<ex>es</ex> are euen by nature besides there practise <lb/>
            verie apt for water workes. / . And to supplie theire want <lb/>
            of souildiors for the lande it will appeare they may bee <lb/>
            furnished from the neighbour<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> kingdomes sufficientlie to <lb/>
            make them hable to confront. / . But ere I enter <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th theire forraine powers I will sett downe vppon <lb/>
            the foete of this discourse concerninge the domestique <lb/>
            constituc<ex>i</ex>ons of theire States, my estimac<ex>i</ex>on of theire Wants <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thin them selues to th’ende the vse of theire forraine <lb/>
            powers maie the better be expressed. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            From my obseruac<ex>i</ex>on made vpon theire seu<ex>er</ex>all domestique <lb/>
            powers. I finde theire want<ex>es</ex> compared as followeth. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            The wants of his <hi rend="italic">Highnes</hi>: is. first Shippinge  2 some men  3 money <lb/>
            The wants of the <hi rend="italic">States</hi>: is first more men. 2 some money <lb/>
            Concerninge those defect<ex>es</ex> the aspects of theire contingent<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            and assistanc<ex>es</ex> expresse themselues thus. / . <lb/>
            For his <hi rend="italic">Highnes </hi>wante of Shipinge hee hathe no p<ex>ro</ex>babillitie <lb/>
            to bee supplied. Hee hath noe other assistance for supplie <lb/>
            then <hi rend="italic">Spayne. </hi>yf <hi rend="italic">Spayne </hi>should attempt an invation of <lb/>
            the States provincesd. his convenient preparac<ex>i</ex>ons by <lb/>
            reason his ordinarie Navie is of an vnnavigable buildinge
            <pb n="115r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f115r/add_ms_11600_f115r.jpg"/>
            for the lowe Countries seas his marriners <del rend="strikethrough">his</del> discontinewed and inexpert in <lb/>
            theire channells and his distance verie remote would gyue the States <lb/>
            sufficient tyme to make them selues appointed to defende. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Besides yf the scituac<ex>i</ex>on of the vnited provinc<ex>es</ex> be well obserued it will <lb/>
              appeare that by reason the broekennes of the land<ex>es</ex> guarded by a Sea <lb/>
            power maie circumvent a landed enemie and soe depriuinge him <lb/>
            of releife either distroy or force him to compounde and quite his <lb/>
            enterprise, to invade them therefore, will in moste places be to <lb/>
            smale purpose except theire power at Sea be first ou<ex>er</ex>come. /. 
         </p>
         <p>
            And to prevent theire defeate at Sea theire Sea power vnited (w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th good obseruac<ex>i</ex>ons anf industrie maie be p<ex>er</ex>formed before <hi rend="italic">Spayne <lb/>
            </hi>cann attempt) is vallued verie sufficient to resiste yf not to beate <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">Spanish</hi> Nauie and to confirme that power to them, theire <lb/>
            Navigation will continewe and preserue theire Nauie in her <lb/>
            present strength yea and increase her foerce. / .
         </p>
         <p>
               2	As for men the States meanes to raise supplies of warlike strange<add place="above">rs</add> <lb/>
            exceedes his <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi> sufficientlie to make theire Armie <lb/>
            hable to confronte: the Archedukes cheefe supplies of men <lb/>
            besides his lowe Duche and <hi rend="italic">Wallones</hi> whereof the States exceedes <lb/>
            in one his Highnes in the other are compos’d of <hi rend="italic">Spaniards Italians <lb/>
            English French </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Almans </hi>and cheefe of those States consiste <lb/>
            cheefelie of greate <hi rend="italic">Brittaynes</hi> french and <hi rend="italic">Almans</hi>. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            The <hi rend="italic">Archedukes Spaniardes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Italians </hi>add somthinge to his <lb/>
            fortes and holdes not much vnto his seruice for the feild by <lb/>
            reason the longe and difficult waie of transportac<ex>i</ex>on besides <lb/>
            some other reasons that disapt them for the feild will render theire <lb/>
            supplies w<ex>i</ex>th an excessiue chardge vntimelie and vncertaine <lb/>
            for the requisite appoibtm<ex>en</ex>t of his Warre. /
         </p>
         <p>
            Of greate <hi rend="italic">Brittaines </hi>howsoeu<ex>er</ex> the comon inclinac<ex>i</ex>on (as it appeare<add place="above">d</add> <lb/>
            in all changes after noueltie drewe a greate concourse in the <lb/>
            begininge of Englands peace to the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>side yet nowe <lb/>
            that humor beinge satisfied the course is lesse affectedlie pursued <lb/>
            and muche the lesse for three other reasons restraininge the same.
         </p>
         <pb n="115v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f115v/add_ms_11600_f115v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            1	The greatest popular p<ex>ar</ex>te of England is more affected to the <lb/>
            States by reason of the conformance in religion different <lb/>
            from his Highnesses.
         </p>
         <p>
            2	That p<ex>ar</ex>te w<ex>hi</ex>ch because of Suspic<ex>i</ex>on is more affected to his Highnes <lb/>
            restraine them selues notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge of theire passage to <lb/>
            his side by theire vnwillingnes to subscribe to those good <lb/>
            lawes of reseruac<ex>i</ex>on necessarilie prouided to prevent <lb/>
            suche daungers as might otherwise ensue to the state of <lb/>
            England by theire vnexamined libertie in that course.
         </p>
         <p>
            3	Suche as are Newtralls in affecc<ex>i</ex>on by reason of his <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Highness </hi>difficultie and dangerous transportac<ex>i</ex>ons more <lb/>
            easelie converted to the State, whose passages are more <lb/>
            prepared and free /.
         </p>
         <p>
            From <hi rend="italic">Fraunce </hi>the States alliance w<ex>i</ex>th that Nation is first <lb/>
            by consanguinitie  2 by comerce  3 in that the States pros <lb/>
            peritie in this warre importes that kingdomes good. <lb/>
            Attracts the greater concourse to their side. And lastlie <lb/>
            touchinge Almaines they are comon to either side and <lb/>
            verie seruiceable./. Thus by the differences of theire <lb/>
            forraine helpes the States (it appeares) haue sufficient <lb/>
            meanes to supplie theire owne difitiencie of men<ex>n</ex>.
         </p>
         <p>
            Tis true the States these twoe yeares past haue suffered <lb/>
            losse but rather by some other causes then the want of men <lb/>
            Certaine it is p<ex>ar</ex>te of that losse <del rend="strikethrough">t</del>hath fallen vppon them by other <lb/>
            kindes of vnsufficiencie though theire Armie I graunte <lb/>
            hath beene in nomber some what lesse. yf that inequallitie <lb/>
            and disproportion be supposed a cause whereby they <lb/>
            lost I cann affirme it comes not by theire want of <lb/>
            possibillitie to levie men<ex>n</ex>. For touchinge English I haue <lb/>
            obserued that yf the States had gyven more large comission <lb/>
            for there English levies the tymes well chosen places of residence
            <pb n="116r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f116r/add_ms_11600_f116r.jpg"/>
            for officers of levie convenientlie disposed and one of vnderstandinge <lb/>
            for the gen<ex>er</ex>allitie to gou<ex>er</ex>ne the p<ex>ar</ex>ticulars would haue increased the <lb/>
            nomber of theire list to dowble that they raised. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            It maie be likewise soe in other p<ex>ar</ex>tes. And by the bearinge of theire acc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            it seems to me that whie theire Armie exceeded not in nomber, <lb/>
            was rather owt of industrie then necessitie. And w<ex>hi</ex>ch is more <lb/>
            howsoeu<ex>er</ex> the Archeduke conceyuinge this Newtrallitie of England <lb/>
            to be his best occasion tyme and opportunitie wherein he canne <lb/>
            make triall of his foerce hath stretched his vttermost to bringe <lb/>
            a gallant Armie and an offensiue warre into the feild.  And <lb/>
            that the States extendinge not theire industrie soe farre as <lb/>
            possibillitie helde onelie a defensiue Armie some what lesse <lb/>
            in nomber then  his. yet when the disposic<ex>i</ex>on of the States <lb/>
            Armie aswell for order as for resoluc<ex>i</ex>on shalbe waighed, it <lb/>
            maye be thought that had the States beene pleased to haue <lb/>
            expressed themselues more actiuelie vpon some tymelie offers <lb/>
            of advantages and opportunities that did present themselues <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">more actiuelie vpon some tymelie offers of advantages</del> theire <lb/>
            greate losse had beene prevented yet noe dowbt theire <lb/>
            wisdomes carried theire affaires w<ex>i</ex>th provident respect to some more <lb/>
            worthie, necessarie end concerninge theire estate in gen<ex>er</ex>all then is <add place="above">the hassard of</add> A <lb/>
            Generall, for savinge a p<ex>ar</ex>ticular howeu<ex>er</ex> yf the enterprise had com<ex>m</ex>e <lb/>
            to triall the event might happely haue approued the bodie of <lb/>
            theire Armie free from an essentiall weakenes to confront or fight./.   
         </p>
         <p>
            Touchinge money howsoeu<ex>er</ex> his highnes setts some tymes a gouldene <lb/>
            flourish on his sworde yet the uncertentie of his revenewe to <lb/>
            maintaine the same sufferinge the lustre nowe and then to fade <lb/>
            and weare awaie the rust and cancker of it selfe duringe the want <lb/>
            of the preservative, will eate as <add place="above">farr</add>  into his edge as his edge did cutt <lb/>
            before into the States. ./.  His necessarie supplies of money unp<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            formeable owt of his proper revenewe beinge p<ex>re</ex>sum’d vppon <lb/>
            the helpe of <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi> his trust to that assistance stands w<ex>i</ex>th perrell <lb/>
            and uncertantie since <hi rend="italic">Spayne </hi>it selfe by reason of the manie <lb/>
            Garrisons it houldes is often vnfurnished to gyue towardes A
            <pb n="116v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f116v/add_ms_11600_f116v.jpg"/>
            forraine expence and soe remote in seate that a supplie from <lb/>
            thence maye come vntimelie to prevent the dangerous incon <lb/>
            veniences exemplified in mutines begott by want, besides <lb/>
            the hassard that muste vndergoe to bee cut of by the watch <lb/>
            of the States at sea. / . Nowe for the States supplies <lb/>
            of money as his highnes is supported by <hi rend="italic">Spayne </hi>soe one <lb/>
            or other deepely interessed in the States successe will <lb/>
            vnderpropp yf not protect them out of provident aduise <lb/>
            to prevent theire fall on whose subsistance the saftie of <lb/>
            his owne p<ex>ar</ex>ticular in some respects, depends. /.  And though <lb/>
            theire forraine helpes in that be lesse then are his <hi rend="italic">highnesses</hi> <lb/>
            Yett maie there wants receyue as full supplie because <lb/>
            theire owne habilitie is more then his proprietie in that. / <lb/>
            Besides theire vnderhand helpes by reason of theire neerenes <lb/>
            and more sure conveyance will in effect holde ballance <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th his highnes professed assistanc<ex>es</ex> since his are somtimes <lb/>
            vnable allwaies vncertaine seldome competent. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Moreou<ex>er</ex> the States haue yet a refuge more then hath his <lb/>
            Highnes, for they haue taken litle of theire countrie to <lb/>
            sustaine the warre more then the com<ex>m</ex>on disposic<ex>i</ex>on of <lb/>
            obedience hath imparted as an ordinarie due accordinge <lb/>
            to the necessarie measure of theire imposic<ex>i</ex>ons for the <lb/>
            maintenance of com<ex>m</ex>on libertie. Soe that yf theire revenewes <lb/>
            raisde by imposic<ex>i</ex>on  or deriued from comon helpes shoude <lb/>
            come by accident to faiule in theire sufficiencie they haue <lb/>
            the extraordinarie disposic<ex>i</ex>on of an able willinge people <lb/>
            vnexacted on reserued to satisfie necessitie and entertaine <lb/>
            the tyme in suche an extremitie, till ordinarie meanes <lb/>
            retorne into theire wonted force../ .
         </p>
         <p>
            Whereas his <hi rend="italic">Highnes </hi>hath alreadie runne that refuge out <lb/>
            of breath and almost owt of harte consideringe the <lb/>
            promised end of takinge vp on credditt, the clearinge of <lb/>
            Flaunders is vnaccomplished and prevented notw<ex>i</ex>thstanding <lb/>
            the imp<ex>ar</ex>tinge of theire best habillities to furnish out the <lb/>
            enterprise. / .
         </p>
         <pb n="117r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f117r/add_ms_11600_f117r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            Soe that yf ordinarie revenewes become weake or wantinge his highnes <lb/>
            shalbe driuen into an exigent more straight and dangerous and more <lb/>
            remote from refuge then the States. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            This beinge A Species proper to the <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes</hi> habilitie it maie <lb/>
            be saide I gyue it an vnproper place inferringe it amonge theire <lb/>
            forraine helpes, Yet since it is a temporarie refuge not an ordinarie <lb/>
            meanes w<ex>hi</ex>ch kinde of power is neu<ex>er</ex> to bee vsed till ordinarie meanes <lb/>
            become disable or difitient it will not be imp<ex>er</ex>tinent to the conclusio<ex>n</ex> <lb/>
            of this point. / .  Nowe therefore after theise examinac<ex>i</ex>ons of his <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi> estate aswell domestique as forraine proper as borrowed <lb/>
            I finde a twoe fould want w<ex>i</ex>thin his power vncertaine of supplie <lb/>
            by meanes of foerce. That is to saie of Shippinge and money <lb/>
            whereof soe longe as he remaines vnfurnished he hathe noe <lb/>
            probabillitie to conquer because how eu<ex>er</ex> his offensiue Armie <lb/>
            duringe his contentinge purse, may florish in a gallant nomber <lb/>
            Yet his proceedings in a yeare or twoe spoendinge his strength to <lb/>
            eate awaie throughe a defence soe inaccessible and vnpassable by <lb/>
            industrie and nature as the vnited prouinc<ex>es</ex> cannot inlardge his <lb/>
            confines verie muche / And once in three Yeares space the Shipping <lb/>
            of the States well imployd maie interrupt the forraine treasure <lb/>
            that contents his Armie and soe begett a discontentm<ex>en</ex>t mutine and <lb/>
            weakenes in his power w<ex>hi</ex>ch will extend themselues into a lardge <lb/>
            advantage that discreetlie entertainde and followed maie in one <lb/>
            yeares spaace recouer. / . For howsoeu<ex>er</ex> the professor in the <lb/>
            Schoole of pollitiques reputed soe profound hath to expresse <lb/>
            howe muche a greater strength of men exceedes a better parse <lb/>
            in gen<ex>er</ex>all advantage to the com<ex>m</ex>on cause imputed ignorance and <lb/>
            error to a certeine <hi rend="italic">Iudgem<ex>en</ex>t </hi>that esteemed money to the scinnewes of <lb/>
            warres. Yett I am confident in this opinion that of a warre continewed <lb/>
            and length of tyme moneys and the very scinnewes that holde the <lb/>
            limbes and members of an Armie togeather And when those <lb/>
            scinnewes creake ar shrincke the bodie of that warre becomes <lb/>
            disable and decaies aswell in foorce as actiuenes. But true it is
            <pb n="117v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f117v/add_ms_11600_f117v.jpg"/>
            there maie be even continewed warres of such <del rend="strikethrough">equall </del>a quallitie <lb/>
            that will advance contentm<ex>en</ex>t to the Armie w<ex>i</ex>thout exactinge it <lb/>
            from the peculiar and provided treasure meerelie of the <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Prince </hi>or State it serves. / Suche are the warres like those <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">Alexander </hi>the greate whose recydencies and motions <lb/>
            quarterd <add place="above">&amp;amp;</add> leade vpon a Strangers lande theire spoyle gyues <lb/>
            satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on to the Armie insteed of paie. /.  Yet when<add place="above">ce</add>soeuer <lb/>
            theire contentm<ex>en</ex>t shalbe drawen from freend, or evemie it <lb/>
            muste consiste on money. And therefore where the <lb/>
            meanes to raise it on the enemie is wantinge it muste <lb/>
            be furnished out of freends revenewes and habilities <lb/>
            or yf the habilities of freend<ex>es</ex> doe likewise faile, the <lb/>
            want will in the end dissband and vndoe the confidence <lb/>
            and service of anie Armie howe gallant soeu<ex>er</ex> in nomber. <lb/>
            Suche is the Archedukes state whosed warre muste lyve <lb/>
            vpon his owne vncompetences and the vncertaine <lb/>
            Assistanc<ex>es</ex> of <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi>. And suche are the condic<ex>i</ex>ons <lb/>
            of <add place="above">the</add> <hi rend="italic">Netherlandish</hi> opposites by reason of theire wants and <lb/>
            refuges that they (transportinge the <hi rend="italic">designes</hi> of either <lb/>
            side somtime w<ex>i</ex>th fludd somtyme w<ex>i</ex>th ebbe w<ex>i</ex>thout A <lb/>
            certaine and continewed progress) tend rather yf theire <lb/>
            Armies continewe and the States dispose themselues <lb/>
            but onelie to defende to a p<ex>er</ex>petuall warre then anie <lb/>
            conqueringe ende. whereof the Archeduke muste needes be <lb/>
            wearie first aswell beecause the vnited prouinc<ex>es</ex> are lesse <lb/>
            opprest by warre then his as alsoe for that a p<ex>er</ex>petuall <lb/>
            warre gyues better satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on to the States then him <lb/>
            for they toeke armes w<ex>i</ex>th purpose to defend, w<ex>hi</ex>ch by <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>petuall warre is in some kinde p<ex>er</ex>formed but <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> <lb/>
            and hee w<ex>i</ex>th an intent and hoepe to ou<ex>er</ex>come w<ex>hi</ex>ch by p<ex>er</ex>petuall <lb/>
            warre canne neu<ex>er</ex> be attaind vnto. /  And as his <hi rend="italic">Highnes</hi>is or <lb/>
            shalbe wearie first of warre. soe followes it. he is the first that <lb/>
            should indevoure his repoese and rest by peace the thinge soe <lb/>
            infinitelie wondered at. / .
            <pb n="118r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f118r/add_ms_11600_f118r.jpg"/>
            Thus farre Concerninge his improbabillitie to conquer three states by foorce
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">Touchinge his highnesses second Motiue.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            He hathe some cause of feare to loese by the continewance of the warre <lb/>
            his present interest (alsoe) and possession in <add place="above">the</add> <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes</hi>. ./.
         </p>
         <p>
            For introducc<ex>i</ex>on to discourse that pointe it maie be supposed that France <lb/>
            could effect the protecc<ex>i</ex>on of the vnited provinc<ex>es</ex> First because expe=<lb break="no"/>
            rience gathered from the howse of <hi rend="italic">Burgundie </hi>maie p<ex>er</ex>swade that <lb/>
            the fall of the <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes </hi>into the Armes of <hi rend="italic">Spayne </hi>would succeed <lb/>
            to the hurte of <hi rend="italic">Fraunce</hi>  Secondlie for that reasonne obseruinge <lb/>
            the constituc<ex>i</ex>on of <hi rend="italic">Fraunce </hi>and the <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes</hi> will conclude <lb/>
            that the <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes </hi>ioyned w<ex>i</ex>th <hi rend="italic">Fraunce </hi>would constitute <lb/>
            the same a mightie potent <hi rend="italic">Monarchie</hi> i in regarde of theire <lb/>
            coniunction of seate w<ex>hi</ex>ch will compose them an entire vnited <lb/>
            boodie   2 because of theire comodious scituac<ex>i</ex>on for commerce w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            consequentli will attract him wealth.  3 In respect of the <hi rend="italic">Nether <lb/>
            landes </hi>naturall in accessabilitie or at least vnapassabilitie <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch ioyned w<ex>i</ex>th <hi rend="italic">Fraunce </hi>will stand like an vnpregnable fortifi=<lb break="no"/>
            cac<ex>i</ex>on vpon his coaste frontier to defend him against inv<del rend="strikethrough">it</del>ac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            4 by reason of tht answerable strength at sea w<ex>hi</ex>ch they woulde <lb/>
            add vnto his power aswell invasiue as defensive against som<ex>m</ex>e <lb/>
            potentates his neighbours whome for pretence and power he <lb/>
            hath in ieaslosie. / . Nowe yf <add place="above">
                    <ex>tha</ex>t</add>  Fraunce should vndertake to protect <lb/>
            them and in the meane tyme the Ciuill peace of <hi rend="italic">Fraunce </hi>continew <lb/>
            firme and greate <hi rend="italic">Brittaine </hi>newtrall: the Archedukes were threa <lb/>
            tned in very fewe yeares to be dryven owt of the <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes</hi>. /
         </p>
         <p>
            First because <hi rend="italic">Fraunce</hi>  is populous to raise a greate armie w<ex>i</ex>th muche <lb/>
            expedic<ex>i</ex>on wealthie to maintaine a flourishinge Armie w<ex>i</ex>th good competencie <lb/>
            and convenientlie seated to make continewall invation w<ex>i</ex>th litle difficultie
         </p>
         <p>
            2	To add facillitie to the progress of his power the States p<ex>re</ex>sent <hi rend="italic">dissigne</hi> <lb/>
            vpon <hi rend="italic">America</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Affrica </hi>prosequited w<ex>i</ex>th actiuenes and life will diu<ex>er</ex>te <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>Spanish assistance and leaue his highness in gou<ex>er</ex>nement <lb/>
            distracted and confounded w<ex>i</ex>th the French invasions and the States <lb/>
            alarmes heere and there on eu<ex>er</ex>ie side offensiuelie and in the middeste a <lb/>
            discontented Subiect vnresolued in his defence For when his <hi rend="italic">Highness</hi> shall
            <pb n="118v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f118v/add_ms_11600_f118v.jpg"/>
            haue lost the maritine townes, his inland Subiects Findinge <lb/>
            them selues soe circumvented w<ex>i</ex>th dispaire of redemption <lb/>
            will not onlie entertaine, but meditate also and labour <lb/>
            meanes of revolte. /  It maie bee heere obiected that Fraunce <lb/>
            examininge the present constituc<ex>i</ex>on of it selfe and then remem <lb/>
            bringe what a vigilant preventinge eye a certaine potent <lb/>
            Neighbour ought to hould vpon the progresse of his power <lb/>
            Shall finde infirmities at home and foerce abroade that maie <lb/>
            advaunce them selues against his enterprise not onlie to <lb/>
            prevent the inlardgem<ex>en</ex>t but alsoe to attempt the diminuc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of his power and the restrycc<ex>i</ex>on of his bonds of Monarchie <lb/>
            reasons that should diswade him to protect <ex>th</ex>e <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes</hi> <lb/>
            and soe the States become depriued of that hoepe. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            To opproue notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge my assertion that his highnes hath <lb/>
            some cause of feare to loese by the continewance of the <lb/>
            warres. I will inferre first a daungerous infirmitie <lb/>
            in the domestique constituc<ex>i</ex>on of his <hi rend="italic">Highnes </hi>power <lb/>
            and secondlie a probabilitie in the States vnborrowed <lb/>
            strengthe to nourishe that infirmitie even till it hathe <lb/>
            begotten an incurable consumption in his State. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            The infirmitie expresseth it selfe in this his sufficiencie <lb/>
            of purse to satisfie the paiment of his Armie in whole <lb/>
            leaves<unclear>:</unclear> a greate p<ex>ar</ex>te of the generall entertainem<ex>en</ex>t continuallie <lb/>
            suspended and detainde from eu<ex>er</ex>y p<ex>ar</ex>ticular w<ex>hi</ex>ch in smale <lb/>
            tyme amountinge to a greate som<ex>m</ex>e gyves occasion of <lb/>
            mutine, the malivolence and malignancie, whereof is <lb/>
            by example of theire form<ex>er</ex> good successe in suche eruptions <lb/>
            growne at this present to an exceedinge bouldnes, A <lb/>
            daungerous diuision in his power since they that <lb/>
            mutine are for the most p<ex>ar</ex>te suche men whoese obedience <lb/>
            hee hath moste reason to preserve and whose revolte <lb/>
            he hathe greatest cause to prevent of all the Nations in <lb/>
            his Armie because they consiste chefelie of <hi rend="italic">Wallones</hi> <lb/>
            his seruiceablest men of warre. by reason that besides
            <pb n="119r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f119r/add_ms_11600_f119r.jpg"/>
            theire aptnes for the feilde they are in nomber strongest and in seates the <lb/>
            readiest to admitt supplie w<ex>i</ex>thout whose seruice hee is not hable to <lb/>
            expose him selfe into the feilde. / Nowe to nourishe that infirmitie <lb/>
            vntill it growe vnto uncurable disease  The States haue bent <lb/>
            a warre against the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaynes</hi> dominion in <hi rend="italic">America</hi> <lb/>
            and <hi rend="italic">Affrica</hi> vpon w<ex>hi</ex>ch growndes beinge the best p<ex>ar</ex>ticulars belon <lb/>
            ginge vnto <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi> the supportac<ex>i</ex>on of the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>weaknes <lb/>
            and debilitie consists. w<ex>hi</ex>ch supportac<ex>i</ex>on removes the Architecture <lb/>
            of his State Massive and waightie lest vpon a narrowe loose vnfirm <lb/>
            foundac<ex>i</ex>on will stand vnstedfastlie waueringe and totteringe ready <lb/>
            to fall vnder an offensiue warre that shall attempt to batter it. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            To gyve that proiect of the States the better hoepe and probabillitie <lb/>
            to prosper the fleete that carries the <hi rend="italic">designe</hi> is straighted w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            good confidence in it selfe to transporte her requisite proceedinges <lb/>
            from hence and some encouragem<ex>en</ex>t to welcome her attempts ashoore <lb/>
            vppon the landinge of her enterprise there. /.  Her confidence <lb/>
            consists besides her foerce vpon her constituc<ex>i</ex>on pollitique whose <lb/>
            frame is raisde vpon soe good a grownde that the prouision of her <lb/>
            proceedings, although the treasure of the com<ex>m</ex>on pursse be at anie <lb/>
            tyme necessarilie exhausted for the domestique warre, shall seldome <lb/>
            be soe muche neglected as to disapointe the service of the particular <lb/>
            because besides those habilities that the com<ex>m</ex>on pursse and power of <lb/>
            the vnited provinc<ex>es</ex> ordaine to her shee shalbe still supported w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            an able stocke composd of private substanc<ex>es</ex>. / And her incouragem<ex>en</ex>t <lb/>
            theire maie be derived from the practices of those tractes whoe being <lb/>
            oppressed and greeued w<ex>i</ex>th miserie and bondage w<ex>i</ex>th the heavie gou<ex>er</ex>ne <lb/>
            m<ex>en</ex>t of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> hathe <del rend="strikethrough">hetherto</del> heeretofore inflicted on them maie <lb/>
            bee easilie drawen to ioyne w<ex>i</ex>th anie newe attempt that pro=<lb break="no"/>
            miseth to alter thoese condic<ex>i</ex>ons w<ex>hi</ex>ch they hate. / .  Nowe yf it <lb/>
            shall please God to bless that hoepefull proiect of the States w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            good successe yea yf it weare but an enterprise of muche lesse <lb/>
            hoepe<del rend="strikethrough">full</del> then this that coulde but for a yeare or twoe com<ex>m</ex>aunde <lb/>
            and intercepte the passages betweene the <hi rend="italic">Spaniarde </hi>and his
            <pb n="119v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f119v/add_ms_11600_f119v.jpg"/>
            Mynes of Golde the Archedukes warre alreadie rraisd w<ex>i</ex>th mutinies <lb/>
            by want of money will fall into a com<ex>m</ex>on discontentment <lb/>
            and confounde itselfe makinge by that diuision followed <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th the States invasion A wounde incurable in the bodie of <lb/>
            his State endaungeringe the life thereof by a consuminge <lb/>
            languishm<ex>en</ex>t yf not distroyinge it by Suddaine deathe:/ <lb/>
            Soe muche touchinge his <hi rend="italic">Highnes </hi>seconde Motiue. /.
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">The thirde Motiue</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            The <hi rend="italic">Archeduke</hi> hath greate reason to continewe his <lb/>
            present possession yf not by warre by peace. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            His present possession onelie in the <hi rend="italic">Netherlandes</hi> is of all <lb/>
            his other dignities wheather in possession or promise <lb/>
            absolutelie the most worthie  / If then there be suche cause <lb/>
            of diffidence to confirme it by warre hee hath greate cause <lb/>
            and reason to indououre the assurance thereof by peace /.
         </p>
         <p>
            And thus by the premisses that appeares to me that his <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi> the Archeduke maie by moude w<ex>i</ex>th good reason <lb/>
            to affecte a true peace../.  Nowe to p<ex>er</ex>swade his <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ie</ex>s aggreac<ex>i</ex>on of <hi rend="italic">Spayne </hi>to peace there maie be <lb/>
            coniectured. First the considerac<ex>i</ex>ons of the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> <lb/>
            twoe Firste motiues / <hi rend="italic">Namelie </hi>That hee hath litle <lb/>
            or noe probabilitie to reduce the States into the armes <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi> by foerce and some cause of feare not onlie <lb/>
            not to winne but alsoe to loese../ .
         </p>
         <p>
            The contynewance of the warre threatens the depriuac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            alsoe of those his <hi rend="italic">Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties </hi>best particulars wherein the <lb/>
            pride and greatenes of his power consistes. And further <lb/>
            the hassarde of his principallitie. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            The <hi rend="italic">States</hi> companie of <hi rend="italic">Merchants</hi> before menc<ex>i</ex>oned <lb/>
            haue vndertaken w<ex>i</ex>th good probabilitie to prosper to open <lb/>
            a waie for traffique into <hi rend="italic">America </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Affrica</hi>. the
            <pb n="120r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f120r/add_ms_11600_f120r.jpg"/>
            Mynes of his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties welthe the growndes of his pride and the chefest bases <lb/>
            wherein the pillors of his greatenes doe consiste. /.  Yf it please God <lb/>
            to blesse that <hi rend="italic">designe</hi> in the successe accordinge to the hoepe, the instituc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            and begininge gyves the Attractiue obiect of the goulden Fleete is life <lb/>
            to drawe the hartes of other Nations to the like desire and consequentlie <lb/>
            to the like. /.  The communitie to other Nations of those partes depri <lb/>
            vinge him of his possession reserved in them will threaten further <lb/>
            the hassard of his principallitie. because when the protestant <lb/>
            princes shall see the poepes champion soe disabled the apprehension <lb/>
            of the advantage maie offer them incourgem<ex>en</ex>t ro proiecte an uniu<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            sall reformac<ex>i</ex>on of the Churche through Christendome the rather <lb/>
            since besides theire duties to religious officers the p<ex>re</ex>seruac<ex>i</ex>on of theire <lb/>
            Temporall estates will incessantlie importune it. because soe longe <lb/>
            as <hi rend="italic">Antechriste </hi>striues to bee plac’d aboue that w<ex>hi</ex>ch is called <hi rend="italic">God</hi> <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">Poepe </hi>will continewallie labour to cast downe Gods leivtenante from <lb/>
            his throenes./ .For the confusion of whose divelishe practises <lb/>
            the Attempte<del rend="strikethrough">e</del> (proceedinge soe) is like to make a waie throughe <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi> either by proposic<ex>i</ex>on of aduise to drawe him to conforme <lb/>
            tie and reformac<ex>i</ex>on of yf aduise wwill take noe place by foerce./ . <lb/>
            his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie therfore in dowbt of the successe of that <hi rend="italic">designe </hi>and leaste <lb/>
            the prosperous successe thereof should open and exemplefie a waie <lb/>
            to other Nations for the like com<ex>m</ex>unitie and participac<ex>i</ex>on in that <lb/>
            whose reservac<ex>i</ex>on his estate imports him to regard and consequentlie <lb/>
            attempt him further to be secured from soe daungerous a hassarde <lb/>
            of his greatenes. maie for a retractac<ex>i</ex>on of that enterprise <lb/>
            from suche Attemptes on him abroade, be the rather drawen <lb/>
            to admitt the vndertakers those peacefull Motiues of contentment <lb/>
            in them selues att hoome./ . The operac<ex>i</ex>on of a Compounde <lb/>
            made of the collected Simples (howe simple soeu<ex>er</ex> mixed w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            other argum<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> and reasons of a ioynte effecacie) maie be suppos’d <lb/>
            to haue wrought the purgac<ex>i</ex>on of that chollericke distemp<ex>er</ex>ature <lb/>
            of warre in the affections of <hi rend="italic">Austria</hi> the rather and w<ex>i</ex>th more <lb/>
            facillitie since twoe good preparatiues be ministred before./ .
            <pb n="120v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f120v/add_ms_11600_f120v.jpg"/>
            <hi rend="italic">Namely</hi> <lb/>
            The States when in the eye of opinion theire affaires did seeme <lb/>
            to decline and <hi rend="italic">Spayne </hi>(it may be) expected they shoulde seeke for <lb/>
            peace expressed euen then an Argum<ex>en</ex>t of confidence and resoluc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            in them not onlie to endure but alsoe to prosecute the warre as <lb/>
            appeareth in their <hi rend="italic">Octroy</hi>: made for the constituc<ex>i</ex>on of theire <lb/>
            Merchants companie (erected) to continewe theire com<ex>m</ex>erce <lb/>
            persistable againste the <hi rend="italic">Spanish</hi> offence where they ordaine <lb/>
            that noe finall accounte shalbe made of that Negotiation <lb/>
            vntill the ende of 36 yeares and then the form<ex>er</ex> ballanced and <lb/>
            clered, to institute the same yf the participants consents a newe <lb/>
            Secondlie the scoepe and purpose of the State of <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi> <lb/>
            affectinge heeretofore the Empire of <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> w<ex>hi</ex>ch moued it <lb/>
            the more willinglie to entertaine all occasions to drawe the <lb/>
            sworde of warre. Nowe since experience hath proued it but <lb/>
            a vaine conception, the hoepe thereof is dead and w<ex>i</ex>th hoepe to <lb/>
            ouercome an inclinac<ex>i</ex>on alsoe to pursue, instructinge the <lb/>
            moderac<ex>i</ex>on of theire experienced counsaile rather to loeke backe to <lb/>
            a plentifull peace, then to continewe paie to a fruitles Warre. <lb/>
            And to conclude this pointe w<ex>i</ex>th that w<ex>hi</ex>ch I suppose, confederates <lb/>
            theire disposic<ex>i</ex>ons to this peace. I muste not be vnmindfull of <lb/>
            his <hi rend="italic">Holines the Poepe</hi>: For yf that attribute of holines be <lb/>
            not vnworthelie succeeded to him, yf hee degenerates not from <lb/>
            the Sanctitie of thoese his predecessors that lyved in the simple <lb/>
            godlie and primitiue age of the <hi rend="italic">Churche</hi>. hee is the peace=<lb break="no"/>
            maker gen<ex>er</ex>all of all christendome. But hee vsurpes that <lb/>
            name of holines, the mother of tranquillitie and peace. / <lb/>
            For yf his workes be veiwed and examined pride and ambic<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            the verie opposites to the humilitie and peace of sowle: where <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th the Churche of God should bee indued soe palpablie and <lb/>
            demonstratiuelie appeare in him, that noe vnblinded eye <lb/>
            but maie see his spirritt to bee even the convenc<ex>i</ex>on howse of <lb/>
            worldlie perturbac<ex>i</ex>ons and disquietnesses w<ex>hi</ex>ch w<ex>i</ex>th incessant
            <pb n="121r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f121r/add_ms_11600_f121r.jpg"/>
            motion carrie and transporte his contemplac<ex>i</ex>ons vpon the light winge of <lb/>
            vanitie hou<ex>er</ex>inge betweene heaven and earth seldome descendinge w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            a thought into the Grave nor aspiringe w<ex>i</ex>th a meditation higher then <lb/>
            the Moene../  Soe that yf this propounded peace be by a true syncere <lb/>
            and peaceable intent produced it were an errour to suppose the <lb/>
            Poepe to haue the leaste correspondencie w<ex>i</ex>th it vnlesse the scence and <lb/>
            apprehension of necessitie bee interpos’d betweene his pride and <lb/>
            him. / . But yf it bee a temporisinge stratagem intended to a <lb/>
            deceiptfull ende the <hi rend="italic">Poepe</hi> affect<ex>es</ex> the State of temporallitie <lb/>
            soe well, that w<ex>i</ex>thout offence or synne against his holines. hee maie <lb/>
            be thought to be <hi rend="italic">Primus Motor</hi> and directer of the same./.
         </p>
         <p>
            Howsoeu<ex>er</ex> I am of opinion tgat in this affaire he hath a voice and <lb/>
            gand because it muche concernes his owne particular not onlie for <lb/>
            the reasons before me<ex>n</ex>c<ex>i</ex>oned, that importe the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> <lb/>
            wherein the Poope likewise is deepelie interessed but alsoe in <lb/>
            annother respect peculiar to him selfe. / . Religion and pollicie <lb/>
            beginne to take roote and spreade in manie braunches against the <lb/>
            effect<ex>es</ex> of his Supremacie even in the land and Nation where hee <lb/>
            lyves, the groweth thereof he feares and would suppresse <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> that should vndertake his quarrell is ingaged in other <lb/>
            warres: Thoese warres converted into peace his forces and <lb/>
            habillities drawen neere hoeme will beare the better fronte <lb/>
            and contenaunce againste the boldne<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>ses that rise soe neare <lb/>
            the residence of <hi rend="italic">Romes </hi>securitie. / And then to countervail <lb/>
            that fauor to the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>, the Poepe maie happelie <lb/>
            promise to prevaile for him more affectuallie vppon the <lb/>
            vnited provinces w<ex>i</ex>th a feawe vnderminings <hi rend="italic">Iesuit<ex>es</ex>
                </hi> then <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Spinola</hi> w<ex>i</ex>th the open foerce of an <hi rend="italic">Armie of Menn</hi>. And <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th Halfe the chardge though Goulde indeede muste <lb/>
            bee an instrument. ./.
         </p>
         <pb n="121v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f121v/add_ms_11600_f121v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            Soe that by theese computac<ex>i</ex>ons the cause and meaninge of his <lb/>
            ouerture for peace, consist<ex>es</ex> of Necessitie and miserie. ./. <lb/>
            And I imagine the hoepe and end  expected once by them, is that <lb/>
            they should by one worke bee able not onlie to diuert the danger <lb/>
            of an enterprise that threatens to subdue themselues but also <lb/>
            to subdue or reduce the vndertakers of that Attempt into <lb/>
            the compasse of theire power and furnish themselues of <lb/>
            instruments and means against occasion offers it selfe <lb/>
            for the accomplishm<ex>en</ex>t of greater and more offensiue pur=<lb break="no"/>
            poses then by continewed warre cann be acchived. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            Wheather the States shoulde affecte a peace vpon this offer of <lb/>
            his <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi> ./ .In disputinge this question there <add place="above">are</add> to <lb/>
            bee considered. that. the conclusion of this peace accordinge <lb/>
            to the amplitude of the effecte wilbe lesse honorable to <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>then to the States. the lesse honorable the more <lb/>
            discontentfull and soe the more provokinge a desire to <lb/>
            change. /. A State seldome stoopes her honor but <add place="above">in</add> necessitie <lb/>
            or mistery. and the p<ex>ar</ex>tinge from honor holdes the Sperritt <lb/>
            in labours to recou<ex>er</ex> it againe. /. It is against the <hi rend="italic">Poepes</hi> <lb/>
            profession whose principles are built vpon by <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> <lb/>
            to keepe faithe w<ex>i</ex>th protestants. / . To vndermine princi=<lb break="no"/>
            pallitie by dissembled waies hath beene warranted by <lb/>
            the supreame heade of the <hi rend="italic">Spanish Churche</hi> in diuerse <lb/>
            p<ex>ar</ex>ticulers. And ambition is neu<ex>er</ex> more apte touchinge <lb/>
            honor and faithe vnder a good pretence to a bad ende then <lb/>
            when seeminge religion pleades her excuse. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            Synce the desire of amitie betweene principallities <lb/>
            proceedes most com<ex>m</ex>onlie from necessarie reasons that <lb/>
            concerne the seu<ex>er</ex>all and proper good and not so muche from <lb/>
            anie Naturall or other true affenitie of loue, the selfe <lb/>
            respects of Naturall contracts. therefore takinge soe faste <lb/>
            a roete in gen<ex>er</ex>all muste needes bee deepelie planted: <lb/>
            in this particular where arguments of hatred and offence
            <pb n="122r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f122r/add_ms_11600_f122r.jpg"/>
            wilbe accorded to posteritie and (while the gou<ex>er</ex>ment of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>is anie <lb/>
            where honored in the <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi>) keepe hidden sparks of this combustion <lb/>
            still aliue to gyue the vnquiett Spirritts that are allwaies accident to <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Princes</hi> Courtes. conttinewall subiect for there turbulence to worke <lb/>
            vppon. /.  And to gyve fier to suche Saltpeter braines the common <lb/>
            disagreem<ex>en</ex>t of theire verie soules in matter of religion wilbe still <lb/>
            in readines. That difference is like to bee pursued w<ex>i</ex>th greater heate <lb/>
            offence, and daunger by the <hi rend="italic">Spanish</hi> syde againste the States then <lb/>
            on the contrarie. /. First because of religion the growndes and <lb/>
            principles professed by the States Churche are true and good: but <lb/>
            those of <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>muche falsefied and badd. / Bad waies bee <lb/>
            still more earnestlie pursued then good, and goodnes workes <lb/>
            more openlie then badnes whose malitious practizes are carried <lb/>
            secretlie in Mynes and darkenes, therefore muche more daungerous
         </p>
         <p>
            2	The whore of <hi rend="italic">Babilon</hi> trickt in the pride w<ex>i</ex>th scensuall pleasures <lb/>
            and delights. beesetts her fornicators w<ex>i</ex>th soe deepe a passion that <lb/>
            they hazard even theire deerest good vppon the creditt <del rend="strikethrough">onlie</del> onlie of <lb/>
            her idle promises incompassinge the moste wicked inhumaine and <lb/>
            barbarous practices to satisfie her luste. Yea even these soules that <lb/>
            simplie in them selues are farre from suche contriuinge perswaded <lb/>
            by her pleasingnes doe vndertake the moste abhominable damnab<add place="above">le</add> <lb/>
            and deevlish practices as works of merritt to theire eu<ex>er</ex>lastinge good. <lb/>
            From theise and other considerac<ex>i</ex>ons of the like nature it maie be <lb/>
            argued. Firste that the States haue cause to suspect an ill <lb/>
            meaninge in this ouerture for a peace /  secondlie that yf necessitie <lb/>
            hath wrought this ouerture when there necessitie dissolueth <lb/>
            the bandes of amitie are like to breake. /.  To stande vppon <lb/>
            a guarde against the daunger of w<ex>hi</ex>ch opposites. The States, <lb/>
            before they conclude vpon the offer haue reason to resolue them <lb/>
            selues. /  Firste wheather they are able to winne the Netherlands <lb/>
            by warre. / . secondly whether a peace will not augm<ex>en</ex>t the <hi rend="italic">Spanish</hi> <lb/>
            strength &amp;amp; detract from theirs. and soe disable theire power to defende./ .
         </p>
         <pb n="122v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f122v/add_ms_11600_f122v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            If boethe or either of theise questions bee resolued affirmatiuelye <lb/>
            the States haue greate<add place="above">r</add> reason to persiste in warres them graunte <lb/>
            a peace to th’ends to secure themselues from the daungerous <lb/>
            consequence<ex>es</ex> of an ill meaninge, and in meere necessitie to <lb/>
            prevente theire fall w<ex>hi</ex>ch w<ex>i</ex>th the dissabillitie of theire defence <lb/>
            is like to be attempted.  ./. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Touchinge theire habillities tto conquer it muste consiste <lb/>
            (next vnder god) either <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> vpon forraine protecc<ex>i</ex>on or on <lb/>
            the vertue of theire offencive warre proiected against <lb/>
            the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>. /.  As for forraine protecc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            by whose power they maye hoepe to wynne, the first declares <lb/>
            noe promise to vndertake: the seconde importes an vncertaine <lb/>
            and a daungerous successe w<ex>i</ex>thout the aggreation of the <lb/>
            first. / . 				Concerninge the firste <lb/>
            first from greate <hi rend="italic">Brittaine</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Spaines </hi>longe experience <lb/>
            makes him knowe and feele that the amitie of England <lb/>
            muche more of <hi rend="italic">Greate Brittaine</hi> is worthie of his <lb/>
            loue. beinge therefore possest thereof his necessitie <lb/>
            will make him labour to preserue it: And Englandes <lb/>
            natiue and religious faith will neu<ex>er</ex> gyue the firste <lb/>
            occasion to breake it. And vntill it be broeken the united <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Prouinces </hi>duringe theire present State are promised noe <lb/>
            protec<ex>i</ex>on thence. /.  Yet howsoeu<ex>er</ex> yf protecc<ex>i</ex>on maye be <lb/>
            theire obtained the argum<ex>en</ex>ts that would induce them to <lb/>
            conclude w<ex>i</ex>th this suspected ou<ex>er</ex>ture for peace maie <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th good reason be ou<ex>er</ex>throwne. /.  But as for the seconde <lb/>
            From <hi rend="italic">Fraunce</hi>. First that protecc<ex>i</ex>on is vncertaine in <lb/>
            it selfe. alone of good successe because (amonge other reasons) <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">Frenche Kinge </hi>beinge of a decaied bodie promiseth noe <lb/>
            longe life, <hi rend="italic">The Dolphin </hi>is in minoritie: <hi rend="italic">A Protector</hi> is <lb/>
            gen<ex>er</ex>allie <unclear>emulated</unclear> the kings bloud flowes in a diuided streame. 
            <pb n="123r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f123r/add_ms_11600_f123r.jpg"/>
            religion is diuided and boeth presuminge in theire seu<ex>er</ex>all strength The <lb/>
            Nobilitie are verie manie and some very powerfull in them selues. All <lb/>
            theise are infirmities that maie dishable it to consiste in itselfe muche <lb/>
            more to protect anie other./  2  The protecc<ex>i</ex>on of <hi rend="italic">Fraunce </hi>maie happen <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout the consent of <hi rend="italic">Greate Brittaine</hi>) to tourne to theire p<ex>er</ex>ill because <lb/>
            the Seates of <hi rend="italic">Fraunce </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi> w<ex>i</ex>th other materialls and maine <lb/>
            circumstanc<ex>es</ex> be considered it will appeare that there coniunction and <lb/>
            vnion would proue to be of daungerous consequence to the State of <lb/>
            England. <hi rend="italic">England </hi>therefore shall haue litle cause to suffer a procee <lb/>
            dinge to that end. And yf the power of England shalbe forced for <lb/>
            otherwise it neu<ex>er</ex> will appose it selfe. the vnited prouinc<ex>es</ex> shall haue <lb/>
            cause to feare theire ill successe aswell for that diuision wherevnto <lb/>
            Fraunce is subiect as alsoe because England is hable to beate them <lb/>
            att theire owne weapons and in theire <del rend="strikethrough">owne </del>
                <add place="above">propper</add> Element the water <lb/>
            wherein theire power consists. w<ex>hi</ex>ch yf it suffer wracke will sincke <lb/>
            theire State. /.  This seperac<ex>i</ex>on and reserudnes betweene the kingdom <lb/>
            of England aand Fraunce in matter of extremitie is of a necessarie <lb/>
            vse. but where a moderac<ex>i</ex>on maie haue place to discontract them <lb/>
            in eu<ex>er</ex>y p<ex>ar</ex>te were in regard of a third power not soo convenient for <lb/>
            the mutuall saftie of theire States. w<ex>hi</ex>ch moderac<ex>i</ex>on rather should <lb/>
            in this particular be admitted. for howsoeu<ex>er</ex> they shall beare them <lb/>
            selues aparte when the maliuolent aspect of eyther on the other <lb/>
            is the question betweene them. Yet nowe in this where they are <lb/>
            interressed bothe (for some respect) alike in one in the same <lb/>
            affaire and seeinge neyther canne by a thirde be ou<ex>er</ex>come w<ex>i</ex>thout <lb/>
            the others imminent p<ex>er</ex>ill. they haue reason to consent in counsaling <lb/>
            the managinge thereof. / <hi rend="italic">Heauen </hi>therefore soe inspire <lb/>
            theire Counsailes w<ex>i</ex>th the light of wisdome that they maye <lb/>
            provide and prevent against the vyolence and power of <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Roemes </hi>pride. <hi rend="italic">Spaynes </hi>desire of Empiere and the goulde <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">India </hi>confederated in a faction. And that this calme of <lb/>
            peace be not a meanes to recreat those wearied Spirritts and enable
            <pb n="123v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f123v/add_ms_11600_f123v.jpg"/>
            them w<ex>i</ex>th actiuenes and strength against occasion waken them <lb/>
            to make a warre more Stormie violent and daungerous <lb/>
            For when desier and meanes remayne stronge enterprises <lb/>
            are begotten and produced / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Nowe touchinge theire offensiue warre vppon the kinge <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi>. w<ex>hi</ex>ch settinge theire protecc<ex>i</ex>ons asyde is the <lb/>
            onlie hoepefull meane and instrument (next vnder god) <lb/>
            they haue to wynne. Yet not soe hoepefull as to be relied <lb/>
            vppon w<ex>i</ex>thout forraine consent. /  Noe dowbt that warre <lb/>
            proceedinge w<ex>i</ex>th a blessed and prosperous successe <lb/>
            will highly raise the state of theire affaires and yet <lb/>
            expresseth reasons of p<ex>er</ex>swasions to induce a second to <lb/>
            the worke for it importes a verie probable begininge <lb/>
            for an hable waie to ou<ex>er</ex>throwe the pride of <hi rend="italic">Antechriste</hi> <lb/>
            to roete owt the seditions of thoese inhumaine abhominable <lb/>
            practices of fyer and bloud, that will soe longe as <hi rend="italic">Ante=<lb break="no"/>
            christ</hi> continewes proud and fearefull of his fall make <lb/>
            fearefull inundac<ex>i</ex>ons and Combustions in the com<ex>m</ex>on <lb/>
            peace of Christendome, to replant the vniformitie of <lb/>
            the true primatiue Churche of Christendome to <lb/>
            convert manie barbarous nations from theire igno=<lb break="no"/>
            raunce and infidelitie the true knowledge and worshipp <lb/>
            of God. &amp;amp;c./ . <hi rend="italic">Oh </hi>thaat I had habillitie and libertie of <lb/>
            voice to open and expresse my harte. But since my <lb/>
            voyce is lesser then my zeale and that my humble <lb/>
            reverence vnto the height of State prohibitts me to <lb/>
            measure thoese transcendences soe farre aboue the <lb/>
            dutie of my reache. I will locke vpp the contemplat<ex>i</ex>ons <lb/>
            of my soule onely from that entyre bothe natiue and <lb/>
            religious) love I owe my Soveraigne and Countrie <lb/>
            lett me deliuer the generall. /
         </p>
         <pb n="124r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f124r/add_ms_11600_f124r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            If anie consequence of daunger to the State of England lurke in the <lb/>
            conclusion of this peace Nowe is tyme to prevent it. Nowe when a <lb/>
            worthie purpose well proiected and digested and composed w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            able Substances, is readie to be sett on foete against the head of <lb/>
            that ambitious mightines. Nowe when the bodie of that power <lb/>
            and faccultie of that action is wearie and fainte  Nowe when the <lb/>
            fresh remembrance of the <hi rend="italic">Poepes </hi>abhominable practizes will <lb/>
            moue the gen<ex>er</ex>all harte of all vnblinded iudgm<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> to applaude the <lb/>
            interprise as tendinge to suppresse his pride and chastice his <lb/>
            arrogancie &amp;amp;c. /  For procrastinate that wworke of providence by <lb/>
            sufferinge peace If anie Daunger lurke in it is like to take awaie <lb/>
            or weaken those habilities and oportunities that nowe present <lb/>
            them selues. And then it will be difficultier to defend them nowe <lb/>
            to ou<ex>er</ex>come, then when his wearie bodie shalbe recreated w<ex>i</ex>th the <lb/>
            reste of peace. his Indians fortefied his Navie multiplied <lb/>
            his Coeffers fild and all his vaines swelld highe w<ex>i</ex>th pride <lb/>
            then when the constituc<ex>i</ex>on of that noble purpose of the States <lb/>
            shalbe dissolued and by the participant<ex>es</ex> diuerted or p<ex>er</ex>swaded into <lb/>
            other courses different from that. Then when his ostentac<ex>i</ex>on of <lb/>
            conformitie w<ex>i</ex>th other practizes of insinuation shall haue reco=<lb break="no"/>
            uered reputac<ex>i</ex>on for him w<ex>i</ex>th the vnited provinc<ex>es</ex> redeeme him <lb/>
            owt of theire publique hate and skrewed his name and <lb/>
            power againe into the <hi rend="italic">Netherland<ex>es</ex>
                </hi> &amp;amp;c. If therefore <lb/>
            an hable protection will contract his power w<ex>i</ex>th this the <lb/>
            States <hi rend="italic">Dissigne </hi>theire hoepe to ou<ex>er</ex>come by warre and dowbt <lb/>
            to subsist by peace might move them to affect a conquest <lb/>
            rather then a composic<ex>i</ex>on that theire worke of peace might <lb/>
            soe be Crownde w<ex>i</ex>th a more sure establishm<ex>en</ex>t. . But yf theire <lb/>
            enterprise cannot be seconded protcted nor assisted but <lb/>
            left suspended betweene hoope and dowbt the States haue <lb/>
            reason notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>difficulties and theire <lb/>
            <pb n="124v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f124v/add_ms_11600_f124v.jpg"/>
            hoepes to affecte an honorable composic<ex>i</ex>on prouided it dishables <lb/>
            not the instrum<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> of theire defence: first because the good<del rend="strikethrough">nes</del> <add place="above">successe</add> <lb/>
            of that <hi rend="italic">Dissigne </hi>is but in hoepe and expectac<ex>i</ex>on vnassured../ <lb/>
            2    Yf that dissigne be ou<ex>er</ex>throwne it will fall to theire heavie <lb/>
            damage because it will dishable manie of theire merchants <lb/>
            discourage the vnitie and confidence of theire people and <lb/>
            weaken theire power att Sea w<ex>hi</ex>ch are the cheefest ioyntes <lb/>
            whereon the bodie of theire State dothe moue. /.  3 w<ex>i</ex>thout <lb/>
            the good successe of that <hi rend="italic">Dissigne</hi> they are of themselues and <lb/>
            theire vnderhand helpes. but able to resiste <del rend="strikethrough">and </del>
                <add place="above">not</add> to conquere <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch tendinge to a perpetuall warre wilbe perpetuallie <lb/>
            miserable. /. 4  They have little reasonne to relie <lb/>
            presuminglie vpon theire owne (onelie) p<ex>ar</ex>ticular power <lb/>
            and habilitie aswell consideringe theire principall sub=<lb break="no"/>
            sistaunce when theire owne habilities did stoope vnder the <lb/>
            handes of opression, wwas hitherto supported and protected <lb/>
            (next under god) by the soueraigne and gratious helpe of <lb/>
            forraine power. And alsoe that yf suche a forrayne <lb/>
            power shall finde it requisite hee maie in the iudgement <lb/>
            of reason diuerte or hinder even their greatest vndertakinge. <lb/>
            Soe that w<ex>i</ex>thout protecc<ex>i</ex>on the Stat<ex>es</ex> haue reason to affect <lb/>
            this peace prouided it dishables not the instrum<ex>en</ex>ts of <lb/>
            theire defence. . /.		Nowe wheather a peace muste <lb/>
            necessarelie dishable theire power to defende. ./ .
         </p>
         <p>
            This question in the scence and apprehension (onelie) <lb/>
            of the eare will (questionlesse) sounde harche and strange <lb/>
            consideringe it hath the com<ex>m</ex>on voyce that peace is boeth <lb/>
            the mother and Nursse of plentifull habillities. ./ . <lb/>
            But for <del rend="strikethrough">N</del> the Netherlands in theire deuided State yf <lb/>
            they weare rightly vnderstoed the due consideration.
            <pb n="125r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f125r/add_ms_11600_f125r.jpg"/>
            will approue it (not an idle feare) but an indeavor of a requisite truste and <lb/>
            prouidence to call even an intended peace in question howe it standes <lb/>
            disposed vnto the States: for peace doethe promise to supplie theire <lb/>
            opposites w<ex>i</ex>th those materiall necessarie instruments the wants whereof <lb/>
            dishables him to wynne. Namelie <hi rend="italic">Shippinge</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Money</hi>. /.  Touchinge <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Shippinge </hi>a peace will promise him increase. /. First Because <lb/>
            hee hathe convenient Havens and Townes for Marte and traffique <lb/>
            the principall beginers and maintayners of a Navie. /.  2 As warre <lb/>
            by blockinge vpp his <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi> havens and Townes of Marte <lb/>
            converted all theire traffique to the vnited provinc<ex>es</ex> by reasonne <lb/>
            they weare open for Commerce. Soe peace restoringe to his <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">highnes</hi> provinces the freedome of the <del rend="strikethrough">same</del> <add place="above">Sea</add> will w<ex>i</ex>th that libertie <lb/>
            reverte a parte of that commerce they loste by warre. /. As warre <lb/>
            by takinge <hi rend="italic">Antwerpe </hi>prisoner enlardged the liberties of <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Anstardame</hi>: soe peace by Settinge <hi rend="italic">Antwerpe </hi>free will <lb/>
            reduce the liberties of <hi rend="italic">Ansterdame</hi> thoughe not confine them <lb/>
            in the narrowe bowndes and lymitts w<ex>hi</ex>ch they hadd before the<del rend="strikethrough">y</del> <lb/>
            warre into the lesser scoepe. /. For the vnited provinces <lb/>
            in this theire present State are like a traded Cittie w<ex>hi</ex>ch florisheth <lb/>
            the more because noe other corporac<ex>i</ex>on sealed on the passage <lb/>
            hathe the priveledge and libertie to share the frequentation of <lb/>
            the waie / But when a second Corporac<ex>i</ex>on shall advaunce <lb/>
            itselfe vpon the passage of the firste (ambitious to the <lb/>
            same prerogative and benefitt) the building<ex>es</ex> and erections <lb/>
            of the seconde raisd w<ex>i</ex>th substaunces detracted from the firste <lb/>
            It followes that as the seconde ryseth the firste declines w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            kynde of growth shoets vpp to a predominate hight sonest <lb/>
            of <hi rend="italic">Anie</hi>. ./ . 3  There are reasons of com<ex>m</ex>oditie and conveniencie <lb/>
            (as a better State and better ayre) to drawe the Staples of <lb/>
            forraine commodities to the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> syde, and wheather <lb/>
            the <hi rend="italic">Staples</hi> goe of suche comodities as are of vniuersall
            <pb n="125v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f125v/add_ms_11600_f125v.jpg"/>
            trade and vse the concourse com<ex>m</ex>onlie of other Merchants <lb/>
            followes and his increase of <hi rend="italic">Shippinge</hi> will growe to the <lb/>
            States preiudice the more by reason it beinge to be made <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thin the <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi> will be of an aunswerable buildinge <lb/>
            for theire Seas his Marriners experienced in theire havens <lb/>
            and landinge places and his State of a prepared readines <lb/>
            to take the offer of opertunitie for Attempt. And as for <lb/>
            money a peace will furnishe the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>syde before <lb/>
            the States. Firste because the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> debts I coniecture <lb/>
            will in the mutuall league betweene his highnes and the <lb/>
            kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi> be cutt of whereas the States engaged <lb/>
            to theire confederats and freends, the satisfacc<ex>i</ex>on of theire <lb/>
            debt<ex>es</ex> will expend a good p<ex>ar</ex>te of theire revenewe while <lb/>
            in the meane tyme his highnes shalbe layinge vpp in <lb/>
            stoere . /.  2    The States havinge the greater cause to <lb/>
            suspect the protestac<ex>i</ex>on of sinceritie concerninge peace <lb/>
            are bounde in providence to holde a greater guarde <lb/>
            vppon theire frontiers then his highnes shall on his <lb/>
            whereby theire chardge will exceade his.  3.  The <lb/>
            States haue noe other subiect of revenewe then the <lb/>
            vnited provinc<ex>es</ex>. whereas the Archeduke besides his <lb/>
            provinces (contracted) w<ex>i</ex>th the kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spayne</hi> <lb/>
            shall haue the goulde of <hi rend="italic">India</hi> to his addic<ex>i</ex>on. /
         </p>
         <p>
            4	The kinge of <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>by reason of his vniu<ex>er</ex>sall <lb/>
            peace transportinge his treasure safelie home will <lb/>
            in a fewe yeares growe riche and hable for a second <lb/>
            warre yf other meanes and instrum<ex>en</ex>ts Concurre. ./. <lb/>
            And theese advantages synce the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>pro=<lb break="no"/>
            vinc<ex>es</ex> are like to be transmitted to the handes of <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>vpon his <hi rend="italic">highnes </hi>death, will questionlesse
            <pb n="126r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f126r/add_ms_11600_f126r.jpg"/>
            bee entertaind and prosecuted w<ex>i</ex>th the best of industrie. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            Thus it appeares theese twoe supplies of Shippes and money A <lb/>
            peace will promise to advaunce to him: but yet (mee thinckes) <lb/>
            not soe sufficientlie as to produce him to a seconde warre unlesse <lb/>
            togeather w<ex>i</ex>th his supplies, diuision and improuidence possesse <lb/>
            the vnited provinces. or that the accumulac<ex>i</ex>on of his power <lb/>
            and <del rend="strikethrough">wheather</del> <add place="above">wealth</add> will make him hable to contest and warre w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            Greate <hi rend="italic">Brittaine</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fraunce</hi>. besides w<ex>hi</ex>ch though I hoepe will <lb/>
            neu<ex>er</ex> bee Yet are they point<ex>es</ex> of serious consequence and subiect for <lb/>
            the moste elected ripest Iudgem<ex>en</ex>ts w<ex>i</ex>th the verie sowle of prudence <lb/>
            to consulte vppon. /.  But so longe as they continewe in a faithfull <lb/>
            vnitie of State and that the powers of theire contingences &amp;amp; confederat<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            be not dishabled to protect theire owne difensiue instrum<ex>en</ex>ts may stand <lb/>
            in competent habilitie as well in peace as warre. /.  Firste <lb/>
            Because the States haue more havens for com<ex>m</ex>erce then his <hi rend="italic">Highnes</hi> <lb/>
            and therefore more meanes to increase Shippinge. ./.
         </p>
         <p>
            2	The States provinc<ex>es</ex> haue one other meanes and preservac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of Navigac<ex>i</ex>on namelie fishinge w<ex>hi</ex>ch the Archeduke cannot <lb/>
            soe plentifullie accomodate his provinc<ex>es</ex> w<ex>i</ex>th all. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            3	The States comaunde the Channell of <hi rend="italic">Antwerpe</hi> the Archduk <lb/>
            cheefest Towne of Marte. w<ex>hi</ex>ch is a bridle that discreetely <lb/>
            mannaged will muche assiste the holdinge of the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> <lb/>
            whole estate in good devotion to the peace. /
         </p>
         <p>
            4	The States are before hand and alreadie furnished of a power <lb/>
            att sea. whereas his highnes is to beginne, Soe that his steppes <lb/>
            and proseading<ex>es</ex> prudentlie and diligentlie obserued they maie <lb/>
            easelie provide that his strength and power at Sea shall <lb/>
            neu<ex>er</ex> growe to exceade theires. ./ . And as for money and <lb/>
            other assistanc<ex>es</ex> out of <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> they shall arriue w<ex>hi</ex>ch cause <lb/>
            of dowbt to undertake a second warre vnlesse I saie his <lb/>
            power be of a ioynte habilitie to warre againste the other.
            <pb n="126v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f126v/add_ms_11600_f126v.jpg"/>
            mightiest potents of <hi rend="italic">Christendome</hi> because they are som<ex>m</ex>e potentat<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            of good habilitie to gyve a good addic<ex>i</ex>on and assistance to the <lb/>
            States, whoe by contingencie of Seate and other nearenesses <lb/>
            are interessed in the States prosperitie and haue cause to <lb/>
            add a supportac<ex>i</ex>on to prevent the Spanish triumphe ou<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            them and then the freenes of theire State dischardginge <lb/>
            theire defensive warre of all the imputac<ex>i</ex>ons of vnlaw=<lb break="no"/>
            fullnes w<ex>hi</ex>ch questionles haue heeretofore suspended theire <lb/>
            assistanc<ex>es</ex> betweene dowbt and resoluc<ex>i</ex>on will promise <lb/>
            to obtaine protections for them more resolued and confident <lb/>
            Nowe touchinge practizes to worke diuision in the con=<lb break="no"/>
            stituc<ex>i</ex>on of theire State. ./ .
         </p>
         <p>
            There lurkes the daungerossest ill, concerning the vnited <lb/>
            provinc<ex>es</ex> in p<ex>ar</ex>ticular that canne bee hidden in this rancke <lb/>
            and ou<ex>er</ex>growinge goodnes of a peace yet not of suche <lb/>
            necessitie alone as to p<ex>er</ex>swade them to refuse an honorable <lb/>
            peace since the p<ex>re</ex>vention of that p<ex>er</ex>ill maie by the <lb/>
            wisdomes of theire gou<ex>er</ex>ment and Counsaile be p<ex>er</ex>formed <lb/>
            soe longe as God whoe hetherto hath stoede vppon theire <lb/>
            side shall not oppose him selfe. /. To conclude my <lb/>
            discourse vpon this question, wheather the States <lb/>
            shoulde effecte a peace vppon this offer of his <hi rend="italic">Highnesses</hi> <lb/>
         </p>
         <p>
            The substaunce of my voyce is this. A peace will <lb/>
            furnishe <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>w<ex>i</ex>th more habilities then  now hee hath <lb/>
            As for the States thoughe there bee some hoepe<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>  that <lb/>
            theire defence will not by peace be vtterly dishabled <lb/>
            yet questionles it will in manie points dishable there <lb/>
            offencive warre. not onlie by the tyme and meanes <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi> shall thereby haue to fortefie himselfe: <lb/>
            but alsoe by dissoluinge the consitutc<ex>i</ex>on of there p<ex>re</ex>sent <lb/>
            instrum<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex> and purposes, w<ex>hi</ex>ch discontracted once will
            <pb n="127r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f127r/add_ms_11600_f127r.jpg"/>
            hardlie bee reduced to theire vnited bodie againe. And howsoeu<ex>er</ex> the entent <lb/>
            maie proue will gyue theire opposite encouragem<ex>en</ex>ts and incitac<ex>i</ex>ons to <lb/>
            a second warre. /. A gallant actiue warre directed and sett forward <lb/>
            therefore w<ex>i</ex>th a mynde and probabilitie of meanes to conquere woulde <lb/>
            bee the more assured course. Yet howsoeu<ex>er</ex> they haue reason to referr <lb/>
            the makinge of theire resoluc<ex>i</ex>ons to the counsaile of thoese powers <lb/>
            by whose protecc<ex>i</ex>ons and assistanc<ex>es</ex> next vnder God they haue <lb/>
            subsisted heatherto. . /.
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">An amplificac<ex>i</ex>on </hi>of discourse concerninge practizes that maie tend <lb/>
            to the diuision and dissoluinge of the constituc<ex>i</ex>on of the vnited prouinc<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            in the Condic<ex>i</ex>on and State of peace yf it bee brought to passe. ./.
         </p>
         <p>
            If anie misterie be meant to make diuision in the constituc<ex>i</ex>on of the <lb/>
            States. the Stratagematist<ex>es</ex> and Ingeners. of Hell. maie plott <lb/>
            theire practices into two kindes ./.  i <hi rend="italic">Insinuac<ex>i</ex>on</hi> .2. <hi rend="italic">Violence</hi>.
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Insinuation </hi>well prevented, <hi rend="italic">Violence </hi>is halfe defeated because <lb/>
            insinuac<ex>i</ex>on woerkes the gen<ex>er</ex>all pointe more lardgelie then violence <lb/>
            prepares her waies, and serves to frame and forge her instruments <lb/>
            to worke w<ex>i</ex>th all: as Traitors to betraie men of State: <hi rend="italic">Shipping</hi> <lb/>
            and fortifficac<ex>i</ex>on the principall subiect<ex>es</ex> in the vnited provinces <lb/>
            that <hi rend="italic">violence </hi>woulde worke vpon to distrucc<ex>i</ex>on wracke and <lb/>
            Surprise. ./.  But for there full defeate: no dowbt the <hi rend="italic">Iustic</hi> <lb/>
            of God w<ex>hi</ex>ch hath expressed his wrath in miracles againste the <lb/>
            works of suche abhominable practizes will neu<ex>er</ex> suffer them <lb/>
            to attaine to theire desyred end. /.  <hi rend="italic">Insinuation</hi> maie tend to the <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thdrawinge of theire <hi rend="italic">Merchants</hi>. 2 devidinge theire vnitie of <lb/>
            State.  3 possessinge them selues of some fortifications of <lb/>
            importance to an offensiue warre./. The drawinge awaie <lb/>
            of theire Merchant<ex>es</ex> maie be endeuoured by practisinge occasions <lb/>
            of discontentment in them touchinge there condic<ex>i</ex>ons w<ex>i</ex>th the States <lb/>
            and settinge obiect<ex>es</ex> of Encouragem<ex>en</ex>t and attracc<ex>i</ex>on before them <lb/>
            on the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> syde./.   Touchinge the better prevention <lb/>
            whereof theire cautions amonge other are not altogeather voyde <lb/>
            of vse. ./.  That the retractac<ex>i</ex>on and dissoluinge of theire
            <pb n="127v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f127v/add_ms_11600_f127v.jpg"/>
             erected companie of Marchants begett noe evill discontentm<ex>en</ex>t <lb/>
            in the participants whoese affecc<ex>i</ex>ons they haue reason to <lb/>
            continewe devoted to the State. ./.  2. That good reser=<lb break="no"/>
            uation of contentm<ex>en</ex>ts bee provided for theire owne Townes <lb/>
            of Traffique to continewe theire establishd corporac<ex>i</ex>ons. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            3	That they be carefull to continewe the Staples of suche <lb/>
            Forraine comodities as are of vniu<ex>er</ex>sall trade and vse <lb/>
            properlie to theire owne Townes, for wheather the Staples <lb/>
            goe of suche commodities the concourse com<ex>m</ex>onlie of other <lb/>
            marchants followes. / .4: That whereas <del rend="strikethrough">the </del>diuerse of <lb/>
            the substantiall inhabitants of the vnited provinces haue <lb/>
            interest in the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi> syde by right of theire former <lb/>
            possessions good heede be taken leaste vnder cullor of satisfa <lb/>
            ction suche men on whose habilitie the State muche dependes <lb/>
            be not alienated. ./.  The diuision of theere vnited state <lb/>
            maie be practised by the secrett plotts of vndermyninge <lb/>
            papists. by the temptac<ex>i</ex>on of corruptinge goulde by the <lb/>
            publique work<ex>es</ex> of ostentac<ex>i</ex>on tendinge to make the people
         </p>
         <p>
            discontented w<ex>i</ex>th theire owne condic<ex>i</ex>ons and to steale awaie <lb/>
            theire hartes. /.  Towards the prevention whereof <lb/>
            these Articles amonge manie other seeme not muche <lb/>
            impertinent. /  1 That true religion be w<ex>i</ex>th faithfull <lb/>
            zeale and vigilance maintained and bent soe farre as <lb/>
            Christian moderac<ex>i</ex>on will admitt against the dangerous <lb/>
            insinuac<ex>i</ex>ons of seditious <hi rend="italic">Romanist<ex>es</ex>
                </hi>. a faction that <lb/>
            will still be turbulentlie stirringe vpp combustions <lb/>
            to maintaine a life and warmenes in the shakinge Ague <lb/>
            and consumption of theire churche. /.  2. That A <lb/>
            prudent eye be helde vpon the correspondencies and <lb/>
            passages of publique persons w<ex>i</ex>th the other side. . / .
         </p>
         <p>
            3	That while theire State continewe an <hi rend="italic">Aristocratic</hi> no <lb/>
            one be gyven more power in gou<ex>er</ex>m<ex>en</ex>t thereof then maie <lb/>
            securelie be revoked. . / .
         </p>
         <pb n="128r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f128r/add_ms_11600_f128r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            4	That noe conception be produced but buried in the wombe that would <lb/>
            devide the vnited provinc<ex>es</ex> into pluralitie of Gouerments and all <lb/>
            occasions ministred and entertained that may confirm theire <lb/>
            present vnitie. / .  5. That whereas they are to raise theire moneis <lb/>
            on the people (onelie) of theire provinc<ex>es</ex> the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes</hi>. his more <lb/>
            dependentlie vpon the borrowed Mynes of  <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>, They therefore <lb/>
            provide that when theire Commons shall compare there impositions <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th those of his <hi rend="italic">Highnes </hi>and fynde theire owne more heavie there <lb/>
            scence of the burthen cause not the daungerous offices of miscon=<lb break="no"/>
            structions murmurings and discontentm<ex>en</ex>t<ex>es</ex>  / 6. That synce <lb/>
            they are engaged to theire assistanc<ex>es</ex> and confederat<ex>es</ex>. theire present <lb/>
            imposic<ex>i</ex>ons therefore hauinge first exprest theire reasons of p<ex>er</ex>swasion <lb/>
            for the same. be still continewed till theire sum<ex>m</ex>es be raised. And in <lb/>
            the raisinge of those som<ex>m</ex>es theire wisdomes maie togeather w<ex>ith</ex> <lb/>
            respect vnto that end converte the worke w<ex>i</ex>th good vse to the <lb/>
            aduauncem<ex>en</ex>t of theire provisionall habilities. For nowe the <lb/>
            people are inured to it the custome makes it easie digestable <lb/>
            the rather when they doe for:see the ende thereof approchinge <lb/>
            dailie nearer them. Whereas to intermitt cessac<ex>i</ex>on of the taxe <lb/>
            and then to innovate the same a newe will w<ex>i</ex>th the taste of <lb/>
            former sweetnes begett distast of that displeasingnes and <lb/>
            gyue aspirers and conspirers leave and incouragement<ex>es</ex> <lb/>
            to worke vppon discontented multitude. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            To dispossesse the States of Fortificac<ex>i</ex>ons important to an <lb/>
            offensiue warre for <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>thoughe Violence maie claime <lb/>
            the stronger hande yet insinuation labours to assiste the <lb/>
            worke as appeares in the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>desier to chaunge <lb/>
            some Townes w<ex>hi</ex>ch hee expresseth in a clause incerted <lb/>
            in his offer by the waie. /.
         </p>
         <p>
            To provide against the daunger of suche praactices it <lb/>
            behoues them. . /. Firste that the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>desier <lb/>
            to chaunge som<ex>m</ex>e Townes be lefte vnsatisfied. . / .
         </p>
         <pb n="128v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f128v/add_ms_11600_f128v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            For though to make exchaunge of suche particulars as either side <lb/>
            is nowe possessed of in the provinces whose greater p<ex>ar</ex>te <lb/>
            and tytle is subiect to the contrarie side be in com<ex>m</ex>on sence <lb/>
            a fitt and reasonable graunte because that eache syde then <lb/>
            shall haue the provinc<ex>es</ex> hee beares the title of intirelie free <lb/>
            from forraine interest. Yet to make suche an exchaunge <lb/>
            would gyve his <hi rend="italic">Highnes </hi>lardge advantage for a second warre <lb/>
            and infinitelie <add place="above">to <ex>th</ex>e</add> damage of the States. / 
         </p>
         <p>
            For <hi rend="italic">Sluice Bergin vp soome </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Breda </hi>w<ex>i</ex>th other fortes <lb/>
            and holdes vpon the Coastes are like to be the places that <lb/>
            his <hi rend="italic">Highnes </hi>bendes his cheefest ayme vppon because they <lb/>
            are the meanes, weare hee possessed of them to free his <lb/>
            cheefeste provinces. of daungerous invations to in=<lb break="no"/>
            large his Maryntine affaires and in tyme to vndermyne <lb/>
            the state of the neighbour <hi rend="italic">Ilandes </hi>advantages that <lb/>
            well persued and seconded will threaten to subdue the <lb/>
            States. / .  Whereas the <hi rend="italic">Archedukes </hi>foetinge in the <lb/>
            States provinces importes not soe muche benefitt to <lb/>
            him or preiudice to them as theires in his. were it returned <lb/>
            into his handes. / .  And for the reservac<ex>i</ex>on of thoese <lb/>
            theire possessions the States maie freely stande, synce if <lb/>
            his highnes obserues the sence of his offer. the States ex=<lb break="no"/>
            ception of that his inference shall noe waie interupt <lb/>
            the course of treatie nor obstructe the passages of peace <lb/>
            But for the apparant lawfullnes in holdinge those <lb/>
            Townes that lye w<ex>i</ex>thin the Archedukes provinces. iudiciall <lb/>
            care ought to be had that by a publique Acte they bee <lb/>
            depropriated from the claime and tytle of the provinces <lb/>
            wherein they lye and corporate in the States proprietie <lb/>
            leaste yf his <hi rend="italic">Highnes </hi>or his successors tytle in <hi rend="italic">Capite</hi>
            <pb n="129r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f129r/add_ms_11600_f129r.jpg"/>
             and gen<ex>er</ex>allie to the provinces of <hi rend="italic">Brabante</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Flaunders</hi> &amp;amp;c. bee assented <lb/>
            by the States it comprehendes thoese places and soe reserues a lawfull <lb/>
            nes. to him or them vppon accasion of advantage ro reviue theire <lb/>
            claime to them as an induction to a faarther warre. . / .
         </p>
         <p>
            That to distande theire Armie they proceade noe faster then <lb/>
            maie continewe them a strength to holde proporc<ex>i</ex>on w<ex>i</ex>th his <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">highnes</hi> reserued troapes. / .  That faithfull and sufficient <lb/>
            Garrisons bee continewed in the important frontiers especiallie <lb/>
            yf the Corporac<ex>i</ex>ons maie be suspected of vnsoundnes to theire <lb/>
            State: Yet soe that togeather w<ex>i</ex>th theire guardes they use <del rend="strikethrough">and </del>
                <add place="above">an</add> <lb/>
            industrie to worke conformance of Affection. where vnsoundnes <lb/>
            is for to containe theire bodies when they are diuided in theire <lb/>
            mindes maintaine a nourishm<ex>en</ex>t in theire desire to chaunge. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            And to conclude the assurance of the reste it seemes to beare a <lb/>
            good aspect to them. that they indeauour w<ex>i</ex>th a studious <lb/>
            industrie to contract them selues w<ex>i</ex>th a confederate whose amitie <lb/>
            by reason of the stabilitie of the State Neighbourhoed of <lb/>
            Seate correspondence of power and conformancie of religion <lb/>
            maie gyve them the moste sure hable readie and faithfull <lb/>
            assistance / That yf the sure establishm<ex>en</ex>t of theire peace maie
         </p>
         <p>
            by the hable protecc<ex>i</ex>on of some other principallitie be better <lb/>
            p<ex>er</ex>formed then by them selues in their <hi rend="italic">Aristocratie</hi>: there free <lb/>
            condic<ex>i</ex>on be not a temptinge obiecte of Ambition to diuerte <lb/>
            theire eies of providence and due respecte w<ex>i</ex>th loue of selfe <lb/>
            desiringe rule from thate estate vnder whose gou<ex>er</ex>nment <lb/>
            they maye more safelie and assuredlie subsiste. . / .
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
               protection is <lb/>
               p<ex>er</ex>formed by one <lb/>
               of power of reall <lb/>
               Mightines in prin <lb/>
               cipallity, so thatt <lb/>
               My meaning as <lb/>
               Not a translation <lb/>
               of their state <lb/>
               into another: Name <lb/>
               onely a forme of <lb/>
               Gouernment
            </add>
            Lastlie touchinge the choise admitted them wheather for <lb/>
            a Truce or a perpetuall peace. / . <lb/>
         </p>
         <pb n="129v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f129v/add_ms_11600_f129v.jpg"/>
         <p>
            A Truice or suspention of Armes maintaines a vigilance <lb/>
            more liuelie for the preseruation of theire State then A <lb/>
            perpetuall peace. And makes the com<ex>m</ex>on disposic<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            of the lande more willinglie imparte itselfe and stoepe <lb/>
            to what shall iustlie be imposed, because they see <lb/>
            apparant reasonne to provide <add place="above">for</add> theire defence whereas <lb/>
            the<del rend="strikethrough">
                    <unclear/>
                </del> apprehention of perpetuall peace flatters the <lb/>
            people to securetie and moeues them easelie to misconture <lb/>
            any Acte of providence that pleaseth not the taste of <lb/>
            comon sence. besides a truice though seeminge to confine <lb/>
            the peace reviveth not a warre the soener for that lymmitt <lb/>
            nor canne the promise of perpetuall peace assure a peace <lb/>
            vnto the States the longer for that promise synce whensoeu<ex>er</ex> <lb/>
            good advantages shall by the <hi rend="italic">Spanish </hi>syde be founde <hi rend="italic">Spaines <lb/>
            </hi>loue and <hi rend="italic">Roemes </hi>fidelitie are like to breake awaie through <lb/>
            anie promise of a peace to warre. And yett thoughe truice <lb/>
            confines the peace soe longe as the States remaine in <lb/>
            theire habilitie they maie expecte a further treatie <lb/>
            even from <hi rend="italic">Spaine </hi>it selfe to gyue enlargement to <lb/>
            the Truice and soe continewe. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            If then a Truice will admitt as reall confirmation <lb/>
            to the publique Acte that shalbe made to ratefie <lb/>
            the freenes of theire State yt seemes of worthe to <lb/>
            bee preferred. . /        
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f106v/add_ms_11600_f106v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f107r/add_ms_11600_f107r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="3" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f107v/add_ms_11600_f107v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="4" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f108r/add_ms_11600_f108r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="5" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f108v/add_ms_11600_f108v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="6" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f109r/add_ms_11600_f109r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="7" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f109v/add_ms_11600_f109v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="8" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f110r/add_ms_11600_f110r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="9" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f110v/add_ms_11600_f110v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="10" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f111r/add_ms_11600_f111r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="11" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f111v/add_ms_11600_f111v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="12" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f112r/add_ms_11600_f112r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="13" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f112v/add_ms_11600_f112v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="14" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f113r/add_ms_11600_f113r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="15" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f113v/add_ms_11600_f113v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="16" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f114r/add_ms_11600_f114r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="17" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f114v/add_ms_11600_f114v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="18" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f115r/add_ms_11600_f115r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="19" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f115v/add_ms_11600_f115v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="20" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f116r/add_ms_11600_f116r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="21" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f116v/add_ms_11600_f116v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="22" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f117r/add_ms_11600_f117r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="23" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f117v/add_ms_11600_f117v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="24" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f118r/add_ms_11600_f118r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="25" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f118v/add_ms_11600_f118v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="26" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f119r/add_ms_11600_f119r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="27" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f119v/add_ms_11600_f119v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="28" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f120r/add_ms_11600_f120r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="29" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f120v/add_ms_11600_f120v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="30" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f121r/add_ms_11600_f121r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="31" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f121v/add_ms_11600_f121v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="32" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f122r/add_ms_11600_f122r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="33" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f122v/add_ms_11600_f122v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="34" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f123r/add_ms_11600_f123r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="35" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f123v/add_ms_11600_f123v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="36" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f124r/add_ms_11600_f124r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="37" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f124v/add_ms_11600_f124v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="38" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f125r/add_ms_11600_f125r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="39" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f125v/add_ms_11600_f125v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="40" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f126r/add_ms_11600_f126r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="41" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f126v/add_ms_11600_f126v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="42" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f127r/add_ms_11600_f127r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="43" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f127v/add_ms_11600_f127v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="44" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f128r/add_ms_11600_f128r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="45" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f128v/add_ms_11600_f128v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="46" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f129r/add_ms_11600_f129r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="47" url="/bl/add_ms_11600/add_ms_11600_f129v/add_ms_11600_f129v.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>