<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Petition for His Brother's Freedom</title>
            <author>
               <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0202">Francis Phellips</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="VA">
                    <name>Victoria Anker</name>
                    <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/NorfRO_MC_1123_386X5.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="NorfRO_MC_1123_386X5">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>Norwich</settlement>
               <repository>Norfolk Record Office</repository>
               <collection/>
               <idno>MC 1/123, 386X5</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">Norfolk Record Office,  MC 1/123, 386X5</p>
            </msDesc>
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated">
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLAddMS40838.xml">British Library, Additional MS 40838, ff. 54r–56v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLAddMS4108.xml">British Library, Additional MS 4108, ff. 48r–50v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLAddMS44848.xml">British Library, Additional MS 44848, ff. 93r–95v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLAddMS69394.xml">British Library, Additional MS 69394, ff. 89v–93v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHargraveMS226.xml">British Library, Hargrave MS 226, ff. 283r–290r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHarleyMS3638.xml">British Library, Harley MS 3638, ff. 93r–98r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHarleyMS444.xml">British Library, Harley MS 444, ff. 180r–184v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHarleyMS4888.xml">British Library, Harley MS 4888, ff. 257x–258x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLHarleyMS6865.xml">British Library, Harley MS 6865, ff. 272r–275x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLLansdowneMS1232.xml">British Library, Lansdowne MS 1232, ff. 11r–14v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Add_MS_12511.xml">British Library, Additional MS 12511, ff. 49r–51v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Add_MS_25707.xml">British Library, Additional MS 25707, ff. 139r–141r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Add_MS_34217.xml">British Library, Additional MS 34217, ff. 32r–v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Add_MS_72421.xml">British Library, Additional MS 72421, ff. 46r–49v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Harley_MS_1221.xml">British Library, Harley MS 1221, ff. 106r–108r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Harley_MS_2232.xml">British Library, Harley MS 2232, ff. 69r–72v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Stowe_MS_180.xml">British Library, Stowe MS 180, ff. 49x–50x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Beinecke_Osborn_b32.xml">Beinecke Library, Osborn b32, pp106–113</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Ashmole_749.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Ashmole 749, item 5, 1–6</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Eng_hist_e_28.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Eng. hist. e. 28, ff. 54–62</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Rawlinson_B_151.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Rawlinson B 151, ff. 47v–48r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Tanner_264.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Tanner 264, ff. 28r–29v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Tanner_82.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Tanner 82, ff. 135v–139v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/CUL_MS_Ee523.xml">Cambridge University Library,  MS Ee.5.23, pp478–480</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/CUL_MS_Mm633.xml">Cambridge University Library,  MS Mm.6.33, ff. 129r–133r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Folger_MS_V_b_277.xml">Folger Shakespeare Library,  MS V.b.277, ff. 226r–229r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Folger_MS_V_b_303.xml">Folger Shakespeare Library,  MS V.b.303, pp239–241</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Folger_MS_V_b_303.xml">Folger Shakespeare Library,  MS V.b.303, pp329–333</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Huntington_HM_36836.xml">Huntington Library,  HM 36836, ff. 30–43</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Inner_Temple_Petyt_MS_538_18.xml">Inner Temple Library, Petyt MS 538/18, f. 186x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/LSA_MS_291.xml">London Society of Antiquaries,  MS 291, ff. 18r–22r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/NUL_Cl_LP_21.xml">Nottingham University Library, Cl LP 21, ff3</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/St_Johns_College_Cambridge_MS_K56.xml">St John's College,  MS K.56, item 52</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/St_Johns_College_Cambridge_MS_K56.xml">St John's College,  MS K.56, item 53</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/TNA_SP_14_129.xml">The National Archives,  SP 14/129, /21 [ff.28r–29r]</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/University_College_Oxford_MS_152.xml">University College,  MS 152 [on deposit at the Bodleian], ff. 204–209</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Woburn_Abbey_MS_19.xml">Woburn Abbey,  MS 19, pp235–237</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1622">1622</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
            <language ident="LA">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term>petition</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-09-24" who="#RB" status="drafted"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#NM" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="[1r]"/>
         <head rend="align-centre">
            To the Kinges most excellent Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie
         </head>
         <p rend="outdent">
            Most dread soveraigne
         </p>
         <p>
            If the thrones of heaven and earth were to be solicited one and the same ways, I shoul<supplied reason="damage">d</supplied> <lb/>
            haue learned by my often prayeng to God for yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie how to praye to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie for <lb/>
            others: Butthe liturgies of the churche and Court ar diferent, as in manye other <lb/>
            poyntes so in this especiallye, that in the one there ys not so poor e a siner, but maye <lb/>
            offer his vowes immediatlye to the Almightye, wheras in the other a right loyall subiect <lb/>
            maye poure out his soule in vaye without <foreign xml:lang="la">
                    <hi rend="italic">ora pro nobis</hi>
                </foreign>: Now suche is the obscure <lb/>
            condition of yo<ex>u</ex>r humble supp<ex>lian</ex>t, as I knowe no <hi rend="italic">saint</hi> about the sacred person, to whome <add place="above">I can</add> <lb/>
            addresse my orisons, or on whose mediations I dare repose the least assurance Let it <lb/>
            therfore be lawfull for me in this extraordinarye occasion, to passe the ordinarye formes, <lb/>
            and raisinge my spiritt aboue vnertainties, fixt my entire faith vpon yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties suprea<add place="above">m</add>e <lb/>
            goodnesse, which is and ever ought to be esteemed the best Tribunal and best sanctuary <lb/>
            for a good subiect: But how good soever my cause be, it would be high presumption <lb/>
            in me to stand vpon it, I haue therfore rather chosen to cast my selfe at yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties feete, from <lb/>
            whence I would not willinglie rise, but there remaine a monument of sorrowe and <lb/>
            humilitye, till I had obtayned some gracious answere to my petic<ex>i</ex>on: For though yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties thoughtes cannot descend so lowe, as to conceyve how much it importes a distressed <lb/>
            subiect to be releived or neglected, yet yow maye be pleased to beleeve, that we ar <lb/>
            as highlye affected, and as much anguished, with the extreamities that presse o<ex>u</ex>r little <lb/>
            fortunes, as Princes or with theires: I speake not not of anye pride I take in comparing <lb/>
            small thinges with great, but onelye <del rend="strikethrough">d</del>to dispose yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>es</ex>tie: to a favorable construction of my <lb/>
            wordes, if they seeme overcharged with zeale and affection, or to expresse more <lb/>
            earnestnesse then perhappes yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie maye thinke the businesse merittes: For <lb/>
            as my selfe valewes yt, the sute I am to make to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie, is no sleight one, but <lb/>
            maye safelye be graunted without the trouble of <hi rend="italic">Referees</hi>, for as I dare <lb/>
            assure your Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie, vpon my life, it is neither against the the lawes of yo<ex>u</ex>r kingdome nor, <lb/>
            will diminishe anye of yo<ex>u</ex>r royall treasure, either that of yo<ex>u</ex>r coffers or that of yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            peoples hartes, it being an Act of clemencye, or rather a word, for even that will <lb/>
            serve to create in yo<ex>u</ex>r poore distressed suppl<ex>ican</ex>t and a hew hart, and send him awaye <lb/>
            as full of contentude as he is now of greife and despaire: Nor is it for my selfe <lb/>
            that I thus importune yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties grace, but for one that is farre more worthy, and in <lb/>
            whome all that I am consistes, my deare and onely brother, who (by I know not <lb/>
            what misfortune) hath fallen or rather bene pusht, into yo<ex>u</ex>r high displeasure, <lb/>
            not in darke and crooked wayes (such as corrupt and ill affected subiectes vse <lb/>
            to reade) which both him selfe and all good Englishmen (that know not the privye <lb/>
            patche of the court) would haue sworne had led most safelye and most directlye <lb/>
            to yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties service: From yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties displeasure (then which there needes noe <lb/>
            other invenc<ex>i</ex>on to crucifie a generous and honest mynded subiect) hath yssued <lb/>
            and bene derived vppon him, a whole torment of exemplarie punishment, wherin <lb/>
            his reputation, his person, and estate haue greivouslye suffered: For having <lb/>
            vpon the last recesse of parliament retired him selfe to his poore home in the <lb/>
            Cuntrye, with hope to haue breathed a while after the troublesome affaires, <lb/>
            and still breathing nothing but yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties service, <add place="above">he</add> was sent for ere he had <lb/>
            finished his <hi rend="italic">Christ-masse</hi> by a <hi rend="italic">Sergeant</hi> at Armes, who arrested him in <lb/>
            his owne house with as much terror as belonges to the apprehension of <lb/>
            Treason it selfe: but thankes be to God his concience never started, and <lb/>
            for his obedience, he well shewed it was not in the power of any authoritye to <lb/>
            surprise it, For at the instant without asking so muche as a mynutes tyme <lb/>
            of resolution, he rendred himselfe to the offices discretion, who according to <lb/>
            his direction brought him vp a captive, and presented him to the councell <lb/>
            table as a dilinquent, From whence he was assoone comitted to the tower, where <lb/>
            he hath ever since bene kept close prisoner, and that with so straight a hand, as his deere <lb/>
            beloved wife and my selfe, having sometyme since an vrgeant and vnfayned occasion <lb/>
            to speake with him, about some private businesse of his famylie, and thervppon makin<supplied reason="damage">g</supplied> <lb/>
            humble sute vnto the Lordes of yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties most ho<ex>noura</ex>
                <sic>lbe</sic> privye councell for the favor of accesse, <lb/>
            we were to our great discomfortes denyed, by reaso as their Lo<ex>rdsh</ex>ips were then pleased to <lb/>
            declare vnto vs, that he had not then fullye satisfied, yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie in some pointes, which is so <lb/>
            farre from being his fault, that I dare saye it is the greatest part of his affliction that he 
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">sees</fw>
            <pb n="[1v]"/>
            sees himself debarred from the meanes of doing it: The Lo<ex>rd</ex> Comissioners that were <lb/>
            appointed by yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>es</ex>tie to examyne his offence, since the first weeke of his imprisonment <lb/>
            haue not done him the honor to be with him, by which meanes not onlye his bodye <del rend="strikethrough">th</del> but the <lb/>
            best part of his mind namelye his humble invenc<ex>i</ex>ons are kept in restraint./ <lb/>
            May it therfore please yo<ex>u</ex>r most excellent ma<ex>jes</ex>tie now at the <del rend="strikethrough">er</del> lengthe after 3 moenthes <lb/>
            extreame durance, to ordayne some such course of expedition in this cause, as may <lb/>
            stand with yo<ex>u</ex>r iustice and yet not avert yo<ex>u</ex>r mercye, either of them will serve, o<ex>u</ex>r turnes <lb/>
            but that which is most agreable to yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties royall and gratious inclination will <lb/>
            best accomplishe o<ex>u</ex>r desires: To live still in close prison is all one as to be buryed <lb/>
            alive, and for a man that hath anye hope of salvation it were better to pray for <lb/>
            the daye of iudgment then to lye languishing in such waking miserye: yet not <lb/>
            ours but yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties will be done, for if in yo<ex>u</ex>r princely wisdome yow shall not thinke <lb/>
            it so soone to restore him to his fomer Condic<ex>i</ex>on, or to accept the frutes of his <lb/>
            correction (A humble and penitent submission for his <add place="above">vn</add>
                <hi rend="underline">happinesse</hi> in offending <lb/>
            yo<ex>o</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie) which I assure my selfe is long since ripe and growne to full <lb/>
            proporc<ex>i</ex>on, in so forward an affection and so propper for all manner of loyall <lb/>
            duties as he hath ever bene, If I saye it be not yett tyme to shew mercye, <lb/>
            but that he must still remayne within the walles of bondage, to expiate what <lb/>
            he did within these of priviledge, my hope is that he who will dye at any time <lb/>
            for yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties service, will find patience to live any where for yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>ies</ex>ties <lb/>
            pleasure, onelye let me beseech yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie againe and againe, not to denye you<ex>r</ex> <lb/>
            most humble and obedient subiecte that mitigation of rigor of his suffering, <lb/>
            so farre as to graunt him the libertye of the tower, and that he may longer <lb/>
            groane vnder the burthen of the Incomodityes, which daylie preiudice <lb/>
            his health and fortunes in a higher degree I beleeve then yor ma<ex>jes</ex>tie either <lb/>
            knowes or intendes./
         </p>
         <p>
            I am the more bold to importune yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie in this point of favor bycause it <lb/>
            concernes my owne good &amp; preservacon, for yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie shall daigne to vnder=<lb break="no"/>
            stand, that I haue noe meanes to live yo<ex>u</ex>r subiect, but what proceedes <lb/>
            from his brotherlye loue and bountye, so as if I maye not be suffered <lb/>
            to goe vnto him, and receyve order for my mayntenance, I know none <lb/>
            but o<ex>u</ex>r father which art in heaven, of whome I can begg my dailye bread; <lb/>
            he that was my father vpon earthe is long since departed and if I <lb/>
            haue not bene misinformed who was then beyond seas, yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties anger <lb/>
            was to him little better than the messinger of death, Though I perswade <lb/>
            my selfe it was rather sent in yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties name, then on yo<ex>u</ex>r warrant, for <lb/>
            what vse could yo<ex>ur</ex> ma<ex>jes</ex>tie haue of his being no more, who never was nor never <lb/>
            could be but your faithfull and affectionate servant, who in his hart adored <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r royall person as much as ever mortall man did immortall God. And <lb/>
            Lastlye whose hart was <add place="above">so</add> bent to please yo<ex>u</ex>r Matie, that the very sound of <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r displeasure was enough to breake yt, more perfect obedience then <lb/>
            this <del rend="strikethrough">cannot</del> <add place="above">can no</add> Subiect shew, to make his Soveraignes favor and disfavor <lb/>
            equall to life ad deathe: Pardon me dread Soveraigne yf in this <lb/>
            action I cannot hynder my fathers ghost from appearinge, for how <lb/>
            can it possiblye be at rest, as long as yo<ex>u</ex>r fatall displeasure raignes in <lb/>
            his poore familye, and makes it the house of contynuall mornynge, <lb/>
            Remove then yf it be yo<ex>u</ex>r blessed will the cloudes that haue so long honge <lb/>
            over o<ex>u</ex>r heades, and let not the present storme that wantes matter to <lb/>
            produce, extorte a thunderbolt, For what is <hi rend="italic">Phillippes</hi> or the sonne of <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Phillippes</hi> that yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie should destroye them, wee are vnworthye of <hi rend="italic">Caesars</hi> <lb/>
            anger aswell in regard of o<ex>u</ex>r <hi rend="underline">meanes</hi> as innocence./
         </p>
         <p>
            To concldue my prayers I most humblye beseech yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie to forgiue them, and let <lb/>
            not my ignorance of the stile and Ceremonyes vsed in Court be imputed to yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">h<supplied reason="damage">umble</supplied>
                </fw> <lb/>
            <pb n="[2r]"/>
            humble and well meanyng Suppll<ex>ian</ex>t as a wilfull wante of reverence, for there <lb/>
            lives not in yo<ex>u</ex>r domynions a subiect, in whose brest the two loyall qualities of <lb/>
            loue and feare, doe more religiouslye meete, or who would more willinglye <lb/>
            part with his owne essence, to adde the least acquisition to the greatnesse <lb/>
            and ma<ex>jes</ex>tie of his soveraigne; Trew it is that the subiect that employed the <lb/>
            facultyes of my woule at this present, was of such a Nature, as I could <lb/>
            not deny it the vttmost of my affection, And he who thinkes he can never <lb/>
            speake enough, maye easilie speake too much, my comfort is that neither <lb/>
            my brother nor my selfe can be said to haue <add place="above">fayled or</add> exceeded in any thing but <lb/>
            wordes, but what will that avayle vs vnlesse yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie will pardon, withot <lb/>
            that all crymes ar equall, and as much daunger lyes in an humble petic<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            as in a plott of high treason: Be pleased then most gracious Soveraigne <lb/>
            to give vs back o<ex>u</ex>r questionable wordes, and keepe o<ex>u</ex>r vndouted hartes, at least <lb/>
            shew vs so much mercye as to Judge vs accordinge to yo<ex>u</ex>r owne goodnesse, for <lb/>
            if we had not libertye to approache hither, we should be in daunger of <lb/>
            loosing the happiest parte of o<ex>u</ex>r birthright, and instead of being yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties <lb/>
            subiects, become other mens slaves. From yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie therfore yo<ex>u</ex>r faithfull <lb/>
            subiect craves and expectes, the ioyfull word of grace, which if I maye be <lb/>
            so happye as to carrye my poore brother, before he growes any elder in <lb/>
            miserye, I shall fill many an honest hart with praise and thankesgiving, <lb/>
            and for my particular, yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>ties greatest favors and liberalitye shall not <lb/>
            more oblige and bolt or affect others, then this yo<ex>u</ex>r royall clemency shall me. <lb/>
            In memorye wherof I shall daylie pray that yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>jes</ex>tie may obtayne all yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            desires in heaven, and be obeyed in all yo<ex>u</ex>r commandes vpon earth, that yow <lb/>
            maye live to see yo<ex>u</ex>r holie intenc<ex>i</ex>ons take effect for the good of Christendome, <lb/>
            and so honor the age we live in with the merittes of yo<ex>u</ex>r wisdome, fyally <lb/>
            that yo<ex>u</ex>r felicitye in this world may overtake that in the next, and make <lb/>
            yow weare a perpetuall Crowne to gods glorye and yo<ex>u</ex>r owne.
         </p>
         <p rend="align-right">
            Yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>es</ex>ties most humble loyall <lb/>
            and Englishe subiect
         </p>
         <p rend="align-right">
            Francis Phillippes
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>