<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Relation of all the Important Passages of the Treaty held at Brussels between the Ministers of the Archdukes and Sir Richard Weston</title>
            <author/>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="VA">
                    <name>Victoria Anker</name>
                    <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="TW">
               <name>Tim Wales</name>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLAddMS4149.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_4149">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Additional</collection>
                <idno>MS 4149</idno>
                <msName/>
             </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Additional MS 4149</p>
            </msDesc>
            
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_48044">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Additional</collection>
                <idno>MS 48044</idno>
                <msName/>
             </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated">
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Beinecke_Osborn_fb178.xml">Beinecke Library, Osborn fb178, ff. 127r–149v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Perrott_4.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Perrott 4, ff. 107x–120x</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Bodl_MS_Rawlinson_D_369.xml">Bodleian Library,  MS Rawlinson D 369, ff. 30r–51v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Woburn_Abbey_MS_23.xml">Woburn Abbey,  MS 23, pp19–22</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1622">c.1622?</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
            <language ident="LA">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term>treaty</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term>diplomacy</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-04-27" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2018-04-17" who="#TW" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>  
         <pb n="226r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f226r/add_ms_4149_f226r.jpg"/>
         <head rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">
               A Relac<ex>i</ex>on of all the important passa=<lb break="no"/>
               ges of the treatie held at Bruxells btw=<lb break="no"/>
               eene the Ministers of the Arche Dutches <lb/>
               &amp;: S<ex>i</ex>r Richarde weston Ambasador of <lb/>
               the Kinge of greate Britaine in the <lb/>
               Yeare <hi rend="underline">1622</hi> about a Suspencion of Dep=<lb break="no"/>
               osicion of Armes. / .
            </hi>
         </head>
         <p>
            May it please yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie: / <lb/>
            The occasion of yo<ex>u</ex>r sendinge Mee to the Arche Dutches  <lb/>
            was the invitac<ex>i</ex>on of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie by the Emperoure, first <lb/>
            by his l<ex>ett</ex>res of the xiiijth of Ianuarye, and after by his  <lb/>
            Ambassador, the Count of Swartzburgh, Who declared <lb/>
            to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie that yf you pleased to send yo<ex>u</ex>r Ambassador to Br=<lb break="no"/>
            uxells, the Infanta should haue an absolute powere to <lb/>
            treate and Conclude a Cessation of Armes, and afterwa=<lb break="no"/>
            rdes to Name the tyme, and place for the Principall treat=<lb break="no"/>
            <add place="LM">
                    <hi rend="italic">May .3. <lb/>
            <hi rend="underline">.1622.</hi>
                    </hi>
                </add>
            ye of the Peace, on the .3. of Maye I arrived at Brux=<lb break="no"/>
            ells, My reception  Was verie Honorable, and My treat=<lb break="no"/>
            ment while I was, defrayed by the Infanta (w<ex>hi</ex>ch conti=<lb break="no"/>
            nued vntill yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie gaue Mee order to the Contrarie) <lb/>
            Was full of all demonstracon of respect and Honoure <lb/>
            to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie some two dayes Were spent in Ceremonie. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            <add place="LM">
                    <hi rend="italic">May .9. <lb/>
            .<hi rend="underline">1622</hi>.</hi>
                </add> <lb/>
            On the .9th. We begane to treate, at W<ex>hi</ex>ch time I Made <lb/>
            a declarac<ex>i</ex>on, to the Infantas deputie of that w<ex>hi</ex>ch Your <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie had vnderstoode by the l<ex>ett</ex>re and Ambassador of the <lb/>
            Emperour, and by a l<ex>ett</ex>re also from her Highnes of the <lb/>
            Powere she had Receaved to treate a Suspenc<ex>i</ex>on and <lb/>
            deposic<ex>i</ex>on of Armes, and of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s sendinge Mee ther=<lb break="no"/>
            vpon, w<ex>i</ex>th ample Comission to the same ende, W<ex>hi</ex>ch I tould <lb/>
            them I had there readie to shewe, expectinge the like <lb/>
            from them, accordinge to the order vsuall and requisite <lb/>
            in such Cases, Not for any the least doubte I Made of <lb/>
            that w<ex>hi</ex>ch her highnes did acknowledge and affirme, but <lb/>
            for My owne discharge, in regard of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties Coma=<lb break="no"/>
            ndement. They promised to acquinte her Highnes <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">w<ex>i</ex>th My desire, and</fw>
            <pb n="226v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f226v/add_ms_4149_f226v.jpg"/>
            W<ex>i</ex>th My desire. And at the Next meetinge Confessed <lb/>
            Shee had No formal Comission, Nor other powere, <lb/>
            then by a l<ex>ett</ex>re from the Emperoure touchinge the point <lb/>
            of Suspenc<ex>i</ex>on of Armes: But they vndertooke there <lb/>
            should be sent vnto her, a full Comission from him  <lb/>
            Containinge <add place="above">an</add> absolute and irrevokable power both for <lb/>
            the suspencion and deposition, and likewise for the ch=<lb break="no"/>
            oyce of tyme and place for the principall treatie, <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch they assured them selues should be W<ex>i</ex>thin .<hi rend="italic">xxvj</hi>. <lb/>
            dayes. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            The Next thinge Was, they desired to see the subm=<lb break="no"/>
            ission of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s Sonne in Lawe, in regard that <lb/>
            Was Menc<ex>i</ex>oned in My Comission: Whereto I repl=<lb break="no"/>
            ied, that the Submission w<ex>hi</ex>ch the Wordes in the Co=<lb break="no"/>
            mission imported had ben divers tymes donne both <lb/>
            before and after the formall acte of Conformitie to <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie Not onlie in regarde of Peace, but genera=<lb break="no"/>
            llye, and for the Man<ex>n</ex>er of proceedinge, and that yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s affirminge therof Was a suffitient assurance, <lb/>
            Wherew<ex>i</ex>th they seemed to be Well satisfied, Saying <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            the treatye Might still goe on, and promising in her <lb/>
            highnes Name the Ratefieing of all that Might be <lb/>
            agreed on (in the Meane tyme) that the Comission came <lb/>
            from the Emperoure, w<ex>hi</ex>ch promise she also confirmed, <lb/>
            W<ex>i</ex>thin a While after by her l<ex>ett</ex>re to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie, Soe that <lb/>
            the state of thinges in the Pallatinate being then <lb/>
            on equall termes, there Was Not any More excepti=<lb break="no"/>
            on against the Comission for that tyme beinge aboute <lb/>
            the .9th. of May, vntill towardes the last of Iune fo=<lb break="no"/>
            llowinge. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            The Second important pointe W<ex>hi</ex>ch was handled, did <lb/>
            concerne a prouisionall abstinence from all actes of <lb/>
            Hostillitie duringe the treatie, W<ex>hi</ex>ch I propounded for <lb/>
            the prevention of those disturbances that the daylie <lb/>
            accidentes of Warre Might breede, and the deputies <lb/>
            seemed to like for the same reason, addinge also that <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">they conceived the</fw>
            <pb n="227r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f227r/add_ms_4149_f227r.jpg"/>
            they Conceived that the Infantes power for a suspen=<lb break="no"/>
            tion and deposition beinge the greater Might suff=<lb break="no"/>
            itiently Comprehend a prouic<ex>i</ex>onall Surceasance, be=<lb break="no"/>
            inge the lesse: But there Was dispute in two or thr=<lb break="no"/>
            ee Conferrences about the tyme of the Abstinence, <lb/>
            and the Man<ex>n</ex>er of Negotiatinge it, Whether by l<ex>ett</ex>res <lb/>
            of Councell, or by vsinge therein some fitt person or <lb/>
            persons, the Cheefe impediment beinge then thought <lb/>
            on both sides to be in the independence of the Ellector <lb/>
            Pallatynes Auxilliaries, or yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie or the said El=<lb break="no"/>
            ector. The Infantes deputies Makinge Noe doubte <lb/>
            of the obedience of the Emperours Cheefe to her hi=<lb break="no"/>
            ghnes l<ex>ett</ex>res vpon this occasion there Were Named by <lb/>
            the deputies the Ellector of Mayence, and the Lant=<lb break="no"/>
            graue of Dornstad as a Nevtrall Prince, and one <lb/>
            whoe affected Peace: But I answered, that I thought <lb/>
            them vnfitt, the one beinge a Principall Member of the <lb/>
            Catholique league, and the other alwayes adhearinge <lb/>
            to the Emperiall partie: In the ende it Was agreede <lb/>
            on both sides, to Comitt the Negotiac<ex>i</ex>on to the Lorde <lb/>
            Cheechestre then residinge in the Pallatinate, as the <lb/>
            first person in regarde of the Quallity of his implo=<lb break="no"/>
            yment, to W<ex>hi</ex>ch purpose, I did by l<ex>ett</ex>res recomende <lb/>
            the busines vnto him, and the Infanta in like Man=<lb break="no"/>
            ner Wrott vnto the Emperoures Cheefes to Concurr <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th him to that ende soe farr as Might concerne <lb/>
            them. The Lord Cheechester vsed such dilligence <lb/>
            therein that the Electors Auxilliaries Were content <lb/>
            to come to a surceasance for .21. dayes, and he Wrott <lb/>
            also to the Emperours Cheefes to haue a Meetinge <lb/>
            at frankforth, or some other Convenient place: But <lb/>
            he received aunswere from Monsure de Tylly, first <lb/>
            that he could doe Nothinge of him selfe w<ex>i</ex>thout the co=<lb break="no"/>
            mmaunde of his Maister, and W<ex>i</ex>thout the rest of the <lb/>
            Emperours Cheefes, Thirdly that the l<ex>ett</ex>res Were W<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            such Caution for feare of preiudiceing <ex>th</ex>e Emperour <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">and his allies that</fw>
            <pb n="227v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f227v/add_ms_4149_f227v.jpg"/>
            and his allies, that he knewe Not howe to give Waye <lb/>
            vnto it W<ex>i</ex>thout hazard to himselfe: Lastlie, that he <lb/>
            Neuer hearde of any such powere givuen to the Infan=<lb break="no"/>
            ta: Herew<ex>i</ex>th I acquinted both the deputies and the <lb/>
            Marquesse of Spinola demaundinge that her hig=<lb break="no"/>
            hnes Would be pleased to Write directlie and fullie <lb/>
            to the Emperours Cheifes to accept the <del rend="strikethrough">fore</del> aforesaid <lb/>
            tyme of twenty one dayes the like acceptinge thereof <lb/>
            by the Elector and his partie, Whereto the said depu=<lb break="no"/>
            ties brought this Answere from her highnes, That <lb/>
            shee had delt directlie and Cleerelie w<ex>i</ex>thout retr=<lb break="no"/>
            actinge or givinge any vnderhand Comaunde; <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            she had Writt to the Emperours Cheifes Who best <lb/>
            vnderstoode the state of thinges to treate W<ex>i</ex>th My lo=<lb break="no"/>
            rde Cheechestre about the Provic<ex>i</ex>onall abstinence, <lb/>
            and vntill she had heard from them, knewe we Not Wh=<lb break="no"/>
            at More to Write: They did likewise shewe me a  <lb/>
            l<ex>ett</ex>re Written by the Marquesse Spinola by Don Gonz=<lb break="no"/>
            ales de Cordua, Who acknoulledged therin the rece=<lb break="no"/>
            iptes of one from her highnesse to Monsure de Ty=<lb break="no"/>
            lly w<ex>hi</ex>ch he had Not the Convenience to deliuer, Men=<lb break="no"/>
            tioninge W<ex>i</ex>thall the scruple Made by the said Monsure <lb/>
            de Tylly to agree to an abstinence w<ex>i</ex>thout order from <lb/>
            the duke of Bavaria: And lastlie addinge his owne <lb/>
            opinion that forbearance Would asmuch Consume the <lb/>
            forces as Warre. Vppon W<ex>hi</ex>ch answere, and the Maner <lb/>
            of proceedinge in the Pallatinate, I conceivinge litle  <lb/>
            hope of the Provic<ex>i</ex>onall abstinence agreed to prosecute <lb/>
            the treatie. The cheefe pointes whereof had in seuerall <lb/>
            <add place="LM">
                    <hi rend="italic">May .25. <lb/>
            . <hi rend="underline">1622</hi>.</hi>
                </add>
            Conferrences ben handled (Viz) the Place, the persons, <lb/>
            the tyme and the Man<ex>n</ex>er: The Place Was firste ha=<lb break="no"/>
            ndled as the fittest enterance, and I propounded the <lb/>
            Pallatinate, both Vpper and the Lower as the propere subiecte of the treatie, and that onlie W<ex>hi</ex>ch had bine <lb/>
            Considered and insisted on in formor Negotiatinges: <lb/>
            And hereto I added this explicac<ex>i</ex>on, that the first thinge <lb/>
            in his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties intenc<ex>i</ex>on was a generall Cessation and <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">layinge downe</fw>
            <pb n="228r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f228r/add_ms_4149_f228r.jpg"/>
            layinge downe of Armes: But to that w<ex>hi</ex>ch was firste  <lb/>
            considerable in the proposic<ex>i</ex>on was the Pallatinate: <lb/>
            This pointe bread Much Contestinge, it beinge alle=<lb break="no"/>
            adged on the Infantas parte that by this meanes the  <lb/>
            Emperours freindes in Germany should still remaine <lb/>
            exposed to danger by a libertie of Hostillitie in all other <lb/>
            partes thereof as any advauntage Might present it <lb/>
            selfe: Wherevnto I replied, that yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties intenc<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            was generall, that to prepare the waye to the effectinge  <lb/>
            thereof, for yo<ex>u</ex>r owne forces and yo<ex>u</ex>r Sonnes in Lawe, you <lb/>
            would undertake directlie: And that for the Auxiliaries <lb/>
            vpon faire and reasonable termes, w<ex>hi</ex>ch if they would Not <lb/>
            accepte. The Emperoure and kinge of Spayne Might gi=<lb break="no"/>
            ve yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie that Content w<ex>hi</ex>ch Might cause you to pursue <lb/>
            them as enemis, and perturbers of the Publique peace: <lb/>
            As for the persons on the Ellectors side, I saide that I <lb/>
            did daylie expecte powers and Comissioners from the <lb/>
            said auxiliaries vpon the safe conductes w<ex>hi</ex>cch had bene sen=<lb break="no"/>
            te to that purpose; wherevpon I was toulde by the depu=<lb break="no"/>
            ties in her highnesse Name that shee was well satisfied w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            that w<ex>hi</ex>ch I had declared, and would soe farre as the Nece=<lb break="no"/>
            ssitie of thinges Might permitt, give yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie all Content: <lb/>
            About this tyme fellout the invasion of the Lantgrave <lb/>
            of Darmsteats Countrye, and the Seazing of him and his <lb/>
            Sonne, w<ex>hi</ex>ch did both hinder for a tyme the sendinge of <lb/>
            the expected Comissioners, and Made a greate allarum &amp; <lb/>
            was highly Complayned of, both by the Deputies and the <lb/>
            Infanta her selfe: But I hauinge received advertisment <lb/>
            from  the Elector howe thinges had past, and the Reasons <lb/>
            of all, viz. That the invasion proceeded from the Nece=<lb break="no"/>
            ssitie of Releevinge his Army: And that the Seazing of <lb/>
            the Lantgraue who was founde in a Woode, was for preser=<lb break="no"/>
            vinge of his person from outrage of Souldiers, w<ex>hi</ex>ch app=<lb break="no"/>
            eareth to be true by his speedie delivery: I did herew<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            acquinte the deputies, and her highnes, also that thet Might <lb/>
            see thinges were Not soe hainous as they Conceived: I de=<lb break="no"/>
            clared furthere that yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie preferringe the generall <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Peace of Christendom</fw>
            <pb n="229r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f229r/add_ms_4149_f229r.jpg"/>
            Peace of Christendom, before the perticuler regarde of yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Sonne in Lawe. had very latlie Written vnto him a ve=<lb break="no"/>
            rye Rounde l<ex>ett</ex>re, Not knowinge then howe thinges had <lb/>
            passed Wherby he Might finde that his houlding of abo=<lb break="no"/>
            ut such Waveringe Courses, Would cause the W<ex>i</ex>thdraw=<lb break="no"/>
            inge of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties assistance and Countenance from him: <lb/>
            That you had likewise Written to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ambassador and Ge=<lb break="no"/>
            nerall in the Pallatinate charginge them in case of the <lb/>
            Electors disobedience. to licence the Armey payed by you, <lb/>
            and to returne to yo<ex>u</ex>r presense: Finallie I prayed herr <lb/>
            highenes to take knowledge of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties Reall and cleere <lb/>
            proceedings, and of the Electors readines at the same <lb/>
            tyme to Conforme himselfe to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s pleasure, wher=<lb break="no"/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th shee seemed then to rest satisfied, acknowledging yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s sinceretie, and addinge further that shee woulde <lb/>
            referre the Iudgement of the Electors carriage to yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie and wholie relye on you for reducinge and Continu=<lb break="no"/>
            inge of him in order. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Nowe in a dispatch W<ex>hi</ex>ch I made two dayes after to Mr <lb/>
            Secretarye Calvarte hauinge formorlie apprehended <lb/>
            an intention they had to sett vppon the duke of Brunsw=<lb break="no"/>
            icke whereof I gaue him advirtisment in one of My  <lb/>
            dispatches (before w<ex>hi</ex>ch then prooued true) I did desire him <lb/>
            to consider what small Comforte I had, and howe it Mi=<lb break="no"/>
            ght stande W<ex>i</ex>th yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s honoure While I was treatinge <lb/>
            of a Suspecntion of Armes, to haue the busines Check=<lb break="no"/>
            ed w<ex>i</ex>th such disasters, that I would haue patience to ex=<lb break="no"/>
            pecte the issue if I sawe any possibillitie of a <unclear>promisi=<lb break="no"/>
            all</unclear> abstinence or accomadatinge of the Auxiliaries: But <lb/>
            since I had Noe likelihood of either I desired speedie dir=<lb break="no"/>
            ections howe to carye my selfe, that yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s  honore Mig=<lb break="no"/>
            gt Noe More despend vpon such incertentie: Towardes <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            <add place="LM">
                    <hi rend="italic">Junij .22. <lb/>
            .1622.</hi>
                </add>
            ende of June, there came from the Elector Palatine a full <lb/>
            and ample l<ex>ett</ex>re of Submission to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie w<ex>i</ex>th l<ex>ett</ex>res also from <lb/>
            the Marquesse of Thurluck and Counte of Mansfeilde, <lb/>
            Somwhat before w<ex>hi</ex>ch tyme hapned the Duke Christiane <lb/>
            of Brunswickes retreate, and we beinge still in treatie, <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">The Emperours</fw>
            <pb n="229r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f229r/add_ms_4149_f229r.jpg"/>
            The Emperours affaires seeminge then to prosper: Her <lb/>
            highnes deputies renewed theire former exceptiones <lb/>
            against My Comission, and referred the aboue mencon=<lb break="no"/>
            ed l<ex>ett</ex>res as beinge onlie l<ex>ett</ex>res of Credence: Wherevpon  <lb/>
            I toulde them I knewe Not what better assurance to ex=<lb break="no"/>
            pecte from such persons, then theire handes and Seals <lb/>
            yet I promissed to speake to those Ministers whom they <lb/>
            had imployd to Me, and cause such formall poweres <lb/>
            to be sent for, as the said deputies demaunded, w<ex>hi</ex>ch was <lb/>
            also performed (tho w<ex>i</ex>thout successe) But w<ex>i</ex>thall for the <lb/>
            Electore I shewed them his first Submission to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie <lb/>
            and the Emperours l<ex>ett</ex>res of the .4th. of Ianuary in the <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie alone is Menc<ex>i</ex>oned for the Pointe or Tre=<lb break="no"/>
            atie, and invited therevnto, I did likewise declare that <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout further order from yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie I could Not departe <lb/>
            from that w<ex>hi</ex>ch I said before, seeinge No cause in reason <lb/>
            or honoure why yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie (vndertakinge for yo<ex>u</ex>r sonne in <lb/>
            lawe was Not altogether suffitiente, or whie the Co=<lb break="no"/>
            mission W<ex>hi</ex>ch I had should Not fullie Comprehend all that <lb/>
            concerned him in that behalfe, supposinge those defectes <lb/>
            and incapacities w<ex>hi</ex>ch Might else be obiected and shoulde <lb/>
            be salved by Noe other expediente: I did also entreate <lb/>
            them to Considere; That the Electors sendinge of the po=<lb break="no"/>
            were whereon they insisted Might <add place="above">not</add> intangle the busynes <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th an other dispute, for it was Not to be thought hee <lb/>
            Woulde forbeare any of his tytles, W<ex>hi</ex>ch he spared Not <lb/>
            to vse euen in his formall submission: But all this <lb/>
            Could Not satisfie her highnes Nor them: yet w<ex>i</ex>thin a <lb/>
            daye or two they propounded an expedient, wherby <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            difficoultie aboute tytles Might be whollie avoyded <lb/>
            viz, by the incertion of divers Wordes such as Might <lb/>
            be ioyntlye agreed vpon in my Comission, and the El=<lb break="no"/>
            ectors subscription of his Name vnder the same Com=<lb break="no"/>
            ission beinge Made a Newe, and said w<ex>i</ex>thall that altho=<lb break="no"/>
            ugh it woulde require some good space of tyme, yet it <lb/>
            Needed Not to staye the proceedinges of the treatie w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            Might be in the<del rend="strikethrough">
                    <unclear/>
                </del> meanetyme Continued, to w<ex>hi</ex>ch ende <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">they weare redye</fw>
            <pb n="229v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f229v/add_ms_4149_f229v.jpg"/>
            they Were redie to heare What I had to propounde touch=<lb break="no"/>
            inge those Auxiliaries Who had sent vnto me Wishinge <lb/>
            theire demaunde Might be reasonable to Moderate on <lb/>
            practicall termes, or since it tended to a co<ex>m</ex>on good it <lb/>
            Were fitt it should be a Com<ex>m</ex>on Worke, as for the pr=<lb break="no"/>
            opoundes expedient by inserc<ex>i</ex>on, the Maner whereof <lb/>
            was agreed, I promised to give advirtisment of it, ho=<lb break="no"/>
            pinge that if yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie woulde accept it, there should be <lb/>
            No more questions about that pointe: But contrarye <lb/>
            to all expectac<ex>i</ex>on, W<ex>i</ex>thin fowere dayes after They rai=<lb break="no"/>
            sed a Newe difficultie, for they declared, that vpon fu=<lb break="no"/>
            rther Considerac<ex>i</ex>on they found the same Comission <lb/>
            defective Not in substance but formallitie, because the <lb/>
            title of Elector Was vsed therein, and therefore her <lb/>
            highnes desired to knowe whether yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie would Not <lb/>
            be pleased to leaue out that tytle (the acceptinge where <lb/>
            of by her beinge Made) to a thinge in W<ex>hi</ex>ch the Prince <lb/>
            is soe quallified would argue an approouing and co=<lb break="no"/>
            nfirminge of the same tytle: Whereto I answered <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            I had alreadie given advirtisment of the propounded  <lb/>
            expedient, w<ex>hi</ex>ch I knewe Not Whether yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie would <lb/>
            accepte or Reiecte: That I would deale cleerlie and <lb/>
            roundlie W<ex>i</ex>th them, letting them knowe, yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie exp=<lb break="no"/>
            ected the Restituc<ex>i</ex>on Not onlie of the Patrimonye, but <lb/>
            likwise of the Honore of yo<ex>u</ex>r Children, Wherefore as <lb/>
            I would advirtise of this Newe scruple in regard it <lb/>
            was deliuered in her highnes Name, for soe I pro=<lb break="no"/>
            tested against it, tellinge them also I did Not thinke <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie would take in good parte this Newe raisinge  <lb/>
            of difficultie, that it was licklie, the Comission was <lb/>
            in hand againe vpon the formor dispatch, and Might <lb/>
            perhappes be deliuered Me before this other adverti=<lb break="no"/>
            sment could come to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie so as if the reformi=<lb break="no"/>
            inge of that pointe should be graunted it Must cause <lb/>
            a third alterac<ex>i</ex>on, w<ex>hi</ex>ch Might argue a desire in them <lb/>
            to <del rend="strikethrough">Winne</del> gaine tyme, as likinge theire insistinge soe <lb/>
            much vpon formalities, dis shewe that they had litle <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Meaninge to give</fw>
            <pb n="230r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f230r/add_ms_4149_f230r.jpg"/>
            Meaninge to give yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie satisfaction in Matter of <lb/>
            Substance: About this tyme Was the first rumor  <lb/>
            of the siege of Hidleberghe, and therefore in the same <lb/>
            Conferrence I prest them to the ende I Might treate <lb/>
            securelie, to haue assurance that the townes then he=<lb break="no"/>
            ld in the Pallatinate should be forborne, least otherw=<lb break="no"/>
            wise I might tarrie to see the treatie illuded, and <lb/>
            afterward departe w<ex>i</ex>th Scorne, And this I prayed <lb/>
            them to reporte to her highnes, And therevpon after <lb/>
            attendance when I receaved Noe satisfaction from them <lb/>
            I craved audience of her highnes, and desired herr <lb/>
            (taking occasion vpon that allarum) That she would <add place="above">Comaunde</add> <lb/>
            Tylly and Gonzalles to forbeare: Her highnes an=<lb break="no"/>
            swers, that for Tylly <add>s</add>he had No power as beinge <lb/>
            vnder the Emperoure: And I replied therevpon that <lb/>
            the Emperoure hauinge given to her highnes Power  <lb/>
            to conclude a Cessation, had likewise giuen her pow=<lb break="no"/>
            er to directe his Ministers vnto that ende: But ho=<lb break="no"/>
            wsoeuer if she had Not that comaunde ouer Tylly yet <lb/>
            I desired she would prohibite and restraine Gonza=<lb break="no"/>
            lles and his forces from aattemptinge: her answere to <lb/>
            this was, that for Gonzalles he had expresse order <lb/>
            out of Spaine, that when Tylly and he were toge=<lb break="no"/>
            ther he should be directed by him, as if he were his <lb/>
            inferior. This seemed soe strange to Me, that it Mo=<lb break="no"/>
            ved me to tell her, that yf yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie had knowene soe <lb/>
            much before, and that the Emperours Cheefes May <lb/>
            obaye when they list accordinge to the varietie of <lb/>
            advauntages, his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie would haue spared the sendi=<lb break="no"/>
            nge of an Ambassador, that he Might have preven=<lb break="no"/>
            ted the receavinge of such an afront, beinge Now <lb/>
            to be satisfied vpon two greate difficulties, the pro=<lb break="no"/>
            ceedinge vpon the Second Comission w<ex>i</ex>thout a third <lb/>
            alterac<ex>i</ex>on, and the assurance of the places held by <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s  forces in the Pallatinate: I expected theire <lb/>
            answere, but heard Nothinge from them, from the <lb/>
            .28th. of Iune vntill the .8th. of Iuly w<ex>hi</ex>ch they excused <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">by theire Multitud</fw>
            <pb n="230v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f230v/add_ms_4149_f230v.jpg"/>
            by theire Multitude of busines beinge the greater by <lb/>
            reason of the Marquesse Spinolas absence: Then <lb/>
            I prest them vpon the Seconde Comission, declaringe <lb/>
            that yf yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie had knowne tyme enough of the last <lb/>
            Scruple, you would haue omitted the tytle of Elector, and <lb/>
            were then Contented to give me leaue to accepte of <lb/>
            a protestac<ex>i</ex>on on theire partes w<ex>i</ex>th a savinge of yo<ex>u</ex>r So=<lb break="no"/>
            nne in Lawes rightes as well as the Emperours, <lb/>
            By w<ex>hi</ex>ch Meanes we Might haue proceeded w<ex>i</ex>thout <lb/>
            losse of tyme,  But they would Not give Waye to this <lb/>
            expedi<del rend="strikethrough">c<ex>i</ex>on</del>ent, insistinge still on theire third altera=<lb break="no"/>
            cion ww<ex>hi</ex>ch caused theire delaye in regarde of their send=<lb break="no"/>
            inge too and fro, and the Seazinge of the Messen=<lb break="no"/>
            ger betweene Sedan and Bruxells, Whether he <lb/>
            was brought prisoner, from the .8. of Iuly to the .8. <lb/>
            of August, before w<ex>hi</ex>ch tyme the last Comission ca=<lb break="no"/>
            me Not yo my handes: In the Meanetyme  I receav=<lb break="no"/>
            ed a l<ex>ett</ex>re from the Ellector Pallatine, advirtiseinge <lb/>
            Me of his arrivall at Sedan as a place Most pro=<lb break="no"/>
            per, beinge both Newtrall and Neere the place of tr=<lb break="no"/>
            eatie, that he had taken this resoluc<ex>i</ex>on to give the lesse <lb/>
            impediment to our Negotiation, and to obay yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties Co <lb/>
            maunde, and that seeinge the greate disorders of his <lb/>
            Army w<ex>hi</ex>ch Might be imputed to him, and vsed for a  <lb/>
            pretexte to interrupte the treatye contrarie to you<ex>u</ex>r good <lb/>
            intention, for the preventinge hereof and that the Wo=<lb break="no"/>
            rlde Might see howe desirous he Was of Peace. Th=<lb break="no"/>
            erefore before his departure he had discharged all his <lb/>
            forces there remaininge, only those w<ex>hi</ex>ch were payede <lb/>
            of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie But this Conformitie could Not remoue <lb/>
            the Complaints                                   and pretended ieal=<lb break="no"/>
            ousies and feares, it beinge alledged that the Armye <lb/>
            Was lessened but by one Man: And whereas I ma=<lb break="no"/>
            de divers instances of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s offeres to ioyne with <lb/>
            the Emperoure for reducinge of the Electors Auxili=<lb break="no"/>
            aries to reason, both before his licenceinge of them, <lb/>
            and after, yet there Was Noe <del rend="strikethrough">e<unclear> </unclear>e</del> eare given there=<lb break="no"/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">vnto, Nor any other</fw>
            <pb n="231r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f231r/add_ms_4149_f231r.jpg"/>
            vnto, Nor any other accomodac<ex>i</ex>on propounded vntill the <lb/>
            Secret ouerture of depositinge of <unclear>Mamehem</unclear> and franck=<lb break="no"/>
            endale in her Highnes handes, And leauinge of Hidlebu=<lb break="no"/>
            rghe, for the Electors residence w<ex>i</ex>th the revenues both of <lb/>
            that and the other twoe, Wherof I Made perticuler Relac<ex>i</ex>on <lb/>
            to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie by a dispatch of the xixth of Iulij, But it be=<lb break="no"/>
            inge soe tender a pointe in regard of honor and assuran=<lb break="no"/>
            ce, and for other Considerac<ex>i</ex>ons of w<ex>hi</ex>ch I likewise gave <lb/>
            advertisment at the same tyme. I refused the imbra=<lb break="no"/>
            ceing or propoundinge of it, and left it to them yf they <lb/>
            thought fitt, Notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge What I had saide against it, <lb/>
            To propounde by theire Ambassadors here, Neuerthelesse <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Don Carola Colona </hi>
                <unclear>
                    <del rend="strikethrough">whom</del>
                </unclear> howsoeuer he were Made acq- <lb/>
            uinted w<ex>i</ex>th it, yet had No order to Make the offer vntill <lb/>
            about the .viijth. of September, at w<ex>hi</ex>ch tyme it was kno=<lb break="no"/>
            wne Hidelberge Was either in greate distresse, or els <lb/>
            taken: Hauinge on the viijth of August receaved yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s Comission, I presentlie gaue Notice of it, and dem=<lb break="no"/>
            aunded a Conference, w<ex>hi</ex>ch I could Not haue vntill the <lb/>
            xijth by reason of the absence of one of the Deputies: <lb/>
            At that Meetinge I exhibited the Comission vnto them, <lb/>
            who had Nothing to oppose, but saide it were fitt to Co=<lb break="no"/>
            mvnicate it w<ex>i</ex>th her Highnes, wherevpon in the same <lb/>
            daye in the afternoone an authenticall Coppie thereof <lb/>
            was deliuered them: The Next Daye, They declared her <lb/>
            highnes acceptation, and said they were readie to proce=<lb break="no"/>
            ede in the treatie; Wherevnto I answered, that I desired <lb/>
            Nothinge More, and then we resolued to Meete againe <lb/>
            on the .xvth At w<ex>hi</ex>ch tyme I deliuered them this propo=<lb break="no"/>
            sition in Writinge. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            W<ex>hi</ex>ch Contayneth, and expresseth a Svccinat proposition <lb/>
            howe farre his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie of Greate Brittaine can and will <lb/>
            ingage himselfe, for somuch as Concerneth a Suspetion <lb/>
            and Deposition of Armes in the twoe Pallatinates, his <lb/>
            said Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie promiseth, aswell for himselfe as for his sonne <lb/>
            in lawe, that Neither they, Nor theire forces shall give <lb/>
            any assistance, directlie or indirectlie to the enemies of <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">either parte w<ex>i</ex>thin</fw>
            <pb n="231v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f231v/add_ms_4149_f231v.jpg"/>
            either parte, W<ex>i</ex>thin the twoe Pallatinates aforesaide Nor <lb/>
            in any other place Whatsoeuer. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            He Promiseth also to vse all posssible Meanes that the Ar=<lb break="no"/>
            ticles resolued on, shalbe involablye observed and Mai=<lb break="no"/>
            ntained, duringe the tyme in all that concerneth the Pa=<lb break="no"/>
            llatinate, and all the Places thereof possessed by either <lb/>
            partie: And he wilbe sor farre <del rend="strikethrough">forth </del>from permittinge <lb/>
            that the truce shalbe any waye infringed in  the aboue=<lb break="no"/>
            saide places: That contrariwise he promiseth and de=<lb break="no"/>
            clareth that he Will ioyne his Armes w<ex>i</ex>th those of his <lb/>
            Emperiall Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie against all such, as shall attempt it. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Touchinge the Duke Christian of Brvnswicke and Cou=<lb break="no"/>
            nt of Mansfield who haue bene heretofore Auxilliar=<lb break="no"/>
            ries of his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties Sonne in Lawe, it is suffitientlie <lb/>
            evident, that he hath discharged them, a good while si=<lb break="no"/>
            nce, and Medleth Noe More W<ex>i</ex>th theire affaires, Nor th=<lb break="no"/>
            ey w<ex>i</ex>th his, havinge imbarqued them selves in other de=<lb break="no"/>
            signes and seperate resoluc<ex>i</ex>ons. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Nowe when the treatie of a generall Peace shall come <lb/>
            to be handled, if then the said duke and Count will Not <lb/>
            be Comprehended therein vpon such termes as be Con=<lb break="no"/>
            sonant to reason and honoure: His said Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie will de=<lb break="no"/>
            clare himselfe theire enemyes, and iointlie imploye <lb/>
            his forces against them, as against the perturbers of the <lb/>
            Com<ex>m</ex>on repose of Christendome. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Wherefore sith this is all his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie cane doe for the  <lb/>
            present, and that Maye be expected from him for the fv=<lb break="no"/>
            uture in Honoure and Equitie, in regard whereof, hee <lb/>
            desireth that her highnes will thinke good to declare her <lb/>
            selfe. viz. Whether the truce Maye be Made vpon this <lb/>
            proposition. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Att the deliuerie Whereof, I toulde the Deputies that <lb/>
            I should Not Neede to remember vnto them yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s gr=<lb break="no"/>
            eate Merits towardes the Howse of Austria, how you <lb/>
            had held the Patrimonie of yo<ex>u</ex>r Children taken awaye <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>thout opposinge the Course of the Emperors victories <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">as hauinge More</fw>
            <pb n="232r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f232r/add_ms_4149_f232r.jpg"/>
            as hauinge More care of the Peace of Christendome <lb/>
            then of yo<ex>u</ex>r sonnes affaires, w<ex>hi</ex>ch all the World had seene, <lb/>
            and them selues acknowledged, and that therefore your <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie expectinge Nowe the fruites of yo<ex>u</ex>r Longe Patience <lb/>
            and theire Many promisses, had Comaunded Me to pro=<lb break="no"/>
            pounde that w<ex>hi</ex>ch I had then deliuered, and to a rounde and <lb/>
            present answere. They promissed to acquinte her Highnes <lb/>
            therew<ex>i</ex>th, and to lett me knowe her Resoluc<ex>i</ex>on, w<ex>i</ex>thin twoe <lb/>
            dayes after came Newes of the Count of Mansfield be=<lb break="no"/>
            inge in Henault, together w<ex>i</ex>th the duke Christian whose <lb/>
            passage thorough those partes to ioyne w<ex>i</ex>th the forces of <lb/>
            the vnited states, gaue indeede litle leasure to the Infa=<lb break="no"/>
            nta and her Councell to thinke on other Matters: yet <lb/>
            I did Sollicet for an answere, but More earnestlie wh=<lb break="no"/>
            en it was knowne that Mansfield was ioyned w<ex>i</ex>th  <lb/>
            the States forces. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            That impediment of the Count Mansfield beinge re=<lb break="no"/>
            moued as I thought, and hauinge Received l<ex>ett</ex>res out of <lb/>
            Spayne from My Lord Digby of Much assurance, I had <lb/>
            reason to conceive some better hope, and therevpon <lb/>
            havinge obtained Audience, I desired her Highnes to <lb/>
            hasten the Answere, and in that Audience taking No=<lb break="no"/>
            tice of the good offices done by her, Whereof I had <lb/>
            advertisment from My Lorde Digby: I added w<ex>i</ex>thall <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            thereby I had the greater confidence of the good effectes <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie attended from her, havinge Now in her <lb/>
            owne handes, the Meanes, and the Powere to give <lb/>
            him Content. That the takinge of the remainder To=<lb break="no"/>
            wnes could be litle glorie to them: That the Howse <lb/>
            of Austria wanted but one thinge to Crowne theire  <lb/>
            victories: w<ex>hi</ex>ch was to lett the World see, they can as <lb/>
            wislie laye downe theire Armes, as they can take them <lb/>
            vpp: Lastlie, that there was No enemie, and therefore <lb/>
            Noe cause of Feare, or iealousie to them or theire  <lb/>
            Neighbours: Her answere to that was, in feawe and <lb/>
            generall Wordes, of her good affection to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie: That <lb/>
            shee Would give Mee answere to My demaundes w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">convenient speede</fw>
            <pb n="232v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f232v/add_ms_4149_f232v.jpg"/>
            Convenient speed, and           		if it laye in her po=<lb break="no"/>
            were vpon w<ex>hi</ex>ch I did hope shee would haue given ord=<lb break="no"/>
            er to her Comissioners, and after I sent Mr Trvmball <lb/>
            and Mr Dickinson to the Chauncellor Pequins, who <lb/>
            spake couldlie of it, tellinge them, he had order from <lb/>
            her Highnes to Make relation of what had passed <lb/>
            in the last Conference, w<ex>hi</ex>ch she purposed to sende hee <lb/>
            knewe Not whether: But he thought, it was to be se=<lb break="no"/>
            nt to the Marquesse of Spinola, Who Was then in=<lb break="no"/>
            the Armye: And here vpon I advertized yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie Th=<lb break="no"/>
            at When I compared the Comfortes from Spayne w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            the Language held here, I founde a greate deale of <lb/>
            difference. Presentlie after that audience I vnder=<lb break="no"/>
            stoode of the Siege of Hidleberge, W<ex>hi</ex>ch at last prooved <lb/>
            true, for W<ex>i</ex>thin twoe dayes after that I was adver=<lb break="no"/>
            tised of the Certaynty thereof by l<ex>ett</ex>res from the Lord <lb/>
            Chichester, Where vpon I demaunded, and had Audi=<lb break="no"/>
            ence againe: In W<ex>hi</ex>ch tyme I pressed for the W<ex>i</ex>thdrawin=<lb break="no"/>
            ge of the Siege, and forbearinge of the other places: But <lb/>
            her Highnes answered that I had experience by her <lb/>
            former l<ex>ett</ex>res to Monsure Tilly that he woulde Not obay <lb/>
            her, and that the powere she had was for a suspension <lb/>
            and deposition, Not for hopeinge of <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> the Course of <lb/>
            Armes in the Meane tyme, And I replied that in her <lb/>
            Power from the Emperoure, there Was Noe exception <lb/>
            of Monsure Tilly or any other But a generall and <lb/>
            vnrestrained inablinge of Her, and that if shee Wan=<lb break="no"/>
            ted Pwere to graunt a present surcessance, yet she <lb/>
            had that w<ex>hi</ex>ch is more essen<del rend="strikethrough">tia</del>tiall to Conclude the s<ex>ai</ex>d <lb/>
            Suspention and Deposic<ex>i</ex>on W<ex>hi</ex>ch <del rend="strikethrough">W </del>Now all impedime=<lb break="no"/>
            nts beinge remoued as appeareth to the Whole World, <lb/>
            She had Noe reason to delay: I demaunded also that at <lb/>
            the least she would take order for the Remouinge of the  <lb/>
            Siege, vntill I might receave a Resolution from yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie vpon her answere, W<ex>hi</ex>ch I expected and was <lb/>
            promissed to the proposition: But she saied as before, &amp; <lb/>
            all I could gett was a promise to write to the Arche <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Duke Leopold and</fw>
            <pb n="233r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f233r/add_ms_4149_f233r.jpg"/>
            Duke Leopold and Monsure Tilly wherof though I expec=<lb break="no"/>
            ted Not any good effectes, as I tould both her highnes and <lb/>
            her deputies, and the issue shewed howe greate reason <lb/>
            I had to doubte: yet I thought good Not to refuse them <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            Might w<ex>i</ex>thout touch to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s Honour to hould the trea=<lb break="no"/>
            tie on foote till I receaved an Answere: w<ex>i</ex>thin fower da=<lb break="no"/>
            yes was sent me a single l<ex>ett</ex>re to the Arche Duke Leopold <lb/>
            wherew<ex>i</ex>th he beinge offended aswell w<ex>i</ex>th the losse of tyme <lb/>
            in a Matter of such weight, as for the Manner of the <lb/>
            penninge, and the omission of De Tillye, I could Neuer=<lb break="no"/>
            thelesse Not gett both the l<ex>ett</ex>res such as they weare, vntill <lb/>
            the seventh daye after the first promise: On the viijth of <lb/>
            September beinge fully . xxiiij. dayes from the exhib=<lb break="no"/>
            itinge of the Proposition, this answere Was deliuered. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            The answere of her Highnes Deputies, to the Writinge <lb/>
            of the Ambassador of the kinge of greate Brittaine Intit=<lb break="no"/>
            led a Sciant proposition. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            It is verie certain that in this Conference hath alwais <lb/>
            ben presupposed that the suspecnsyon of Armes ought <lb/>
            to be vniversall in all Germany because otherwise a p<ex>ar</ex>=<lb break="no"/>
            ticuller Suspention w<ex>i</ex>thin two two Pallatinates could  <lb/>
            Not subsist, and that for this Reason, The Powere of <lb/>
            the Marquesse Tarlacke, Duke Christian of Brounswicke <lb/>
            and Count Mansfied haue ben demaunded, in regard <lb/>
            also that yf the said Suspention were Not vniversall it <lb/>
            would turne to the Manifest preiudice of the Confeder=<lb break="no"/>
            ates of the faithfull Subiectes of the Emperor, and be <lb/>
            contrarye to the intention of his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie Imperiall and <lb/>
            wherein it is still Necessarye to persist and hould fir=<lb break="no"/>
            melie; And that the kinge of Greate Brittaine oblige <lb/>
            him selfe to this assurance w<ex>i</ex>th the Prince his Sonne <lb/>
            in Lawe and the Rest as aboue. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Moreouer the invasion, and Hostillitie vsed fewe days <lb/>
            since, by the Army of the said Prince in these Countrys <lb/>
            and States of his Catholicke Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie being a thinge No=<lb break="no"/>
            torious, It is fitt that in the Actors of the said Suspension <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">there be also ex=</fw>
            <pb n="233v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f233v/add_ms_4149_f233v.jpg"/>
            there be also expresly sett downe, that it shalbe observed w<ex>i</ex>th <lb/>
            all the States of his Catholique Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie aswell those of th=<lb break="no"/>
            ese Lowe Countrys, as of Spaine, Itally and the Rest  <lb/>
            in regarde the Army lead and Comaunded by the <unclear>
                    <del rend="strikethrough">aff</del>
                </unclear> <lb/>
            aforesaid Duke Christian and Mansfield hath suffiti=<lb break="no"/>
            ently discouered the bad designes both of the said Pr=<lb break="no"/>
            ince, and of them against his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie Lykewise seinge <lb/>
            the said Mansfield hath refused to accepte the grace of <lb/>
            Pardon of his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie wherby he Might haue returned <lb/>
            to his Regall service, and to his owne Naturall obed=<lb break="no"/>
            ience, and hath w<ex>i</ex>thall drawen from this Cittie him <lb/>
            whom he had sent thither to treate on this his behal=<lb break="no"/>
            lfe. Seeing also howe litle he can hope for, from <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Hollanders, and howe his Pride Will not lett him rema=<lb break="no"/>
            ine in Holland, there beinge w<ex>i</ex>thall perticuller advirtise=<lb break="no"/>
            ments that his ende and purpose is to returne to trouble <lb/>
            the affaires of Germany: Lastlie Seeinge the Duke Ch=<lb break="no"/>
            ristian will take the same Course, as he hath also exp=<lb break="no"/>
            reslie declared to the Count of He<unclear>n</unclear>yn and Secretarye <lb/>
            Brvne<unclear>nn</unclear>, There is Non that seeth Not cleerlie the tr=<lb break="no"/>
            uth of that w<ex>hi</ex>ch hath ben saide, And that it is Nowe Mo=<lb break="no"/>
            re Necessarie then euer to prouide for the generall ass=<lb break="no"/>
            urance. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            And although in regard the said Duke Christian and Man=<lb break="no"/>
            sfield refuse to enter into the treatie of the said suspenti=<lb break="no"/>
            on: yea Contrariwise giue me one of the principall imped=<lb break="no"/>
            imentes to it: Her Highnes Might w<ex>i</ex>th verie greate Rea=<lb break="no"/>
            son and good ground Not admit the said Suspentio; yet <lb/>
            for the desire she hath to satisfie the kinge of Greate <lb/>
            Brittaine  and to Make peace vnto the World, that on th=<lb break="no"/>
            is side there is Noe Wante of Readines to performe a ge=<lb break="no"/>
            nerall quietnesse: Her highnes Will willinglie give ea=<lb break="no"/>
            re to such Meanes, as May be propounded and advirtised <lb/>
            for the Establishment, and setlinge of the said generall ass=<lb break="no"/>
            urance duringe the Suspention on both parties. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            At the deliuerie thereof though I protested that the Siege <lb/>
            of Hidleberge Continuing I could Not Speake one Word <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">More by way of treatie</fw>
            <pb n="234r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f234r/add_ms_4149_f234r.jpg"/>
            more by waye of Treatie: yet I could Not but tell them <lb/>
            that this answere was verie different from that w<ex>hi</ex>ch yo<ex>u</ex>r <lb/>
            Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie expected, it Containinge for the Most parte but a  <lb/>
            rearminac<ex>i</ex>on against yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s sonne in Lawe, vpon those <lb/>
            suspentions, that were before alledged, and by me ful=<lb break="no"/>
            lie answered: That i did not thinke yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s Merites <lb/>
            to the howse of Austria, had ben so slightlie vallued, <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            those thinges should haue ben touched againe, Muche <lb/>
            lesse that they would Couple this Cause, w<ex>i</ex>th the Cause  <lb/>
            of the vnited Prouinces, from w<ex>hi</ex>ch it was euer seuered, <lb/>
            To w<ex>hi</ex>ch they replied that her Highnes had done what <lb/>
            she Coulde, That she had written her l<ex>ett</ex>res to the Arche <lb/>
            duke Leopolde and the Counte of Tilly. I answered <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie did Not expecte from the Infanta offices of <lb/>
            intreatie, but to exercise that power w<ex>hi</ex>ch she had to Co=<lb break="no"/>
            maunde them absolutely to w<ex>i</ex>thdrawe theire Armes: Thi=<lb break="no"/>
            nges beinge in these termes, And I hauinge received <lb/>
            directe Comaundement from yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie to give ouer trea=<lb break="no"/>
            tinge, and to returne to yo<ex>u</ex>r presence, yf the Siege of <lb/>
            Hildleberge were Not remoued. I thought fitt before My <lb/>
            departure to Make a replie to the answere, aswell to re=<lb break="no"/>
            fute imputac<ex>i</ex>ons layed by yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s sonne in Lawe as to <lb/>
            leaue them w<ex>i</ex>thout excuse by declaringe yo<ex>u</ex>r Last offere <lb/>
            viz. of ioyninge W<ex>i</ex>th the Emperour against the Duke Ch=<lb break="no"/>
            ristian, and Counte of Mansfield yf they would pers=<lb break="no"/>
            ist in beinge refractory, aswell in regard of a Suspen=<lb break="no"/>
            tion and Deposition as of a Peace: But in the Meane <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">tyme</del> while accordinge to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s order I moued her hi=<lb break="no"/>
            ghnes againe about her remouinge of the foresaid Siege, <lb/>
            And she answered as before, that she was desirous to gi=<lb break="no"/>
            ve yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie all Contentment that laye in her powere, for <lb/>
            the good of yo<ex>u</ex>r Children, But to Write to Monsure de Tilly <lb/>
            in such sorte as I demaunded, were to Noe purpose beca=<lb break="no"/>
            use she knewe he Would Not obaye her, where vnto after <lb/>
            Much debatinge, when I sawe I could <del rend="strikethrough">not</del> prevaile No <lb/>
            more in that pointe, I replied that then by grauntinge  <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">a Cessation w<ex>hi</ex>ch was</fw>
            <pb n="234v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f234v/add_ms_4149_f234v.jpg"/>
            a Cessation, w<ex>hi</ex>ch was the Subiecte of my imployment, <lb/>
            She Might at once give an ende to all inconveniences, <lb/>
            aswell by freeinge of Hidleberge, as by Securinge the <lb/>
            other two Townes: But yf yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie could Not receave <lb/>
            the satisfaction you expected and yo<ex>u</ex>r Merites iustlie Ch=<lb break="no"/>
            allenged, I was by yo<ex>u</ex>r Expresse Comaundement to take <lb/>
            My leaue of her Highnes and to returne: Where vpon <lb/>
            she prayed Me to propound it to the deputies, promissi=<lb break="no"/>
            nge an answere w<ex>i</ex>th as Much satisfaction as she could <lb/>
            give; I said I would performe her will, But w<ex>i</ex>thall <lb/>
            prayed her that the answere Might be Catigoricall and <lb/>
            Speedye, because the tyme limited by yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie for My <lb/>
            Staye exceeded Not Sixe Dayes: This passed on the <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">xj</del> .xth. of September, and on the xijth (for the .xjth <lb/>
            was Hollidaye) I deliuered this Replie. / .
         </p>
         <p rend="align-centre">
            <hi rend="italic">
               A Reply to the Answere of her high=<lb break="no"/>
               nes Deputies. / .
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            His Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie of Greate Brittaine hath Neuer had other <lb/>
            designe then that the Suspention of Armes. w<ex>hi</ex>ch are ha=<lb break="no"/>
            ndled in this treatie should be vniversall thorough all <lb/>
            Germany, and to this ende hath offered asmuch as in <lb/>
            honore and Equitie can be expected from him as ap=<lb break="no"/>
            peareth, besides that w<ex>hi</ex>ch hath ben often tymes saide by <lb/>
            word of Mouth, by the articles of proposition: Now it is <lb/>
            Evidente inough by the eventes, that at this tyme Ger=<lb break="no"/>
            many is No waye infested by the Armes of those Whoe <lb/>
            haue ben heretofore the Auxiliaries of his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s Sonne <lb/>
            in Lawe: for the Marquesse of Turlacke hath altogether <lb/>
            disarmed certayne Moneths, and Medled No more w<ex>i</ex>th <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Cause: The Ducke Christian of Brounswicke and the Co=<lb break="no"/>
            unt of Mansfild are retired w<ex>i</ex>th the Remainder of their <lb/>
            forces towardes the united States to be imployed in their <lb/>
            Service w<ex>hi</ex>ch hath Noe relation to Germanie, Soe as <lb/>
            for the present, the hinderance w<ex>hi</ex>ch proceeded from the <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">Auxilliaries is</fw>
            <pb n="235r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f235r/add_ms_4149_f235r.jpg"/>
            Auxiliaries is wholly taken awaye. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            For the tyme to come, to prevent all inconveniencis, w<ex>hi</ex>ch May <lb/>
            springe from the Quarrell in Germanye, his said Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie <lb/>
            declareth that somever hath ben promised on his parte <lb/>
            in regarde of a Peace, he will performe, and oblige him <lb/>
            selfe therevnto, in regarde of the foresaid Suspension and <lb/>
            deposition (viz) That in case the said late Auxiliaries <lb/>
            shall attempte any Hostillitie w<ex>i</ex>thin the Empire duringe <lb/>
            the Truce he Will Conioyne his forces against them <lb/>
            w<ex>i</ex>th those of the Emperour his Freindes and Allyes. / .
         </p>
         <p>
            Touchinge his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s Sonne in Lawe, it seemeth ver=<lb break="no"/>
            rye Strange that the Army w<ex>hi</ex>ch he hath soe Manifest=<lb break="no"/>
            lye and reallye discharged, soe Many Monethes since is <lb/>
            still attributed or ascribed to him, And yet More strange, <lb/>
            that from this incertaine presupposition, men will pro=<lb break="no"/>
            ceede to such demaundes, w<ex>hi</ex>ch were Never pretended her=<lb break="no"/>
            tofore, for sithence the said Brunswicke and Mansfield <lb/>
            are retired into Hollande, and there entertayned, to de=<lb break="no"/>
            maunde that in the accorde of the Suspension, These <lb/>
            Lowe Countryes be specified is Nothinge else then to <lb/>
            demaund that w<ex>hi</ex>ch cannot welbe expected w<ex>i</ex>thout the <lb/>
            consent and approbation of the vnited States, and to in=<lb break="no"/>
            volue this Cause w<ex>i</ex>th theirs, from w<ex>hi</ex>ch it hath ben alwa=<lb break="no"/>
            is seperate: But if the Condition of thinges Were su=<lb break="no"/>
            che that a generall treatie Were harkened vnto, it is <lb/>
            Not to be doubted, that his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie of greate Brittayne <lb/>
            would willinglie imploye him selfe therein for the Est=<lb break="no"/>
            ablishment and settinge of a generall quietnes, aswell <lb/>
            in these estates of his Catholique Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie as euery where <lb/>
            ellse: Now whereas forsoemuch  as concerneth the pre=<lb break="no"/>
            sent Constitution of the affaires of these Lowe Countrys, <lb/>
            His Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie of Greate Brittayne doth in such sorte testefie <lb/>
            bothe his good affection and impartiallitie givinge lea=<lb break="no"/>
            ve to soe greate a Number of his Subiectes amongst tho=<lb break="no"/>
            se Maines of honorable quallitie to followe this Warre <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">in the service and</fw>
            <pb n="235v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f235v/add_ms_4149_f235v.jpg"/>
            in the service and defence of his Catholique Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie And <lb/>
            Whereas also there is for the present Noe enemy in Ge=<lb break="no"/>
            rmany, Nor feare of any for the future, in regarde of <ex>tha</ex>t <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch his said Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie of Greate Brittaine doth promise &amp; <lb/>
            vndertake for himselfe and his Sonne in Lawe, And <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            offer he Maketh Nowe to pursue the said Auxilliaries <lb/>
            as perturbers of the publique Peace, yf they returne <lb/>
            to trouble and infest the Empire in any parte thereof <lb/>
            duringe the tyme of the treatie: For this Cause his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie  <lb/>
            aforesaid pretendinge Nothinge else by the said Truce, <lb/>
            then to prepare a Peceable Waye to the Restitution of <lb/>
            his Children to theire Patrimonye and hereditarie  <lb/>
            Honours and Dignities, demaundeth a Cessation of <lb/>
            Armes accordinge to his Merrites towards the Howse <lb/>
            of Austria in tyme past, and offeres for the tyme to <lb/>
            Come, Beyond w<ex>hi</ex>ch he knoweth Not What expedient  <lb/>
            <del rend="strikethrough">agreement</del> agreeinge w<ex>i</ex>th his honoure canbe propou=<lb break="no"/>
            nded or advised for the accomodatinge of this affaire: <lb/>
            At the said tyme hauinge said what was fitt accordi=<lb break="no"/>
            nge to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s order: I pressed perticullerlie to have <lb/>
            a cleere and punctuall answere w<ex>i</ex>thin the tyme before <lb/>
            Menc<ex>i</ex>oned longer then W<ex>hi</ex>ch I could Not attende it, vnli=<lb break="no"/>
            esse it were to haue a Cessation, for the W<ex>hi</ex>ch I Mighte  <lb/>
            adventure some fewe dayes More, But they insisted  <lb/>
            on the accusinge of the Ellector, and on the intention of <lb/>
            the Duke Christian and Mansfield to returne into Ger=<lb break="no"/>
            manye, Wherevpon after Much dispute I intreated <lb/>
            them to state the question thus, whether it were better <lb/>
            that the said Duke Christian and Mansfield should re=<lb break="no"/>
            turne to infest Germanye hauinge yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie their En=<lb break="no"/>
            emie, and yo<ex>u</ex>r forces bent against them, or <unclear>
                    <del rend="strikethrough">doin</del>
                </unclear> doe it <lb/>
            beinge Countenanced by you, and all yo<ex>u</ex>r Freindes: Th=<lb break="no"/>
            ey Confessed the former Were Much better: But asked Me <lb/>
            howe them selues should be secured, for it were verye <lb/>
            strange (they saide) they should plucke the thorne out of <lb/>
            theire Neighboures foote to putt it into theire owne: I <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">tould them that was</fw>
            <pb n="236r" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f236r/add_ms_4149_f236r.jpg"/>
            tould them, that was whollie an other Case, and prayed <lb/>
            them to Consider the Equallitie of yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s carriage, and <lb/>
            suffringe yo<ex>u</ex>r Subiectes to serve her highnes: But wh=<lb break="no"/>
            en I spake of that, and of yo<ex>u</ex>r Merittes, they fledd to Ge=<lb break="no"/>
            rmany, And when I spake of yo<ex>u</ex>r offer to ioyne w<ex>i</ex>th the <lb/>
            Emperour, they fled backe to Holland: w<ex>i</ex>thin two dayes <lb/>
            after I received two dispatches Confirminge yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>t<ex>ies</ex> <lb/>
            Comaundement of Retourninge, if I could not prev=<lb break="no"/>
            aille where vpon on the xvth, I had Audience againe <lb/>
            of her highnes:  In w<ex>hi</ex>ch I tould her that yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s Com=<lb break="no"/>
            aund for My returne to yo<ex>u</ex>r Presence, in case yo<ex>u</ex>r iust de=<lb break="no"/>
            maundes were Not yeilded vnto, was renewed by sh<unclear>e</unclear>=<lb break="no"/>
            she directions: Soe as I might Not longer attende: <lb/>
            Whereto she replied, that she had written to Don Car=<lb break="no"/>
            los to propound vnto Yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie an Expedient Whereby <lb/>
            the busines Might be Well accomodated, and therefore <lb/>
            prayed me to tarrye vntill she received an Answer from  <lb/>
            him: But I tould her the Expedient had No referrence <lb/>
            to My Charge, that I had longe since disclaimed it, <lb/>
            That yo<ex>u</ex>r Comaunde Was directe and expresse, and in <lb/>
            a thinge that did Mainelie touch yo<ex>u</ex>r Honoure Whereof <lb/>
            I was to be tenderlie Carefull, I shall Not Need to tro=<lb break="no"/>
            uble yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie w<ex>i</ex>th all that passed then, beinge the same <lb/>
            for the Most parte w<ex>hi</ex>ch had ben before. One Pointe I <lb/>
            vrged More perticulerlie, That yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie expected fr=<lb break="no"/>
            om the Kinge of Spayne the same assistance if the  <lb/>
            Emperoure would Not restore yo<ex>u</ex>r Childrens patrimo=<lb break="no"/>
            nie and dignities, w<ex>hi</ex>ch yo<ex>u</ex>r selfe would haue given the <lb/>
            Emperour against yo<ex>u</ex>r owne Sonne in Lawe yf hee <lb/>
            had ben still Refractorie: I added w<ex>i</ex>thall that yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie <lb/>
            was well assured the said Kinge of Spayne, aswell  <lb/>
            in regarde of the Amitie betweene you, as of his ow=<lb break="no"/>
            ne honoure, would not well digest a repulse aftere <lb/>
            <unclear>so maye</unclear> Meditations Made by him to the Emperoure <lb/>
            least to the World it should stayne those Manie profess=<lb break="no"/>
            ions w<ex>hi</ex>ch he had Made. Wherevnto her Answere was <lb/>
            <fw type="catch" place="bot-right">that she assured</fw>
            <pb n="236v" facs="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f236v/add_ms_4149_f236v.jpg"/>
            that she assured her selfe, the said Kinge of Spayne Would  <lb/>
            Continewe to doe all good offices for the Restituc<ex>i</ex>on of the Pr=<lb break="no"/>
            rince Pallatine, and shewe by Effectes the desire he hath <lb/>
            to ioyne in      amytie w<ex>i</ex>th yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie and that hee <lb/>
            would thinke it <del rend="strikethrough">dish s<unclear>h</unclear>
                </del>  dishonorable Not to perfecte that <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch he hath begun, or Not to Make good the promise he <lb/>
            hath Made to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie Who hath deserved a Crowne <lb/>
            of Palme, by yo<ex>u</ex>r Royall Carriage. And hereto she ioy=<lb break="no"/>
            ned also a profession of her owne Constant resolution <lb/>
            to Continue the Contributinge of her best offices and as=<lb break="no"/>
            istance. In the Supposinge I Ment to take My leave <lb/>
            at that tyme., She pressed Me soe earnestlie to haue <lb/>
            patience for one day, that I held it incivill to denie it: <lb/>
            My last Audience Was the <hi rend="italic">xvijth</hi> of September in w<ex>hi</ex>ch <lb/>
            her Highnes falliunge on the busines vsed those excu=<lb break="no"/>
            ses of Not givinge yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie Contentment, and such pro=<lb break="no"/>
            fession of her desire and Care to see yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>ti<ex>e</ex>s Children <lb/>
            restored, that although they Were in a Maner the same <lb/>
            w<ex>hi</ex>ch she had divers tymes vsed, yet they were deliu=<lb break="no"/>
            ered w<ex>i</ex>th More earnestnest: The same Language Was <lb/>
            held, and w<ex>i</ex>th the same earnestnest, both by the Spani=<lb break="no"/>
            sh Ambassador, and by the Deputies severallie: Among=<lb break="no"/>
            st other thinges, I Must Note. That Whereas the said <lb/>
            Ambassador had heard that vpon her Highnes pressing <lb/>
            of Me againe to tarrie vntill she had received answer <lb/>
            from Don Carlos, I had tould her I was assured yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie <lb/>
            Would Not Hazard yo<ex>u</ex>r Honour by Continuinge yo<ex>u</ex>r Am=<lb break="no"/>
            bassador there to be frustrate w<ex>i</ex>th Scorne a third tyme: <lb/>
            He said they Were Not Curious where the busines we=<lb break="no"/>
            re <del rend="strikethrough">Caried</del> handled, for they Would seeke Yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie any <lb/>
            where: And it was theire generall Sayinge, that al=<lb break="no"/>
            beit, I were recalled: yet they held Not the treatie <lb/>
            to be broken. Thus I haue trulie and breeflie rela=<lb break="no"/>
            ted to yo<ex>u</ex>r Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie all the important passages of the Trea=<lb break="no"/>
            tye. / .
         </p> 
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f226r/add_ms_4149_f226r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f226v/add_ms_4149_f226v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="3" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f227r/add_ms_4149_f227r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="4" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f227v/add_ms_4149_f227v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="5" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f228r/add_ms_4149_f228r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="6" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f228v/add_ms_4149_f228v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="7" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f229r/add_ms_4149_f229r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="8" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f229v/add_ms_4149_f229v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="9" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f230r/add_ms_4149_f230r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="10" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f230v/add_ms_4149_f230v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="11" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f231r/add_ms_4149_f231r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="12" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f231v/add_ms_4149_f231v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="13" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f232r/add_ms_4149_f232r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="14" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f232v/add_ms_4149_f232v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="15" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f233r/add_ms_4149_f233r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="16" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f233v/add_ms_4149_f233v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="17" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f234r/add_ms_4149_f234r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="18" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f234v/add_ms_4149_f234v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="19" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f235r/add_ms_4149_f235r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="20" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f235v/add_ms_4149_f235v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="21" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f236r/add_ms_4149_f236r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="22" url="/bl/add_ms_4149_part/add_ms_4149_f236v/add_ms_4149_f236v.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>