<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters</title>
            <author>
               <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0055">John Leslie, Earl of Rothes</persName>
            </author>
            <author>
               <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0020">Philip Herbert, Earl of Pembroke and Montgomery</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
                    <name>Noah Millstone</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
                    <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
                    <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
                    <name>Richard Bell</name>
                    <resp>Research Associate</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="VA">
                    <name>Victoria Anker</name>
                    <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
                    <name>Mike Jones</name>
                    <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
                </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
                <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
                <date when="2017">2017</date>
            </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/BLAddMS11045.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_11045">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <repository>British Library</repository>
               <collection>Additional</collection>
               <idno>MS 11045</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">British Library, Additional MS 11045</p>
            </msDesc>
            <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness">
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Egerton_MS_3876">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <repository>British Library</repository>
               <collection>Egerton</collection>
               <idno>MS 3876</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Harley_MS_1219">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <repository>British Library</repository>
               <collection>Harley</collection>
               <idno>MS 1219</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_4106">
                <country>United Kingdom</country>
                <settlement>London</settlement>
                <repository>British Library</repository>
                <collection>Additional</collection>
                <idno>MS 4106</idno>
                <msName/>
             </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_72432">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <repository>British Library</repository>
               <collection>Additional</collection>
               <idno>MS 72432</idno>
               <msName>Weckherlin Papers</msName>
            </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <msIdentifier xml:id="BL_Add_MS_28011">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <repository>British Library</repository>
               <collection>Additional</collection>
               <idno>MS 28011</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated">
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLAddMS28011.xml">British Library, Additional MS 28011, ff. 48r–49r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLAddMS4106.xml">British Library, Additional MS 4106, ff. 191r–196v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BLEgertonMS3876.xml">British Library, Egerton MS 3876, ff. 205r–206v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Add_MS_72432.xml">British Library, Additional MS 72432, ff. 116r–117r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Add_MS_72432.xml">British Library, Additional MS 72432, ff. 118r–119r</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/BL_Harley_MS_1219.xml">British Library, Harley MS 1219, ff. 409r–413v</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Huntington_EL_7830.xml">Huntington Library,  EL 7830</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/KA_U2691Oo208.xml">Kent Archives,  U26/1/Oo208</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="ms" target="../mss/Woburn_Abbey_MS_25.xml">Woburn Abbey,  MS 25</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1640" from="1640-01-29" to="1640-03-08">29 January &amp; 8 March 1640</date>
            <placeName corresp="../places/places.xml#PL0009">Edinburgh</placeName>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term>letter</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term/>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change status="draft" who="#RB" when="2017-10-04"/>
            <change status="proofread" who="#NM" when="2018-06-06"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         
         <pb n="97r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11045_part/add_ms_11045_f097r/add_ms_11045_f097r.jpg"/>
         <p>
            Concerneing my lord Savile, I doe heare, that there are twoe <lb/>
            more wittnesses, that will depose they heard him tell the people <lb/>
            to animate them to chouse Mr. <sic>Hoborne</sic> a Burgesse, That Mr. <lb/>
            <sic>Hoborne</sic> did alwayes oppose the kinge, the shipp monye and all <lb/>
            monopolies what soever; It seemes the first accuser declard <lb/>
            soe much, but I was misinformd; but of this, I am certaine, <lb/>
            That their lo<ex>rdshi</ex>ps did not approve of that which my lord <lb/>
            Savile confest himselfe
            <gap extent="multiple lines" reason="elision"/>
            <pb n="97v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11045_part/add_ms_11045_f097v/add_ms_11045_f097v.jpg"/>
            <pb n="98r" facs="/bl/add_ms_11045_part/add_ms_11045_f098r/add_ms_11045_f098r.jpg"/>
            <gap extent="multiple lines" reason="elision"/>
            My lord Chamberleine <lb/>
            receavd a letter lately from my lord Rothes out of Scotland which <lb/>
            hee shewed to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie being much offended, my lord Rothes should <lb/>
            fasten such Calumnies vpon him, the coppie of which letter, <lb/>
            with my lord Chamberleins aunsweare here followeth:
         </p>
         <p>
            my noble lord, <space extent="6" unit="chars"/>	I haue large incouragements to vse <lb/>
            freedome, both from your owne favours to mee, and my affections <lb/>
            to your lo<ex>rdshi</ex>pe, and soe might expostulate for with draweing <lb/>
            your wonted, and even lately expressed respects at the Campe <lb/>
            to this nation: you found wee had reason for our lawfull de=<lb break="no"/>
            fence, and that wee had loyall harts to our Prince, and Iustice <lb/>
            in all our desires, which movd you to pleade for vs, and soe <lb/>
            ingagd the affections of many to you, but sithence, when my lord <lb/>
            Traquaire made his relation <del rend="strikethrough">
                    <gap reason="illegible" quantity="3" unit="chars"/>h</del> that movd hard conclusions <lb/>
            against vs, not requireing soe much, as that it should not obtaine <lb/>
            truth to the preiudice of a whole nation, till wee weere heard, <lb/>
            and agreeing that an armye should bee leavyed, and lending <lb/>
            monyes hath much greived vs, to bee disappointed of one wee <lb/>
            soe much trusted: I haue therefore made bold to intreate <lb/>
            that wee may keepe better correspondencie, or ells by mistake, <lb/>
            wee maye bee brought againe to begin a mischeife, that will <lb/>
            not end <add place="above">in</add> our dayes, as wee haue formerly declind yt, soe shall <lb/>
            it not bee our fault, and it lyeth in your lo<ex>rdshi</ex>pe, and other greate <lb/>
            persons to pr<ex>e</ex>vent these evills; you haue livd in all greate <lb/>
            ease, and plentie as any nation in the world, and if you like <lb/>
            to interrupt your owne happinesse for the pleasure of some <lb/>
            <milestone unit="section" type="LM"/>
            <seg style="transform:rotateZ(90deg)">
               Prelates, whoe will share little in the hardshipp, and daungers, that will bee indured, you are not well advised: The Earle of Dum=<lb break="no"/>
               farmlyn, and lord Lowdun are sent with full information of our businesse. they will waight vpon your lo<ex>rdshi</ex>pe, and expect your <lb/>
               wonted assistance, They all asmuch as maye bee decline warre, except you will needes nowe haue it: wee hope your lo<ex>rdshi</ex>pe, <lb/>
               and others will make vse of these reasons for the right end, which will fix a greate deale of obligation from both nations <lb/>
               on you, and shall infinitely increase my respects, desireing to continue your lo<ex>rdshi</ex>ps humble servant, Rothes: Edenburg 29. January: <lb/>
               My lord Chamberleins aunsweare followeth, <space extent="6" unit="chars"/> My good lord, <space extent="5" unit="chars"/>	The Civilityes, and good respects which I placed 
            </seg>
            <pb n="98v" facs="/bl/add_ms_11045_part/add_ms_11045_f098v/add_ms_11045_f098v.jpg"/>
                <tei:add xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="LM">1639 March .13. E. R.</tei:add>vpon you, and your nation at my tyme of my being in the Campe, <lb/>
            you stile incouragements, and insinuate them, as reasons, why <lb/>
            you maye expostulate with mee: <add place="above">your</add>
                <del rend="strikethrough">
                    <gap reason="illegible" quantity="2" unit="chars"/>
                </del> premisses, I allowe <lb/>
            you, but your <del rend="strikethrough">infernall</del> inference I returne you againe, as fuller <lb/>
            of sophistry, and meane designe, then of truth, and reason: first, <lb/>
            I never allowed your defence lawfully vndertaken by other armes <lb/>
            then by Petitions, and prayers to your Master, I never found <lb/>
            loyaltie in your Covenant, or duety in your takeing vpp armes: <lb/>
            I never affirmed the Iustice of your cause, neither did I consider <lb/>
            soe much the meritts thereof, as I did your vnwarrantable, and <lb/>
            tumultuous disobedience herein vnto your kinge, with the vexation <lb/>
            and disturbance it brought uppon the nobillity of this kingdome, <lb/>
            neither was I in all this commotion, your advocate, but for other <lb/>
            reasons suffered my selfe to become a mediator to his Ma<ex>jes</ex>tie for <lb/>
            your peace, and forgivenesse, movd there vnto by your frequent <lb/>
            protestations of payeing all duety, and loyaltie, unto your masters <lb/>
            commaunds: if from hence you happily gaind from mee an easier <lb/>
            credulity, then your maskt designes deservd, at my hands, I knowe <lb/>
            not why you should obtrude to mee an alteration of my opinion <lb/>
            or a withdraweing of my (but conditionall) respects to you: thus <lb/>
            farr in aunsweare what concernes mee: And nowe, as a <lb/>
            Counsellour of England, lett mee bee bold to expostulate with you <lb/>
            vpon that which followeth in your letter: Howe comes it to <lb/>
            passe, that you should vpbraide vs, or expect from vs, that <lb/>
            wee should not give creditt to my lord Traquaires relation, <lb/>
            That wee did not mediate with the kinge to change his <lb/>
            resolution of sending forth an armye, and that wee did not <lb/>
            denye the kinge loanes of mony, for his service: <space extent="4" unit="chars"/> my lord, <lb/>
            These inforcements perhaps, as little become you, as it is <lb/>
            certainely unlawfull, and vndutifull <del rend="strikethrough">to</del>
                <add place="above">in</add> the subiects of Eng=<lb break="no"/>
            land to dispute it with their kinge: you maye pretend <lb/>
            Religion to bee the sole cause of your greivance, but wee be=<lb break="no"/>
            leive it a woefull Religion here, that hath thus devested <lb/>
            it selfe of all morrall duety, and civility to their Prince: <lb/>
            nay, you goe further, you threatten, and feare vs with a <lb/>
            mischeife, that will not end in our dayes, and boldly make <lb/>
            it your owne act to haue declind it heretofore without obliga=<lb break="no"/>
            tion to the kings mercy at all; you tell vs of plenty, and ease, <lb/>
            and happinesse many yeares inioyed, and wonder, wee <lb/>
            should expose all these to hazard for the pleasure of some <lb/>
            fewe Prelates: <space extent="4" unit="chars"/> my lord, These are arguments for <lb/>
            common people, and men of broaken fancies to feede vpon, <lb/>
            and such suggestions will not find, nor make a party here; <lb/>
            Perhapps it maye blowe them into a flame, whose zeale <lb/>
            had already burnt vpp their duety, and conscionable alle=<lb break="no"/>
            gience vnto their master: <space extent="4" unit="chars"/> To bee short <add place="above">as</add> I never held <lb/>
            a correspondencie of businesse with your lo<ex>rdshi</ex>pe, soe your letters
            <milestone unit="section" type="LM"/>
            <seg style="transform:rotateZ(90deg)">
               hath assured mee, it is daungerous to begin yt: yet for the Peace of both the Churches, and kingdomes, I will adventure <lb/>
               to give you this Intelligence, That wee haue not <del rend="strikethrough">this Intelligence</del> in our Councells here, proceeded ag<ex>ains</ex>t you without <lb/>
               deliberation, a good conscience, and a iust sence of honour: neither shall I, or any of vs bee intreated, or feared by <lb/>
               any of you from contributeing our assents, or fortunes there vnto, but as our Master shall commaund vs. Lastly, Know you, <lb/>
               my lord of Rothes, that the returne of my old freindshipp to you is to bee expected, when I shall heare of your renova=<lb break="no"/>
               tion, Bee simply my lord Rothes, and not a Covenanter, I shall bee the same freind, Pembroke, 8. March 1639./
            </seg>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="align-right">March the 13.th 1639</hi>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/bl/add_ms_11045_part/add_ms_11045_f097r/add_ms_11045_f097r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="2" url="/bl/add_ms_11045_part/add_ms_11045_f097v/add_ms_11045_f097v.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="3" url="/bl/add_ms_11045_part/add_ms_11045_f098r/add_ms_11045_f098r.jpg"/>
      <graphic n="4" url="/bl/add_ms_11045_part/add_ms_11045_f098v/add_ms_11045_f098v.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>