<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Speech to the House of Commons</title>
            <author>
               <persName corresp="../people/people.xml#P0033">Sir Thomas Wentworth</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="NM">
               <name>Noah Millstone</name>
               <resp>Principal Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SV">
               <name>Sebastiaan Verweij</name>
               <resp>Co-Investigator MPESE</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RB">
               <name>Richard Bell</name>
               <resp>Research Associate</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="VA">
               <name>Victoria Anker</name>
               <resp>BRIHC Research Impact Fellow</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MJ">
               <name>Mike Jones</name>
               <resp>Research Software Engineer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="MMQ">
               <name>Moira MacQuaide</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="VE">
               <name>Victor Eyles</name>
               <resp>Transcription Volunteer</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt xml:id="mpese_pubstat">
            <publisher>Manuscript Pamphleteering in Early Stuart England (MPESE)</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <msDesc corresp="../mss/SHC_1248_1.xml">
               <msIdentifier xml:id="SHC_1248_1">
               <country>United Kingdom</country>
               <settlement>Woking</settlement>
               <repository>Surrey History Centre</repository>
               <collection/>
               <idno>1248/1</idno>
               <msName/>
            </msIdentifier>
                    <p xml:id="ms-label-generated">Surrey History Centre,  1248/1</p>
            </msDesc>
                <listBibl xml:id="mss_witness_generated"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
         <creation>
            <date when="1627-03-22">22 March 1627</date>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="EN">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="text-type">
               <term>speech</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="topic-keyword">
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2018-09-13" who="#RB" status="draft"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#MMQ" status="transcribed"/>
            <change when="2018-08-20" who="#VE" status="transcribed"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="#4" facs="/shc/1248_1/1248_1_4/1248_1_4.jpg"/>
         <head>
            S<ex>i</ex>r Tho<ex>mas</ex>: Wentworth <ex>th</ex>e 22th of Mar: 1627
         </head>
         <p>
            May this daies resolution bee as happy as I conceiue <ex>th</ex>e proposition (which <lb/>
            now makes mee wise) seasonable, and necessary. For wheather wee shall looke <lb/>
            vppon <ex>th</ex>e King, or his people, if did neuer more behoue (vs (this great <lb/>
            Physician) <ex>th</ex>e Parlament to effeckt a true consente among <ex>th</ex>e partes <lb/>
            then now. This debate carries with it addable asspeckt. Towards <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            Soveraine, towards <ex>th</ex>e Subieckt thought both bee Innocent both are <lb/>
            in dainger, In <ex>th</ex>e representation of Iniuries, I shall crave your <lb/>
            attention. In <ex>th</ex>e cure I shall beseech your equall cares, and better <lb/>
            Iudments. Surely in <ex>th</ex>e greatest humilitie I speake it) these illegall <lb/>
            waies are punishments, and markes of Indignation. The rasing <lb/>
            by levys, strenthned by co<ex>m</ex>mission; with unheard of instrucktions, : <lb/>
            <ex>th</ex>e billiting of Souldiers by Leftenants, and deputy Leftenants,haue <lb/>
            binne as if they could haue perswaded Christian Princes (nay worlds) <lb/>
            <ex>th</ex>e right of Empire had binne long agoe, to take away by strong hande <lb/>
            and these haue indeauored (as far as was possible for them) to doe it <lb/>
            This hath not binne done by <ex>th</ex>e King (vnder <ex>th</ex>e pleasing shade of whose <lb/>
            crowne, I hope wee shall euer gather <ex>th</ex>e <unclear>srutes</unclear> of Iustice) but by <lb/>
            Proiecktons. They haue extended <ex>th</ex>e prerogatiue of <ex>th</ex>e King beeyond <lb/>
            <ex>th</ex>e iust li<ex>m</ex>metts. Which makes aiarring harmony of the whole. <lb/>
            They haue rent from vs <ex>th</ex>e light of our eyes, forced acompany of <lb/>
            guests, worse then <ex>th</ex>e ordinances of France <unclear>vitialed</unclear> our wifes <lb/>
            and daughters, before our faces, brought <ex>th</ex>e crowne to greater <lb/>
            want then euer by anticipating of <ex>th</ex>e reuenews; And can <ex>th</ex>e shepard <lb/>
            be smitten and <ex>th</ex>e sheepe not scattered. They haue introduced a priuy <lb/>
            Counsell, rauishing at once <ex>th</ex>e sphere, of all ancient gouernment. <lb/>
            Imprisoning vs with ou<add place="above">t</add>
                <unclear>-</unclear> bale, or bonde. (They haue taken from vs <lb/>
            (or shall I say indeed what haue they left vs) all means of supplying, <lb/>
            <ex>th</ex>e King, and ingratiating our selues with him. Taken vp <ex>th</ex>e rootes <lb/>
            of all propriety, which if it bee not seasonablely set again in to <ex>th</ex>e <lb/>
            ground, by his Ma<ex>jes</ex>ties owne hande, wee shall haue steed<unclear>-</unclear> of <unclear>Beuty</unclear>, <unclear>Baldnesse</unclear> <lb/>
            To <ex>th</ex>e making <add place="above">of</add> this hole againe, I shall apply myselfe, and propound <lb/>
            a remedy to all these diseases. By one and <ex>th</ex>e same hande hath King <lb/>
            and people, binne hurt; and by <ex>th</ex>e same must bee cured. <lb/>
            To vindicate, what new thing <unclear>-</unclear>. Our antient sober, vitall <lb/>
            liberties, by reinforsing <ex>th</ex>e antient laws made by our Ancestors, <lb/>
            by selling such a character vppon them, as noe lisentious <lb/>
            spirit shall dare venter vppon them. And shall wee thinke <lb/>
            there is a way to breake a Parlament? Noe. Our desiers are <lb/>
            modest and iust; I speake truly both for <ex>th</ex>e intrest of King, and <lb/>
            people. If wee inioy not these, it is impossible to releiue him, <lb/>
            for let vs neuer feare <ex>tha</ex>t they should not bee accepted by his goodnesse <lb/>
            Therfore I shall descende to my motiues, consisting of fowre <lb/>
            parts, two of which haue relation to <ex>th</ex>e person, two to <ex>th</ex>e propriety of <lb/>
            goods. For our persons, <ex>th</ex>e Freedome of them first from Imprison <lb/>
            ment. Secondly from Imployment abrode contrary to <ex>th</ex>e antient <lb/>
            customes. For our goods that noe leuy might bee made but by <lb/>
            Parlament. Secondly that there bee noe billiting of Souldiers. <lb/>
            It is necessary that these bee resolued, that <ex>th</ex>e subieckt may bee <lb/>
            secured in booth: For <ex>th</ex>e manner in <ex>th</ex>e second place, it <lb/>
            will bee fitt to bee determined by a Grand Committee
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic n="1" url="/shc/1248_1/1248_1_4/1248_1_4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
</TEI>